Acts 4

1 And as they were speaking to the people, the priests and captain of the temple and the Sadducees came upon them, 2 being distressed on account of their teaching the people and preaching by Jesus the resurrection from among the dead; 3 and they laid hands on them, and put them in ward till the morrow; for it was already evening. 4 But many of those who had heard the word believed; and the number of the men had become about five thousand.

5 And it came to pass on the morrow that their rulers and elders and scribes were gathered together at Jerusalem, 6 and Annas the high priest, and Caiaphas, and John, and Alexander, and as many as were of the high priestly family; 7 and having placed them in the midst they inquired, In what power or in what name have ye done this? 8 Then Peter, filled with the Holy Spirit, said to them, Rulers of the people and elders of Israel, 9 if we this day are called upon to answer as to the good deed done to the infirm man, how he has been healed, 10 be it known to you all, and to all the people of Israel, that in the name of Jesus Christ the Nazaraean, whom ye have crucified, whom God has raised from among the dead, by him this man stands here before you sound in body. 11 He is the stone which has been set at nought by you the builders, which is become the corner stone. 12 And salvation is in none other, for neither is there another name under heaven which is given among men by which we must be saved. 13 But seeing the boldness of Peter and John, and perceiving that they were unlettered and uninstructed men, they wondered; and they recognised them that they were with Jesus. 14 And beholding the man who had been healed standing with them, they had nothing to reply;

15 but having commanded them to go out of the council they conferred with one another, 16 saying, What shall we do to these men? for that indeed an evident sign has come to pass through their means is manifest to all that inhabit Jerusalem, and we cannot deny it. 17 But that it be not further spread among the people, let us threaten them severely no longer to speak to any man in this name. 18 And having called them, they charged them not to speak at all nor teach in the name of Jesus. 19 But Peter and John answering said to them, If it be righteous before God to listen to you rather than to God, judge ye; 20 for as for us we cannot refrain from speaking of the things which we have seen and heard. 21 But they, having further threatened them, let them go, finding no way how they might punish them, on account of the people, because all glorified God for what had taken place; 22 for the man on whom this sign of healing had taken place was above forty years old.

23 And having been let go, they came to their own company, and reported all that the chief priests and elders had said to them. 24 And they, having heard it, lifted up their voice with one accord to God, and said, Lord, thou art the God who made the heaven and the earth and the sea, and all that is in them; 25 who hast said by the mouth of thy servant David, Why have the nations raged haughtily and the peoples meditated vain things? 26 The kings of the earth were there, and the rulers were gathered together against the Lord and against his Christ. 27 For in truth against thy holy servant Jesus, whom thou hadst anointed, both Herod and Pontius Pilate, with the nations, and peoples of Israel, have been gathered together in this city 28 to do whatever thy hand and thy counsel had determined before should come to pass. 29 And now, Lord, look upon their threatenings, and give to thy bondmen with all boldness to speak thy word, 30 in that thou stretchest out thy hand to heal, and that signs and wonders take place through the name of thy holy servant Jesus. 31 And when they had prayed, the place in which they were assembled shook, and they were all filled with the Holy Spirit, and spoke the word of God with boldness.

32 And the heart and soul of the multitude of those that had believed were one, and not one said that anything of what he possessed was his own, but all things were common to them; 33 and with great power did the apostles give witness of the resurrection of the Lord Jesus, and great grace was upon them all. 34 For neither was there any one in want among them; for as many as were owners of lands or houses, selling them, brought the price of what was sold 35 and laid it at the feet of the apostles; and distribution was made to each according as any one might have need. 36 And Joseph, who had been surnamed Barnabas by the apostles (which is, being interpreted, Son of consolation), a Levite, Cyprian by birth, 37 being possessed of land, having sold it, brought the money and laid it at the feet of the apostles.

Acts 5

1 But a certain man, Ananias by name, with Sapphira his wife, sold a possession, 2 and put aside for himself part of the price, his wife also being privy to it; and having brought a certain part, laid it at the feet of the apostles. 3 But Peter said, Ananias, why has Satan filled thy heart that thou shouldest lie to the Holy Spirit, and put aside for thyself a part of the price of the estate? 4 While it remained did it not remain to thee? and sold, was it not in thine own power? Why is it that thou hast purposed this thing in thine heart? Thou hast not lied to men, but to God. 5 And Ananias, hearing these words, fell down and expired. And great fear came upon all who heard it. 6 And the young men, rising up, swathed him up for burial, and having carried him out, buried him. 7 And it came to pass about three hours afterwards, that his wife, not knowing what had happened, came in. 8 And Peter answered her, Tell me if ye gave the estate for so much? And she said, Yes, for so much. 9 And Peter said to her, Why is it that ye have agreed together to tempt the Spirit of the Lord? Lo, the feet of those that have buried thy husband are at the door, and they shall carry thee out. 10 And she fell down immediately at his feet and expired. And when the young men came in they found her dead; and, having carried her out, they buried her by her husband. 11 And great fear came upon all the assembly, and upon all who heard these things.

12 And by the hands of the apostles were many signs and wonders done among the people; (and they were all with one accord in Solomon's porch, 13 but of the rest durst no man join them, but the people magnified them; 14 and believers were more than ever added to the Lord, multitudes both of men and women;) 15 so that they brought out the sick into the streets and put them on beds and couches, that at least the shadow of Peter, when he came, might overshadow some one of them. 16 And the multitude also of the cities round about came together to Jerusalem, bringing sick persons and persons beset by unclean spirits, who were all healed.

17 And the high priest rising up, and all they that were with him, which is the sect of the Sadducees, were filled with wrath, 18 and laid hands on the apostles and put them in the public prison. 19 But an angel of the Lord during the night opened the doors of the prison, and leading them out, said, 20 Go ye and stand and speak in the temple to the people all the words of this life. 21 And when they heard it, they entered very early into the temple and taught. And when the high priest was come, and they that were with him, they called together the council and all the elderhood of the sons of Israel, and sent to the prison to have them brought. 22 And when the officers were come, they did not find them in the prison; and returned and reported 23 saying, We found the prison shut with all security, and the keepers standing at the doors; but when we had opened them, within we found no one. 24 And when they heard these words, both the priest and the captain of the temple and the chief priests were in perplexity as to them, what this would come to. 25 And some one coming reported to them, Lo, the men whom ye put in the prison are in the temple, standing and teaching the people.

26 Then the captain, having gone with the officers, brought them, not with violence, for they feared the people, lest they should be stoned. 27 And they bring them and set them in the council. And the high priest asked them, 28 saying, We strictly enjoined you not to teach in this name: and lo, ye have filled Jerusalem with your doctrine, and purpose to bring upon us the blood of this man. 29 But Peter answering, and the apostles, said, God must be obeyed rather than men. 30 The God of our fathers has raised up Jesus, whom ye have slain, having hanged on a cross. 31 Him has God exalted by his right hand as leader and saviour, to give repentance to Israel and remission of sins. 32 And we are his witnesses of these things, and the Holy Spirit also, which God has given to those that obey him. 33 But they, when they heard these things, were cut to the heart, and took counsel to kill them. 34 But a certain man, a Pharisee, named Gamaliel, a teacher of the law, held in honour of all the people, rose up in the council, and commanded to put the men out for a short while, 35 and said to them, Men of Israel, take heed to yourselves as regards these men what ye are going to do; 36 for before these days Theudas rose up, alleging himself to be somebody, to whom a number of men, about four hundred, were joined; who was slain, and all, as many as obeyed him, were dispersed and came to nothing. 37 After him rose Judas the Galilean in the days of the census, and drew away a number of people after him; and he perished, and all, as many as obeyed him, were scattered abroad. 38 And now I say to you, Withdraw from these men and let them alone, for if this counsel or this work have its origin from men, it will be destroyed; 39 but if it be from God, ye will not be able to put them down, lest ye be found also fighters against God. 40 And they listened to his advice; and having called the apostles, they beat them, and enjoined them not to speak in the name of Jesus, and dismissed them. 41 They therefore went their way from the presence of the council, rejoicing that they were counted worthy to be dishonoured for the name. 42 And every day, in the temple and in the houses, they ceased not teaching and announcing the glad tidings that Jesus was the Christ.

Acts 6

1 But in those days, the disciples multiplying in number, there arose a murmuring of the Hellenists against the Hebrews because their widows were overlooked in the daily ministration. 2 And the twelve, having called the multitude of the disciples to them, said, It is not right that we, leaving the word of God, should serve tables. 3 Look out therefore, brethren, from among yourselves seven men, well reported of, full of the Holy Spirit and wisdom, whom we will establish over this business: 4 but we will give ourselves up to prayer and the ministry of the word. 5 And the saying pleased the whole multitude: and they chose Stephen, a man full of faith and the Holy Spirit, and Philip, and Prochorus, and Nicanor, and Timon, and Parmenas, and Nicolas, a proselyte of Antioch, 6 whom they set before the apostles; and, having prayed, they laid their hands on them. 7 And the word of God increased; and the number of the disciples in Jerusalem was very greatly multiplied, and a great crowd of the priests obeyed the faith.

8 And Stephen, full of grace and power, wrought wonders and great signs among the people. 9 And there arose up certain of those of the synagogue called of freedmen, and of Cyrenians, and of Alexandrians, and of those of Cilicia and Asia, disputing with Stephen. 10 And they were not able to resist the wisdom and the Spirit with which he spoke. 11 Then they suborned men, saying, We have heard him speaking blasphemous words against Moses and God. 12 And they roused the people, and the elders, and the scribes. And coming upon him they seized him and brought him to the council. 13 And they set false witnesses, saying, This man does not cease speaking words against the holy place and the law; 14 for we have heard him saying, This Jesus the Nazaraean shall destroy this place, and change the customs which Moses taught us. 15 And all who sat in the council, looking fixedly on him, saw his face as the face of an angel.

Acts 7

1 And the high priest said, Are these things then so? 2 And he said, Brethren and fathers, hearken. The God of glory appeared to our father Abraham when he was in Mesopotamia, before he dwelt in Charran, 3 and said to him, Go out of thy land and out of thy kindred, and come into the land which I will shew thee. 4 Then going out of the land of the Chaldeans he dwelt in Charran, and thence, after his father died, he removed him into this land in which ye now dwell. 5 And he did not give him an inheritance in it, not even what his foot could stand on; and promised to give it to him for a possession, and to his seed after him, when he had no child. 6 And God spoke thus: His seed shall be a sojourner in a strange land, and they shall enslave them and evil entreat them four hundred years; 7 and the nation to which they shall be in bondage will I judge, said God; and after these things they shall come forth and serve me in this place. 8 And he gave to him the covenant of circumcision; and thus he begat Isaac and circumcised him the eighth day; and Isaac Jacob, and Jacob the twelve patriarchs. 9 And the patriarchs, envying Joseph, sold him away into Egypt. And God was with him, 10 and delivered him out of all his tribulations, and gave him favour and wisdom in the sight of Pharaoh king of Egypt, and he appointed him chief over Egypt and all his house. 11 But a famine came upon all the land of Egypt and Canaan, and great distress, and our fathers found no food. 12 But Jacob, having heard of there being corn in Egypt, sent out our fathers first; 13 and the second time Joseph was made known to his brethren, and the family of Joseph became known to Pharaoh. 14 And Joseph sent and called down to him his father Jacob and all his kindred, seventy-five souls. 15 And Jacob went down into Egypt and died, he and our fathers, 16 and were carried over to Sychem and placed in the sepulchre which Abraham bought for a sum of money of the sons of Emmor the father of Sychem.

17 But as the time of promise drew near which God had promised to Abraham, the people increased and multiplied in Egypt, 18 until another king over Egypt arose who did not know Joseph. 19 He dealt subtilly with our race, and evil entreated the fathers, casting out their infants that they might not live. 20 In which time Moses was born, and was exceedingly lovely, who was nourished three months in the house of his father. 21 And when he was cast out, the daughter of Pharaoh took him up, and brought him up for herself to be for a son. 22 And Moses was instructed in all the wisdom of the Egyptians, and he was mighty in his words and deeds. 23 And when a period of forty years was fulfilled to him, it came into his heart to look upon his brethren, the sons of Israel; 24 and seeing a certain one wronged, he defended him, and avenged him that was being oppressed, smiting the Egyptian. 25 For he thought that his brethren would understand that God by his hand was giving them deliverance. But they understood not. 26 And on the morrow he shewed himself to them as they were contending, and compelled them to peace, saying, Ye are brethren, why do ye wrong one another? 27 But he that was wronging his neighbour thrust him away, saying, Who established thee ruler and judge over us? 28 Dost thou wish to kill me as thou killedst the Egyptian yesterday? 29 And Moses fled at this saying, and became a sojourner in the land of Madiam, where he begat two sons.

30 And when forty years were fulfilled, an angel appeared to him in the wilderness of mount Sinai, in a flame of fire of a bush. 31 And Moses seeing it wondered at the vision; and as he went up to consider it, there was a voice of the Lord, 32 I am the God of thy fathers, the God of Abraham, and of Isaac, and of Jacob. And Moses trembled, and durst not consider it. 33 And the Lord said to him, Loose the sandal of thy feet, for the place on which thou standest is holy ground. 34 I have surely seen the ill treatment of my people which is in Egypt, and I have heard their groan, and have come down to take them out of it; and now, come, I will send thee to Egypt. 35 This Moses, whom they refused, saying, Who made thee ruler and judge? him did God send to be a ruler and deliverer with the hand of the angel who appeared to him in the bush. 36 He led them out, having wrought wonders and signs in the land of Egypt, and in the Red sea, and in the wilderness forty years. 37 This is the Moses who said to the sons of Israel, A prophet shall God raise up to you out of your brethren like me him shall ye hear. 38 This is he who was in the assembly in the wilderness, with the angel who spoke to him in the mount Sinai, and with our fathers; who received living oracles to give to us; 39 to whom our fathers would not be subject, but thrust him from them, and in their hearts turned back to Egypt, 40 saying to Aaron, Make us gods who shall go before us; for this Moses, who brought us out of the land of Egypt, we know not what has happened to him. 41 And they made a calf in those days, and offered sacrifice to the idol, and rejoiced in the works of their own hands.

42 But God turned and delivered them up to serve the host of heaven; as it is written in the book of the prophets, Have ye offered me victims and sacrifices forty years in the wilderness, O house of Israel? 43 Yea, ye took up the tent of Moloch, and the star of your god Remphan, the forms which ye made to do homage to them; and I will transport you beyond Babylon. 44 Our fathers had the tent of the testimony in the wilderness, as he that spoke to Moses commanded to make it according to the model which he had seen; 45 which also our fathers, receiving from their predecessors, brought in with Joshua when they entered into possession of the lands of the nations, whom God drove out from the face of our fathers, until the days of David; 46 who found favour before God, and asked to find a tabernacle for the God of Jacob; 47 but Solomon built him a house. 48 But the Most High dwells not in places made with hands; as says the prophet, 49 The heaven is my throne and the earth the footstool of my feet: what house will ye build me? saith the Lord, or where is the place of my rest? 50 has not my hand made all these things?

51 O stiffnecked and uncircumcised in heart and ears, ye do always resist the Holy Spirit; as your fathers, ye also. 52 Which of the prophets have not your fathers persecuted? and they have slain those who announced beforehand concerning the coming of the Just One, of whom ye have now become deliverers up and murderers! 53 who have received the law as ordained by the ministry of angels, and have not kept it.

54 And hearing these things they were cut to the heart, and gnashed their teeth against him. 55 But being full of the Holy Spirit, having fixed his eyes on heaven, he saw the glory of God, and Jesus standing at the right hand of God, 56 and said, Lo, I behold the heavens opened, and the Son of man standing at the right hand of God. 57 And they cried out with a loud voice, and held their ears, and rushed upon him with one accord; 58 and having cast him out of the city, they stoned him. And the witnesses laid aside their clothes at the feet of a young man called Saul. 59 And they stoned Stephen, praying, and saying, Lord Jesus, receive my spirit. 60 And kneeling down, he cried with a loud voice, Lord, lay not this sin to their charge. And having said this, he fell asleep.

Acts 8

1 And Saul was consenting to his being killed. And on that day there arose a great persecution against the assembly which was in Jerusalem, and all were scattered into the countries of Judaea and Samaria except the apostles. 2 And pious men buried Stephen and made great lamentation over him. 3 But Saul ravaged the assembly, entering into the houses one after another, and dragging off both men and women delivered them up to prison.

4 Those then that had been scattered went through the countries announcing the glad tidings of the word. 5 And Philip, going down to a city of Samaria, preached the Christ to them; 6 and the crowds with one accord gave heed to the things spoken by Philip, when they heard him and saw the signs which he wrought. 7 For from many who had unclean spirits they went out, crying with a loud voice; and many that were paralysed and lame were healed. 8 And there was great joy in that city. 9 But a certain man, by name Simon, had been before in the city, using magic arts, and astonishing the nation of Samaria, saying that himself was some great one. 10 To whom they had all given heed, from small to great, saying, This is the power of God which is called great. 11 And they gave heed to him, because that for a long time he had astonished them by his magic arts. 12 But when they believed Philip announcing the glad tidings concerning the kingdom of God and the name of Jesus Christ, they were baptised, both men and women. 13 And Simon also himself believed; and, having been baptised, continued constantly with Philip; and, beholding the signs and great works of power which took place, was astonished.

14 And the apostles who were in Jerusalem, having heard that Samaria had received the word of God, sent to them Peter and John; 15 who, having come down, prayed for them that they might receive the Holy Spirit; 16 for he was not yet fallen upon any of them, only they were baptised to the name of the Lord Jesus. 17 Then they laid their hands upon them, and they received the Holy Spirit. 18 But Simon, having seen that by the laying on of the hands of the apostles the Holy Spirit was given, offered them money, 19 saying, Give to me also this power, in order that on whomsoever I may lay hands he may receive the Holy Spirit. 20 And Peter said to him, Thy money go with thee to destruction, because thou hast thought that the gift of God can be obtained by money. 21 Thou hast neither part nor lot in this matter, for thy heart is not upright before God. 22 Repent therefore of this thy wickedness, and supplicate the Lord, if indeed the thought of thy heart may be forgiven thee; 23 for I see thee to be in the gall of bitterness, and bond of unrighteousness. 24 And Simon answering said, Supplicate ye for me to the Lord, so that nothing may come upon me of the things of which ye have spoken. 25 They therefore, having testified and spoken the word of the Lord, returned to Jerusalem, and announced the glad tidings to many villages of the Samaritans.

26 But the angel of the Lord spoke to Philip, saying, Rise up and go southward on the way which goes down from Jerusalem to Gaza: the same is desert. 27 And he rose up and went. And lo, an Ethiopian, a eunuch, a man in power under Candace queen of the Ethiopians, who was over all her treasure, who had come to worship at Jerusalem, 28 was returning and sitting in his chariot: and he was reading the prophet Esaias. 29 And the Spirit said to Philip, Approach and join this chariot. 30 And Philip, running up, heard him reading the prophet Esaias, and said, Dost thou then know what thou art reading of? 31 And he said, How should I then be able unless some one guide me? And he begged Philip to come up and sit with him. 32 And the passage of the scripture which he read was this: He was led as a sheep to slaughter, and as a lamb is dumb in presence of him that shears him, thus he opens not his mouth. 33 In his humiliation his judgment has been taken away, and who shall declare his generation? for his life is taken from the earth. 34 And the eunuch answering Philip said, I pray thee, concerning whom does the prophet say this? of himself or of some other? 35 And Philip, opening his mouth and beginning from that scripture, announced the glad tidings of Jesus to him. 36 And as they went along the way, they came upon a certain water, and the eunuch says, Behold water; what hinders my being baptised?[*] 38 And he commanded the chariot to stop. And they went down both to the water, both Philip and the eunuch, and he baptised him. 39 But when they came up out of the water the Spirit of the Lord caught away Philip, and the eunuch saw him no longer, for he went on his way rejoicing. 40 And Philip was found at Azotus, and passing through he announced the glad tidings to all the cities till he came to Caesarea.

Ver. 37 in the Authorized Version is recognized as not genuine.

Acts 9

1 But Saul, still breathing out threatenings and slaughter against the disciples of the Lord, came to the high priest 2 and asked of him letters to Damascus, to the synagogues, so that if he found any who were of the way, both men and women, he might bring them bound to Jerusalem. 3 But as he was journeying, it came to pass that he drew near to Damascus; and suddenly there shone round about him a light out of heaven, 4 and falling on the earth he heard a voice saying to him, Saul, Saul, why dost thou persecute me? 5 And he said, Who art thou, Lord? And he said, I am Jesus, whom thou persecutest. 6 But rise up and enter into the city, and it shall be told thee what thou must do. 7 But the men who were travelling with him stood speechless, hearing the voice but beholding no one. 8 And Saul rose up from the earth, and his eyes being opened he saw no one. But leading him by the hand they brought him into Damascus. 9 And he was three days without seeing, and neither ate nor drank.

10 And there was a certain disciple in Damascus by name Ananias. And the Lord said to him in a vision, Ananias. And he said, Behold, here am I, Lord. 11 And the Lord said to him, Rise up and go into the street which is called Straight, and seek in the house of Judas one by name Saul, he is of Tarsus: for, behold, he is praying, 12 and has seen in a vision a man by name Ananias coming in and putting his hand on him, so that he should see. 13 And Ananias answered, Lord, I have heard from many concerning this man how much evil he has done to thy saints at Jerusalem; 14 and here he has authority from the chief priests to bind all who call upon thy name. 15 And the Lord said to him, Go, for this man is an elect vessel to me, to bear my name before both nations and kings and the sons of Israel: 16 for I will shew to him how much he must suffer for my name. 17 And Ananias went and entered into the house; and laying his hands upon him he said, Saul, brother, the Lord has sent me, Jesus that appeared to thee in the way in which thou camest, that thou mightest see, and be filled with theHoly Spirit. 18 And straightway there fell from his eyes as it were scales, and he saw, and rising up was baptised; 19 and, having received food, got strength. And he was with the disciples who were in Damascus certain days. 20 And straightway in the synagogues he preached Jesus that he is the Son of God. 21 And all who heard were astonished and said, Is not this he who destroyed in Jerusalem those who called on this name, and here was come for this purpose, that he might bring them bound to the chief priests? 22 But Saul increased the more in power, and confounded the Jews who dwelt in Damascus, proving that this is the Christ.

23 Now when many days were fulfilled, the Jews consulted together to kill him. 24 But their plot became known to Saul. And they watched also the gates both day and night, that they might kill him; 25 but the disciples took him by night and let him down through the wall, lowering him in a basket. 26 And having arrived at Jerusalem he essayed to join himself to the disciples, and all were afraid of him, not believing that he was a disciple. 27 But Barnabas took him and brought him to the apostles, and related to them how he had seen the Lord in the way, and that he had spoken to him, and how in Damascus he had spoken boldly in the name of Jesus. 28 And he was with them coming in and going out at Jerusalem, 29 and speaking boldly in the name of the Lord. And he spoke and discussed with the Hellenists; but they sought to kill him. 30 And the brethren knowing it, brought him down to Caesarea and sent him away to Tarsus. 31 The assemblies then throughout the whole of Judaea and Galilee and Samaria had peace, being edified and walking in the fear of the Lord, and were increased through the comfort of the Holy Spirit.

32 Now it came to pass that Peter, passing through all quarters, descended also to the saints who inhabited Lydda. 33 And he found there a certain man, Aeneas by name, who had been lying for eight years upon a couch, who was paralysed. 34 And Peter said to him, Aeneas, Jesus, the Christ, heals thee: rise up, and make thy couch for thyself. And straightway he rose up. 35 And all who inhabited Lydda and the Saron saw him, who turned to the Lord.

36 And in Joppa there was a certain female disciple, by name Tabitha, which being interpreted means Dorcas. She was full of good works and alms-deeds which she did. 37 And it came to pass in those days that she grew sick and died; and, having washed her, they put her in the upper room. 38 But Lydda being near to Joppa, the disciples having heard that Peter was there, sent two men to him, beseeching him, Thou must not delay coming to us. 39 And Peter rising up went with them, whom, when arrived, they brought up into the upper chamber; and all the widows stood by him weeping and shewing him the body-coats and garments which Dorcas had made while she was with them. 40 But Peter, putting them all out, and kneeling down, prayed. And, turning to the body, he said, Tabitha, arise. And she opened her eyes, and, seeing Peter, sat up. 41 And having given her his hand, he raised her up, and having called the saints and the widows, presented her living. 42 And it became known throughout the whole of Joppa, and many believed on the Lord. 43 And it came to pass that he remained many days in Joppa with a certain Simon, a tanner.

Acts 10

1 But a certain man in Caesarea, --by name Cornelius, a centurion of the band called Italic, 2 pious, and fearing God with all his house, both giving much alms to the people, and supplicating God continually, 3 --saw plainly in a vision, about the ninth hour of the day, an angel of God coming unto him, and saying to him, Cornelius. 4 But he, having fixed his eyes upon him, and become full of fear, said, What is it, Lord? And he said to him, Thy prayers and thine alms have gone up for a memorial before God. 5 And now send men to Joppa and fetch Simon, who is surnamed Peter. 6 He lodges with a certain Simon, a tanner, whose house is by the sea. 7 And when the angel who was speaking to him had departed, having called two of his household and a pious soldier of those who were constantly with him, 8 and related all things to them, he sent them to Joppa.

9 And on the morrow, as these were journeying and drawing near to the city, Peter went up on the house to pray, about the sixth hour. 10 And he became hungry and desired to eat. But as they were making ready an ecstasy came upon him: 11 and he beholds the heaven opened, and a certain vessel descending, as a great sheet, bound by the four corners and let down to the earth; 12 in which were all the quadrupeds and creeping things of the earth, and the fowls of the heaven. 13 And there was a voice to him, Rise, Peter, slay and eat. 14 And Peter said, In no wise, Lord; for I have never eaten anything common or unclean. 15 And there was a voice again the second time to him, What God has cleansed, do not thou make common. 16 And this took place thrice, and the vessel was straightway taken up into heaven. 17 And as Peter doubted in himself what the vision which he had seen might mean, behold also the men who were sent by Cornelius, having sought out the house of Simon, stood at the gate, 18 and having called some one, they inquired if Simon who was surnamed Peter was lodged there.

19 But as Peter continued pondering over the vision, the Spirit said to him, Behold, three men seek thee; 20 but rise up, go down, and go with them, nothing doubting, because I have sent them. 21 And Peter going down to the men said, Behold, I am he whom ye seek: what is the cause for which ye come? 22 And they said, Cornelius, a centurion, a righteous man, and fearing God, and borne witness to by the whole nation of the Jews, has been divinely instructed by a holy angel to send for thee to his house, and hear words from thee. 23 Having therefore invited them in, he lodged them. And on the morrow, rising up he went away with them, and certain of the brethren from Joppa went with him. 24 And on the morrow they came to Caesarea. But Cornelius was looking for them, having called together his kinsmen and his intimate friends. 25 And when Peter was now coming in, Cornelius met him, and falling down did him homage. 26 But Peter made him rise, saying, Rise up: I myself also am a man. 27 And he went in, talking with him, and found many gathered together. 28 And he said to them, Ye know how it is unlawful for a Jew to be joined or come to one of a strange race, and to me God has shewn to call no man common or unclean. 29 Wherefore also, having been sent for, I came without saying anything against it. I inquire therefore for what reason ye have sent for me. 30 And Cornelius said, Four days ago I had been fasting unto this hour, and the ninth I was praying in my house, and lo, a man stood before me in bright clothing, 31 and said, Cornelius, thy prayer has been heard, and thy alms have come in remembrance before God. 32 Send therefore to Joppa and fetch Simon, who is surnamed Peter; he lodges in the house of Simon, a tanner, by the sea who when he is come will speak to thee. 33 Immediately therefore I sent to thee, and thou hast well done in coming. Now therefore we are all present before God to hear all things that are commanded thee of God.

34 And Peter opening his mouth said, Of a truth I perceive that God is no respecter of persons, 35 but in every nation he that fears him and works righteousness is acceptable to him. 36 The word which he sent to the sons of Israel, preaching peace by Jesus Christ, (*he* is Lord of all things,) 37 ye know; the testimony which has spread through the whole of Judaea, beginning from Galilee after the baptism which John preached-- 38 Jesus who was of Nazareth: how God anointed him with the Holy Spirit and with power; who went through all quarters doing good, and healing all that were under the power of the devil, because God was with him. 39 We also are witnesses of all things which he did both in the country of the Jews and in Jerusalem; whom they also slew, having hanged him on a cross. 40 This man God raised up the third day and gave him to be openly seen, 41 not of all the people, but of witnesses who were chosen before of God, us who have eaten and drunk with him after he arose from among the dead. 42 And he commanded us to preach to the people, and to testify that he it is who was determinately appointed of God to be judge of living and dead. 43 To him all the prophets bear witness that every one that believes on him will receive through his name remission of sins.

44 While Peter was yet speaking these words the Holy Spirit fell upon all those who were hearing the word. 45 And the faithful of the circumcision were astonished, as many as came with Peter, that upon the nations also the gift of the Holy Spirit was poured out: 46 for they heard them speaking with tongues and magnifying God. Then Peter answered, 47 Can any one forbid water that these should not be baptised, who have received the Holy Spirit as we also did? 48 And he commanded them to be baptised in the name of the Lord. Then they begged him to stay some days.

Acts 11

1 And the apostles and the brethren who were in Judaea heard that the nations also had received the word of God; 2 and when Peter went up to Jerusalem, they of the circumcision contended with him, 3 saying, Thou wentest in to men uncircumcised and hast eaten with them. 4 But Peter began and set forth the matter to them in order, saying, 5 I was in the city of Joppa praying, and in an ecstasy I saw a vision, a certain vessel descending like a great sheet, let down by four corners out of heaven, and it came even to me: 6 on which having fixed mine eyes, I considered, and saw the quadrupeds of the earth, and the wild beasts, and the creeping things, and the fowls of the heaven. 7 And I heard also a voice saying to me, Rise up, Peter, slay and eat. 8 And I said, In no wise, Lord, for common or unclean has never entered into my mouth. 9 And a voice answered the second time out of heaven, What God has cleansed, do not thou make common. 10 And this took place thrice, and again all was drawn up into heaven; 11 and lo, immediately three men were at the house in which I was, sent to me from Caesarea. 12 And the Spirit said to me to go with them, nothing doubting. And there went with me these six brethren also, and we entered into the house of the man, 13 and he related to us how he had seen the angel in his house, standing and saying to him, Send men to Joppa and fetch Simon, who is surnamed Peter, 14 who shall speak words to thee whereby thou shalt be saved, thou and all thy house. 15 And as I began to speak, the Holy Spirit fell upon them even as upon us also at the beginning. 16 And I remembered the word of the Lord, how he said, John baptised with water, but ye shall be baptised with the Holy Spirit. 17 If then God has given them the same gift as also to us when we had believed on the Lord Jesus Christ, who indeed was I to be able to forbid God? 18 And when they heard these things they held their peace, and glorified God, saying, Then indeed God has to the nations also granted repentance to life.

19 They then who had been scattered abroad through the tribulation that took place on the occasion of Stephen, passed through the country to Phoenicia and Cyprus and Antioch, speaking the word to no one but to Jews alone. 20 But there were certain of them, Cyprians and Cyrenians, who entering into Antioch spoke to the Greeks also, announcing the glad tidings of the Lord Jesus. 21 And the Lord's hand was with them, and a great number believed and turned to the Lord. 22 And the report concerning them reached the ears of the assembly which was in Jerusalem, and they sent out Barnabas to go through as far as Antioch: 23 who, having arrived and seeing the grace of God, rejoiced, and exhorted all with purpose of heart to abide with the Lord; 24 for he was a good man and full of the Holy Spirit and of faith; and a large crowd of people were added to the Lord. 25 And he went away to Tarsus to seek out Saul. 26 And having found him, he brought him to Antioch. And so it was with them that for a whole year they were gathered together in the assembly and taught a large crowd: and the disciples were first called Christians in Antioch.

27 Now in these days prophets went down from Jerusalem to Antioch; 28 and one from among them, by name Agabus, rose up and signified by the Spirit that there was going to be a great famine over all the inhabited earth, which also came to pass under Claudius. 29 And they determined, according as any one of the disciples was well off, each of them to send to the brethren who dwelt in Judaea, to minister to them; 30 which also they did, sending it to the elders by the hand of Barnabas and Saul.

Acts 12

1 At that time Herod the king laid his hands on some of those of the assembly to do them hurt, 2 and slew James, the brother of John, with the sword. 3 And seeing that it was pleasing to the Jews, he went on to take Peter also: (and they were the days of unleavened bread:) 4 whom having seized he put in prison, having delivered him to four quaternions of soldiers to keep, purposing after the passover to bring him out to the people.

5 Peter therefore was kept in the prison; but unceasing prayer was made by the assembly to God concerning him. 6 And when Herod was going to bring him forth, that night Peter was sleeping between two soldiers, bound with two chains, and guards before the door kept the prison. 7 And lo, an angel of the Lord came there, and a light shone in the prison: and having smitten the side of Peter, he roused him up, saying, Rise up quickly. And his chains fell off his hands. 8 And the angel said to him, Gird thyself, and bind on thy sandals. And he did so. And he says to him, Cast thine upper garment about thee and follow me. 9 And going forth he followed him and did not know that what was happening by means of the angel was real, but supposed he saw a vision. 10 And having passed through a first and second guard, they came to the iron gate which leads into the city, which opened to them of itself; and going forth they went down one street, and immediately the angel left him. 11 And Peter, being come to himself, said, Now I know certainly that the Lord has sent forth his angel and has taken me out of the hand of Herod and all the expectation of the people of the Jews. 12 And having become clearly conscious in himself, he came to the house of Mary, the mother of John who was surnamed Mark, where were many gathered together and praying. 13 And when he had knocked at the door of the entry, a maid came to listen, by name Rhoda; 14 and having recognised the voice of Peter, through joy did not open the entry, but running in, reported that Peter was standing before the entry. 15 And they said to her, Thou art mad. But she maintained that it was so. And they said, It is his angel. 16 But Peter continued knocking: and having opened, they saw him and were astonished. 17 And having made a sign to them with his hand to be silent, he related to them how the Lord had brought him out of prison; and he said, Report these things to James and to the brethren. And he went out and went to another place. 18 And when it was day there was no small disturbance among the soldiers, what then was become of Peter. 19 And Herod having sought him and not found him, having examined the guards, commanded them to be executed. And he went down from Judaea to Caesarea and stayed there.

20 And he was in bitter hostility with the Tyrians and Sidonians; but they came to him with one accord, and, having gained Blastus the king's chamberlain, sought peace, because their country was nourished by the king's. 21 And on a set day, clothed in royal apparel and sitting on the elevated seat of honour, Herod made a public oration to them. 22 And the people cried out, A god's voice and not a man's. 23 And immediately an angel of the Lord smote him, because he did not give the glory to God, and he expired, eaten of worms. 24 But the word of God grew and spread itself. 25 And Barnabas and Saul returned from Jerusalem, having fulfilled the service entrusted to them, taking also with them John, surnamed Mark.

Acts 13

1 Now there were in Antioch, in the assembly which was there, prophets and teachers: Barnabas, and Simeon who was called Niger, and Lucius the Cyrenian, and Manaen, foster-brother of Herod the tetrarch, and Saul. 2 And as they were ministering to the Lord and fasting, the Holy Spirit said, Separate me now Barnabas and Saul for the work to which I have called them. 3 Then, having fasted and prayed, and having laid their hands on them, they let them go.

4 They therefore, having been sent forth by the Holy Spirit, went down to Seleucia, and thence sailed away to Cyprus. 5 And being in Salamis, they announced the word of God in the synagogues of the Jews. And they had John also as their attendant. 6 And having passed through the whole island as far as Paphos, they found a certain man a magician, a false prophet, a Jew, whose name was Bar-jesus, 7 who was with the proconsul Sergius Paulus, an intelligent man. He, having called Barnabas and Saul to him, desired to hear the word of God. 8 But Elymas the magician (for so his name is by interpretation) opposed them, seeking to turn away the proconsul from the faith. 9 But Saul, who also is Paul, filled with the Holy Spirit, fixing his eyes upon him, 10 said, O full of all deceit and all craft: son of the devil, enemy of all righteousness; wilt thou not cease perverting the right paths of the Lord? 11 And now behold, the Lord's hand is upon thee, and thou shalt be blind, not seeing the sun for a season. And immediately there fell upon him a mist and darkness; and going about he sought persons who should lead him by the hand. 12 Then the proconsul, seeing what had happened, believed, being amazed at the teaching of the Lord. 13 And having sailed from Paphos, Paul and his company came to Perga of Pamphylia; and John separated from them and returned to Jerusalem.

14 But they, passing through from Perga, came to Antioch of Pisidia; and entering into the synagogue on the sabbath day they sat down. 15 And after the reading of the law and the prophets, the rulers of the synagogue sent to them, saying, Brethren, if ye have any word of exhortation to the people, speak. 16 And Paul, rising up and making a sign with the hand, said, Israelites, and ye that fear God, hearken. 17 The God of this people Israel chose our fathers, and exalted the people in their sojourn in the land of Egypt, and with a high arm brought them out of it, 18 and for a time of about forty years he nursed them in the desert. 19 And having destroyed seven nations in the land of Canaan, he gave them their land as an inheritance. 20 And after these things he gave them judges till Samuel the prophet, to the end of about four hundred and fifty years. 21 And then they asked for a king, and God gave to them Saul, son of Kis, a man of the tribe of Benjamin, during forty years. 22 And having removed him he raised up to them David for king, of whom also bearing witness he said, I have found David, the son of Jesse, a man after my heart, who shall do all my will. 23 Of this man's seed according to promise has God brought to Israel a Saviour, Jesus; 24 John having proclaimed before the face of his entry among the people the baptism of repentance to all the people of Israel. 25 And as John was fulfilling his course he said, Whom do ye suppose that I am? I am not he. But behold, there comes one after me, the sandal of whose feet I am not worthy to loose. 26 Brethren, sons of Abraham's race, and those who among you fear God, to you has the word of this salvation been sent: 27 for those who dwell in Jerusalem, and their rulers, not having known him, have fulfilled also the voices of the prophets which are read on every sabbath, by judging him. 28 And having found no cause of death in him, they begged of Pilate that he might be slain. 29 And when they had fulfilled all things written concerning him, they took him down from the cross and put him in a sepulchre; 30 but God raised him from among the dead, 31 who appeared for many days to those who had come up with him from Galilee to Jerusalem, who are now his witnesses to the people. 32 And we declare unto you the glad tidings of the promise made to the fathers, 33 that God has fulfilled this to us their children, having raised up Jesus; as it is also written in the second psalm, Thou art my Son: this day have I begotten thee. 34 But that he raised him from among the dead, no more to return to corruption, he spoke thus: I will give to you the faithful mercies of David. 35 Wherefore also he says in another, Thou wilt not suffer thy gracious one to see corruption. 36 For David indeed, having in his own generation ministered to the will of God, fell asleep, and was added to his fathers and saw corruption. 37 But he whom God raised up did not see corruption. 38 Be it known unto you, therefore, brethren, that through this man remission of sins is preached to you, 39 and from all things from which ye could not be justified in the law of Moses, in him every one that believes is justified. 40 See therefore that that which is spoken in the prophets do not come upon you, 41 Behold, ye despisers, and wonder and perish; for I work a work in your days, a work which ye will in no wise believe if one declare it to you.

42 And as they went out they begged that these words might be spoken to them the ensuing sabbath. 43 And the congregation of the synagogue having broken up, many of the Jews and of the worshipping proselytes followed Paul and Barnabas, who speaking to them, persuaded them to continue in the grace of God. 44 And on the coming sabbath almost all the city was gathered together to hear the word of God. 45 But the Jews, seeing the crowds, were filled with envy, and contradicted the things said by Paul, contradicting and speaking injuriously. 46 And Paul and Barnabas spoke boldly and said, It was necessary that the word of God should be first spoken to you; but, since ye thrust it from you, and judge yourselves unworthy of eternal life, lo, we turn to the nations; 47 for thus has the Lord enjoined us: I have set thee for a light of the nations, that thou shouldest be for salvation to the end of the earth. 48 And those of the nations, hearing it, rejoiced, and glorified the word of the Lord, and believed, as many as were ordained to eternal life. 49 And the word of the Lord was carried through the whole country. 50 But the Jews excited the women of the upper classes who were worshippers, and the first people of the city, and raised a persecution against Paul and Barnabas, and cast them out of their coasts. 51 But they, having shaken off the dust of their feet against them, came to Iconium. 52 And the disciples were filled with joy and the Holy Spirit.

Acts 14

1 And it came to pass in Iconium that they entered together into the synagogue of the Jews, and so spake that a great multitude of both Jews and Greeks believed. 2 But the Jews who did not believe stirred up the minds of those of the nations and made them evil-affected against the brethren. 3 They stayed therefore a good while, speaking boldly, confiding in the Lord, who gave witness to the word of his grace, giving signs and wonders to be done by their hands. 4 And the multitude of the city was divided, and some were with the Jews and some with the apostles. 5 And when an assault was making, both of those of the nations and the Jews with their rulers, to use them ill and stone them, 6 they, being aware of it, fled to the cities of Lycaonia, Lystra and Derbe, and the surrounding country, 7 and there they were announcing the glad tidings.

8 And a certain man in Lystra, impotent in his feet, sat, being lame from his mother's womb, who had never walked. 9 This man heard Paul speaking, who, fixing his eyes on him, and seeing that he had faith to be healed, 10 said with a loud voice, Rise up straight upon thy feet: and he sprang up and walked. 11 But the crowds, who saw what Paul had done, lifted up their voices in Lycaonian, saying, The gods, having made themselves like men, are come down to us. 12 And they called Barnabas Jupiter, and Paul Mercury, because he took the lead in speaking. 13 And the priest of Jupiter who was before the city, having brought bulls and garlands to the gates, would have done sacrifice along with the crowds. 14 But the apostles Barnabas and Paul, having heard it, rent their garments, and rushed out to the crowd, crying 15 and saying, Men, why do ye these things? We also are men of like passions with you, preaching to you to turn from these vanities to the living God, who made the heaven, and the earth, and the sea, and all things in them; 16 who in the past generations suffered all the nations to go in their own ways, 17 though indeed he did not leave himself without witness, doing good, and giving to you from heaven rain and fruitful seasons, filling your hearts with food and gladness. 18 And saying these things, they with difficulty kept the crowds from sacrificing to them.

19 But there came Jews from Antioch and Iconium, and having persuaded the crowds and stoned Paul, drew him out of the city, supposing him to have died. 20 But while the disciples encircled him, he rose up and entered into the city. And on the morrow he went away with Barnabas to Derbe. 21 And having announced the glad tidings to that city, and having made many disciples, they returned to Lystra, and Iconium, and Antioch, 22 establishing the souls of the disciples, exhorting them to abide in the faith, and that through many tribulations we must enter into the kingdom of God. 23 And having chosen them elders in each assembly, having prayed with fastings, they committed them to the Lord, on whom they had believed. 24 And having passed through Pisidia they came to Pamphylia, 25 and having spoken the word in Perga, they came down to Attalia; 26 and thence they sailed away to Antioch, whence they had been committed to the grace of God for the work which they had fulfilled. 27 And having arrived, and having brought together the assembly, they related to them all that God had done with them, and that he had opened a door of faith to the nations. 28 And they stayed no little time with the disciples.

Acts 15

1 And certain persons, having come down from Judaea, taught the brethren, If ye shall not have been circumcised according to the custom of Moses, ye cannot be saved. 2 A commotion therefore having taken place, and no small discussion on the part of Paul and Barnabas against them, they arranged that Paul and Barnabas, and certain others from amongst them, should go up to Jerusalem to the apostles and elders about this question. 3 They therefore, having been set on their way by the assembly, passed through Phoenicia and Samaria, relating the conversion of those of the nations. And they caused great joy to all the brethren. 4 And being arrived at Jerusalem, they were received by the assembly, and the apostles, and the elders, and related all that God had wrought with them. 5 And some of those who were of the sect of the Pharisees, who believed, rose up from among them, saying that they ought to circumcise them and enjoin them to keep the law of Moses.

6 And the apostles and the elders were gathered together to see about this matter. 7 And much discussion having taken place, Peter, standing up, said to them, Brethren, ye know that from the earliest days God amongst you chose that the nations by my mouth should hear the word of the glad tidings and believe. 8 And the heart-knowing God bore them witness, giving them the Holy Spirit as to us also, 9 and put no difference between us and them, having purified their hearts by faith. 10 Now therefore why tempt ye God, by putting a yoke upon the neck of the disciples, which neither our fathers nor we have been able to bear? 11 But we believe that we shall be saved by the grace of the Lord Jesus, in the same manner as they also. 12 And all the multitude kept silence and listened to Barnabas and Paul relating all the signs and wonders which God had wrought among the nations by them. 13 And after they had held their peace, James answered, saying, Brethren, listen to me: 14 Simon has related how God first visited to take out of the nations a people for his name. 15 And with this agree the words of the prophets; as it is written: 16 After these things I will return, and will rebuild the tabernacle of David which is fallen, and will rebuild its ruins, and will set it up, 17 so that the residue of men may seek out the Lord, and all the nations on whom my name is invoked, saith the Lord, who does these things 18 known from eternity. 19 Wherefore I judge, not to trouble those who from the nations turn to God; 20 but to write to them to abstain from pollutions of idols, and from fornication, and from what is strangled, and from blood. 21 For Moses, from generations of old, has in every city those who preach him, being read in the synagogues every sabbath.

22 Then it seemed good to the apostles and to the elders, with the whole assembly, to send chosen men from among them with Paul and Barnabas to Antioch, Judas called Barsabas and Silas, leading men among the brethren, 23 having by their hand written thus: The apostles, and the elders, and the brethren, to the brethren who are from among the nations at Antioch, and in Syria and Cilicia, greeting: 24 Inasmuch as we have heard that some who went out from amongst us have troubled you by words, upsetting your souls, saying that ye must be circumcised and keep the law; to whom we gave no commandment; 25 it seemed good to us, having arrived at a common judgment, to send chosen men to you with our beloved Barnabas and Paul, 26 men who have given up their lives for the name of our Lord Jesus Christ. 27 We have therefore sent Judas and Silas, who themselves also will tell you by word of mouth the same things. 28 For it has seemed good to the Holy Spirit and to us to lay upon you no greater burden than these necessary things: 29 to abstain from things sacrificed to idols, and from blood, and from what is strangled, and from fornication; keeping yourselves from which ye will do well. Farewell. 30 They therefore, being let go, came to Antioch, and having gathered the multitude delivered to them the epistle. 31 And having read it, they rejoiced at the consolation. 32 And Judas and Silas, being themselves also prophets, exhorted the brethren with much discourse, and strengthened them. 33 And having passed some time there, they were let go in peace from the brethren to those who sent them.[*] 35 And Paul and Barnabas stayed in Antioch, teaching and announcing the glad tidings, with many others also, of the word of the Lord.

36 But after certain days Paul said to Barnabas, Let us return now and visit the brethren in every city where we have announced the word of the Lord, and see how they are getting on. 37 And Barnabas proposed to take with them John also, called Mark; 38 but Paul thought it not well to take with them him who had abandoned them, going back from Pamphylia, and had not gone with them to the work. 39 There arose therefore very warm feeling, so that they separated from one another; and Barnabas taking Mark sailed away to Cyprus; 40 but Paul having chosen Silas went forth, committed by the brethren to the grace of God. 41 And he passed through Syria and Cilicia, confirming the assemblies.

Ver. 34 of A.V. is not in the best MSS.

Acts 17

1 And having journeyed through Amphipolis and Apollonia, they came to Thessalonica, where was the synagogue of the Jews. 2 And according to Paul's custom he went in among them, and on three sabbaths reasoned with them from the scriptures, 3 opening and laying down that the Christ must have suffered and risen up from among the dead, and that this is the Christ, Jesus whom I announce to you. 4 And some of them believed, and joined themselves to Paul and Silas, and of the Greeks who worshipped, a great multitude, and of the chief women not a few. 5 But the Jews having been stirred up to jealousy, and taken to themselves certain wicked men of the lowest rabble, and having got a crowd together, set the city in confusion; and having beset the house of Jason sought to bring them out to the people; 6 and not having found them, dragged Jason and certain brethren before the politarchs, crying out, These men that have set the world in tumult, are come here also, 7 whom Jason has received; and these all do contrary to the decrees of Caesar, saying, that there is another king, Jesus. 8 And they troubled the crowd and the politarchs when they heard these things. 9 And having taken security of Jason and the rest, they let them go.

10 But the brethren immediately sent away, in the night, Paul and Silas to Berea; who, being arrived, went away into the synagogue of the Jews. 11 And these were more noble than those in Thessalonica, receiving the word with all readiness of mind, daily searching the scriptures if these things were so. 12 Therefore many from among them believed, and of Grecian women of the upper classes and men not a few. 13 But when the Jews from Thessalonica knew that the word of God was announced in Berea also by Paul, they came there also, stirring up the crowds. 14 And then immediately the brethren sent away Paul to go as to the sea; but Silas and Timotheus abode there. 15 But they that conducted Paul brought him as far as Athens; and, having received a commandment to Silas and Timotheus, that they should come to him as quickly as possible, they departed.

16 But in Athens, while Paul was waiting for them, his spirit was painfully excited in him seeing the city given up to idolatry. 17 He reasoned therefore in the synagogue with the Jews, and those who worshipped, and in the market-place every day with those he met with. 18 But some also of the Epicurean and Stoic philosophers attacked him. And some said, What would this chatterer say? and some, He seems to be an announcer of foreign demons, because he announced the glad tidings of Jesus and the resurrection to them. 19 And having taken hold on him they brought him to Areopagus, saying, Might we know what this new doctrine which is spoken by thee is? 20 For thou bringest certain strange things to our ears. We wish therefore to know what these things may mean. 21 Now all the Athenians and the strangers sojourning there spent their time in nothing else than to tell and to hear the news.

22 And Paul standing in the midst of Areopagus said, Athenians, in every way I see you given up to demon worship; 23 for, passing through and beholding your shrines, I found also an altar on which was inscribed, To the unknown God. Whom therefore ye reverence, not knowing him, him I announce to you. 24 The God who has made the world and all things which are in it, he, being Lord of heaven and earth, does not dwell in temples made with hands, 25 nor is served by men's hands as needing something, himself giving to all life and breath and all things; 26 and has made of one blood every nation of men to dwell upon the whole face of the earth, having determined ordained times and the boundaries of their dwelling, 27 that they may seek God; if indeed they might feel after him and find him, although he is not far from each one of us: 28 for in him we live and move and exist; as also some of the poets amongst you have said, For we are also his offspring. 29 Being therefore the offspring of God, we ought not to think that which is divine to be like gold or silver or stone, the graven form of man's art and imagination. 30 God therefore, having overlooked the times of ignorance, now enjoins men that they shall all everywhere repent, 31 because he has set a day in which he is going to judge the habitable earth in righteousness by the man whom he has appointed, giving the proof of it to all in having raised him from among the dead.

32 And when they heard of the resurrection of the dead, some mocked, and some said, We will hear thee again also concerning this. 33 Thus Paul went out of their midst. 34 But some men joining themselves to him believed; among whom also was Dionysius the Areopagite, and a woman by name Damaris, and others with them.

Acts 18

1 And after these things, having left Athens, he came to Corinth; 2 and finding a certain Jew by name Aquila, of Pontus by race, just come from Italy, and Priscilla his wife, (because Claudius had ordered all the Jews to leave Rome,) came to them, 3 and because they were of the same trade abode with them, and wrought. For they were tent-makers by trade. 4 And he reasoned in the synagogue every sabbath, and persuaded Jews and Greeks. 5 And when both Silas and Timotheus came down from Macedonia, Paul was pressed in respect of the word, testifying to the Jews that Jesus was the Christ. 6 But as they opposed and spoke injuriously, he shook his clothes, and said to them, Your blood be upon your own head: I am pure; from henceforth I will go to the nations.

7 And departing thence he came to the house of a certain man, by name Justus, who worshipped God, whose house adjoined the synagogue. 8 But Crispus the ruler of the synagogue believed in the Lord with all his house; and many of the Corinthians hearing, believed, and were baptised. 9 And the Lord said by vision in the night to Paul, Fear not, but speak and be not silent; 10 because I am with thee, and no one shall set upon thee to injure thee; because I have much people in this city. 11 And he remained there a year and six months, teaching among them the word of God.

12 But when Gallio was proconsul of Achaia, the Jews with one consent rose against Paul and led him to the judgment-seat, 13 saying, This man persuades men to worship God contrary to the law. 14 But as Paul was going to open his mouth, Gallio said to the Jews, If indeed it was some wrong or wicked criminality, O Jews, of reason I should have borne with you; 15 but if it be questions about words, and names, and the law that ye have, see to it yourselves; forI do not intend to be judge of these things. 16 And he drove them from the judgment-seat. 17 And having all laid hold on Sosthenes the ruler of the synagogue, they beat him before the judgment-seat. And Gallio troubled himself about none of these things.

18 And Paul, having yet stayed there many days, took leave of the brethren and sailed thence to Syria, and with him Priscilla and Aquila, having shorn his head in Cenchrea, for he had a vow; 19 and he arrived at Ephesus, and left them there. But entering himself into the synagogue he reasoned with the Jews. 20 And when they asked him that he would remain for a longer time with them he did not accede, 21 but bade them farewell, saying, I must by all means keep the coming feast at Jerusalem; I will return to you again, if God will: and he sailed away from Ephesus. 22 And landing at Caesarea, and having gone up and saluted the assembly, he went down to Antioch. 23 And having stayed there some time, he went forth, passing in order through the country of Galatia and Phrygia, establishing all the disciples.

24 But a certain Jew, Apollos by name, an Alexandrian by race, an eloquent man, who was mighty in the scriptures, arrived at Ephesus. 25 He was instructed in the way of the Lord, and being fervent in his spirit, he spoke and taught exactly the things concerning Jesus, knowing only the baptism of John. 26 And he began to speak boldly in the synagogue. And Aquila and Priscilla, having heard him, took him to them and unfolded to him the way of God more exactly. 27 And when he purposed to go into Achaia, the brethren wrote to the disciples engaging them to receive him, who, being come, contributed much to those who believed through grace. 28 For he with great force convinced the Jews publicly, shewing by the scriptures that Jesus was the Christ.

Acts 19

1 And it came to pass, while Apollos was at Corinth, Paul, having passed through the upper districts, came to Ephesus, and finding certain disciples, 2 he said to them, Did ye receive the Holy Spirit when ye had believed? And they said to him, We did not even hear if the Holy Spirit was come. 3 And he said, To what then were ye baptised? And they said, To the baptism of John. 4 And Paul said, John indeed baptised with the baptism of repentance, saying to the people that they should believe on him that was coming after him, that is, on Jesus. 5 And when they heard that, they were baptised to the name of the Lord Jesus. 6 And Paul having laid his hands on them, the Holy Spirit came upon them, and they spoke with tongues and prophesied. 7 And all the men were about twelve.

8 And entering into the synagogue, he spoke boldly during three months, reasoning and persuading the things concerning the kingdom of God. 9 But when some were hardened and disbelieved, speaking evil of the way before the multitude, he left them and separated the disciples, reasoning daily in the school of Tyrannus. 10 And this took place for two years, so that all that inhabited Asia heard the word of the Lord, both Jews and Greeks. 11 And God wrought no ordinary miracles by the hands of Paul, 12 so that even napkins or aprons were brought from his body and put upon the sick, and the diseases left them, and the wicked spirits went out.

13 And certain of the Jewish exorcists also, who went about, took in hand to call upon those who had wicked spirits the name of the Lord Jesus, saying, I adjure you by Jesus, whom Paul preaches. 14 And there were certain men, seven sons of Sceva, Jewish high priest, who were doing this. 15 But the wicked spirit answering said to them, Jesus I know, and Paul I am acquainted with; but ye, who are ye? 16 And the man in whom the wicked spirit was leaped upon them, and having mastered both, prevailed against them, so that they fled out of that house naked and wounded. 17 And this became known to all, both Jews and Greeks, who inhabited Ephesus, and fear fell upon all of them, and the name of the Lord Jesus was magnified. 18 And many of those that believed came confessing and declaring their deeds. 19 And many of those that practised curious arts brought their books of charms and burnt them before all. And they reckoned up the prices of them, and found it fifty thousand pieces of silver. 20 Thus with might the word of the Lord increased and prevailed.

21 And when these things were fulfilled, Paul purposed in his spirit to go to Jerusalem, passing through Macedonia and Achaia, saying, After I have been there I must see Rome also. 22 And having sent into Macedonia two of those ministering to him, Timotheus and Erastus, he remained himself awhile in Asia. 23 And there took place at that time no small disturbance about the way. 24 For a certain man by name Demetrius, a silver-beater, making silver temples of Artemis, brought no small gain to the artisans; 25 whom having brought together, and those who wrought in such things, he said, Men, ye know that our well-living arises from this work, 26 and ye see and hear that this Paul has persuaded and turned away a great crowd, not only of Ephesus, but almost of all Asia, saying that they are no gods which are made with hands. 27 Now not only there is danger for us that our business come into discredit, but also that the temple of the great goddess Artemis be counted for nothing, and that her greatness should be destroyed whom the whole of Asia and the world reveres. 28 And having heard this, and being filled with rage, they cried out, saying, Great is Artemis of the Ephesians. 29 And the whole city was filled with confusion, and they rushed with one accord to the theatre, having seized and carried off with them Gaius and Aristarchus, Macedonians, fellow-travellers of Paul. 30 But Paul intending to go in to the people, the disciples suffered him not; 31 and some of the Asiarchs also, who were his friends, sent to him and urged him not to throw himself into the theatre. 32 Different persons therefore cried out some different thing; for the assembly was tumultuous, and the most did not know for what cause they had come together. 33 But from among the crowd they put forward Alexander, the Jews pushing him forward. And Alexander, beckoning with his hand, would have made a defence to the people. 34 But, recognising that he was a Jew, there was one cry from all, shouting for about two hours, Great is Artemis of the Ephesians. 35 And the townclerk, having quieted the crowd, said, Ephesians, what man is there then who does not know that the city of the Ephesians is temple-keeper of Artemis the great, and of the image which fell down from heaven? 36 These things therefore being undeniable, it is necessary that ye should be calm and do nothing headlong. 37 For ye have brought these men, who are neither temple-plunderers, nor speak injuriously of your goddess. 38 If therefore Demetrius and the artisans who are with him have a matter against any one, the courts are being held, and there are proconsuls: let them accuse one another. 39 But if ye inquire anything concerning other matters, it will be settled in the regular assembly. 40 For also we are in danger to be put in accusation for sedition for this affair of to-day, no cause existing in reference to which we shall be able to give a reason for this concourse. 41 And having said these things, he dismissed the assembly.

Acts 20

1 But after the tumult had ceased, Paul having called the disciples to him and embraced them, went away to go to Macedonia. 2 And having passed through those parts, and having exhorted them with much discourse, he came to Greece. 3 And having spent three months there, a treacherous plot against him having been set on foot by the Jews, as he was going to sail to Syria, the resolution was adopted of returning through Macedonia. 4 And there accompanied him as far as Asia, Sopater son of Pyrrhus, a Berean; and of Thessalonians, Aristarchus and Secundus, and Gaius and Timotheus of Derbe, and of Asia, Tychicus and Trophimus. 5 These going before waited for us in Troas; 6 but we sailed away from Philippi after the days of unleavened bread, and we came to them to Troas in five days, where we spent seven days.

7 And the first day of the week, we being assembled to break bread, Paul discoursed to them, about to depart on the morrow. And he prolonged the discourse till midnight. 8 And there were many lights in the upper room where we were assembled. 9 And a certain youth, by name Eutychus, sitting at the window-opening, overpowered by deep sleep, while Paul discoursed very much at length, having been overpowered by the sleep, fell from the third story down to the bottom, and was taken up dead. 10 But Paul descending fell upon him, and enfolding him in his arms, said, Be not troubled, for his life is in him. 11 And having gone up, and having broken the bread, and eaten, and having long spoken until daybreak, so he went away. 12 And they brought away the boy alive, and were no little comforted.

13 And we, having gone before on board ship, sailed off to Assos, going to take in Paul there; for so he had directed, he himself being about to go on foot. 14 And when he met with us at Assos, having taken him on board, we came to Mitylene; 15 and having sailed thence, on the morrow arrived opposite Chios, and the next day put in at Samos; and having stayed at Trogyllium, the next day we came to Miletus: 16 for Paul thought it desirable to sail by Ephesus, so that he might not be made to spend time in Asia; for he hastened, if it was possible for him, to be the day of Pentecost at Jerusalem.

17 But from Miletus having sent to Ephesus, he called over to him the elders of the assembly. 18 And when they were come to him, he said to them, Ye know how I was with you all the time from the first day that I arrived in Asia, 19 serving the Lord with all lowliness, and tears, and temptations, which happened to me through the plots of the Jews; 20 how I held back nothing of what is profitable, so as not to announce it to you, and to teach you publicly and in every house, 21 testifying to both Jews and Greeks repentance towards God, and faith towards our Lord Jesus Christ. 22 And now, behold, bound in my spirit I go to Jerusalem, not knowing what things shall happen to me in it; 23 only that the Holy Spirit testifies to me in every city, saying that bonds and tribulations await me. 24 But I make no account of my life as dear to myself, so that I finish my course, and the ministry which I have received of the Lord Jesus, to testify the glad tidings of the grace of God. 25 And now, behold, I know that ye all, among whom I have gone about preaching the kingdom of God, shall see my face no more. 26 Wherefore I witness to you this day, that I am clean from the blood of all, 27 for I have not shrunk from announcing to you all the counsel of God. 28 Take heed therefore to yourselves, and to all the flock, wherein the Holy Spirit has set you as overseers, to shepherd the assembly of God, which he has purchased with the blood of his own. 29 ForI know this, that there will come in amongst you after my departure grievous wolves, not sparing the flock; 30 and from among your own selves shall rise up men speaking perverted things to draw away the disciples after them. 31 Wherefore watch, remembering that for three years, night and day, I ceased not admonishing each one of you with tears. 32 And now I commit you to God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to build you up and give to you an inheritance among all the sanctified. 33 I have coveted the silver or gold or clothing of no one. 34 Yourselves know that these hands have ministered to my wants, and to those who were with me. 35 I have shewed you all things, that thus labouring we ought to come in aid of the weak, and to remember the words of the Lord Jesus, that he himself said, It is more blessed to give than to receive.

36 And having said these things, he knelt down and prayed with them all. 37 And they all wept sore; and falling upon the neck of Paul they ardently kissed him, 38 specially pained by the word which he had said, that they would no more see his face. And they went down with him to the ship.

Acts 21

1 And when, having got away from them, we at last sailed away, we came by a direct course to Cos, and on the morrow to Rhodes, and thence to Patara. 2 And having found a ship passing over into Phoenicia, we went on board and sailed; 3 and having sighted Cyprus, and left it on the left hand, we sailed to Syria, and made the land at Tyre, for there the ship was to discharge her cargo. 4 And having found out the disciples, we remained there seven days; who said to Paul by the Spirit not to go up to Jerusalem. 5 But when we had completed the days, we set out and took our journey, all of them accompanying us, with wives and children, till we were out of the city. And kneeling down upon the shore we prayed. 6 And having embraced one another, we went on board ship, and they returned home. 7 And we, having completed the voyage, arrived from Tyre at Ptolemais, and having saluted the brethren, we remained one day with them.

8 And leaving on the morrow, we came to Caesarea; and entering into the house of Philip the evangelist, who was of the seven, we abode with him. 9 Now this man had four virgin daughters who prophesied. 10 And as we stayed there many days, a certain man, by name Agabus, a prophet, came down from Judaea, 11 and coming to us and taking the girdle of Paul, and having bound his own hands and feet, said, Thus saith the Holy Spirit, The man whose this girdle is shall the Jews thus bind in Jerusalem, and deliver him up into the hands of the Gentiles. 12 And when we heard these things, both we and those of the place besought him not to go up to Jerusalem. 13 But Paul answered, What do ye, weeping and breaking my heart? for I am ready not only to be bound, but also to die at Jerusalem for the name of the Lord Jesus. 14 And when he would not be persuaded, we were silent, saying, The will of the Lord be done.

15 And after these days, having got our effects ready, we went up to Jerusalem. 16 And some of the disciples from Caesarea went with us, bringing with them a certain Mnason, a Cyprian, an old disciple, with whom we were to lodge. 17 And when we arrived at Jerusalem the brethren gladly received us. 18 And on the morrow Paul went in with us to James, and all the elders came there. 19 And having saluted them, he related one by one the things which God had wrought among the nations by his ministry. 20 And they having heard it glorified God, and said to him, Thou seest, brother, how many myriads there are of the Jews who have believed, and all are zealous of the law. 21 And they have been informed concerning thee, that thou teachest all the Jews among the nations apostasy from Moses, saying that they should not circumcise their children, nor walk in the customs. 22 What is it then? a multitude must necessarily come together, for they will hear that thou art come. 23 This do therefore that we say to thee: We have four men who have a vow on them; 24 take these and be purified with them, and pay their expenses, that they may have their heads shaved; and all will know that of those things of which they have been informed about thee nothing is true; but that thou thyself also walkest orderly, keeping the law. 25 But concerning those of the nations who have believed, we have written, deciding that they should observe no such thing, only to keep themselves both from things offered to idols, and from blood, and from things strangled, and from fornication. 26 Then Paul, taking the men, on the next day, having been purified, entered with them into the temple, signifying the time the days of the purification would be fulfilled, until the offering was offered for every one of them.

27 And when the seven days were nearly completed, the Jews from Asia, having seen him in the temple, set all the crowd in a tumult, and laid hands upon him, 28 crying, Israelites, help! this is the man who teaches all everywhere against the people, and the law, and this place, and has brought Greeks too into the temple, and profaned this holy place. 29 For they had before seen Trophimus the Ephesian with him in the city, whom they supposed that Paul had brought into the temple. 30 And the whole city was moved, and there was a concourse of the people; and having laid hold on Paul they drew him out of the temple, and immediately the doors were shut. 31 And as they were seeking to kill him, a representation came to the chiliarch of the band that the whole of Jerusalem was in a tumult; 32 who, taking with him immediately soldiers and centurions, ran down upon them. But they, seeing the chiliarch and the soldiers, ceased beating Paul. 33 Then the chiliarch came up and laid hold upon him, and commanded him to be bound with two chains, and inquired who he might be, and what he had done. 34 And different persons cried some different thing in the crowd. But he, not being able to know the certainty on account of the uproar, commanded him to be brought into the fortress. 35 But when he got upon the stairs it was so that he was borne by the soldiers on account of the violence of the crowd. 36 For the multitude of the people followed, crying, Away with him. 37 But as he was about to be led into the fortress, Paul says to the chiliarch, Is it allowed me to say something to thee? And he said, Dost thou know Greek? 38 Thou art not then that Egyptian who before these days raised a sedition and led out into the wilderness the four thousand men of the assassins? 39 But Paul said, I am a Jew of Tarsus, citizen of no insignificant city of Cilicia, and I beseech of thee, allow me to speak to the people. 40 And when he had allowed him, Paul, standing on the stairs, beckoned with his hand to the people; and a great silence having been made, he addressed them in the Hebrew tongue, saying,

Acts 22

1 Brethren and fathers, hear my defence which I now make to you. 2 And hearing that he addressed them in the Hebrew tongue, they kept the more quiet; and he says,

3 I am a Jew, born in Tarsus of Cilicia, but brought up in this city, at the feet of Gamaliel, educated according to the exactness of the law of our fathers, being zealous for God, as ye are all this day; 4 who have persecuted this way unto death, binding and delivering up to prisons both men and women; 5 as also the high priest bears me witness, and all the elderhood: from whom also, having received letters to the brethren, I went to Damascus to bring those also who were there, bound, to Jerusalem, to be punished. 6 And it came to pass, as I was journeying and drawing near to Damascus, that, about mid-day, there suddenly shone out of heaven a great light round about me. 7 And I fell to the ground, and heard a voice saying to me, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? 8 And I answered, Who art thou, Lord? And he said to me, I am Jesus the Nazaraean, whom thou persecutest. 9 But they that were with me beheld the light, and were filled with fear, but heard not the voice of him that was speaking to me. 10 And I said, What shall I do, Lord? And the Lord said to me, Rise up, and go to Damascus, and there it shall be told thee of all things which it is appointed thee to do. 11 And as I could not see, through the glory of that light, being led by the hand of those who were with me, I came to Damascus. 12 And a certain Ananias, a pious man according to the law, borne witness to by all the Jews who dwelt there, 13 coming to me and standing by me, said to me, Brother Saul, receive thy sight. And I, in the same hour, received my sight and saw him. 14 And he said, The God of our fathers has chosen thee beforehand to know his will, and to see the just one, and to hear a voice out of his mouth; 15 for thou shalt be a witness for him to all men of what thou hast seen and heard. 16 And now why lingerest thou? Arise and get baptised, and have thy sins washed away, calling on his name. 17 And it came to pass when I had returned to Jerusalem, and as I was praying in the temple, that I became in ecstasy, 18 and saw him saying to me, Make haste and go quickly out of Jerusalem, for they will not receive thy testimony concerning me. 19 And I said, Lord, they themselves know that I was imprisoning and beating in every synagogue those that believe on thee; 20 and when the blood of thy witness Stephen was shed, I also myself was standing by and consenting, and kept the clothes of them who killed him. 21 And he said to me, Go, for I will send thee to the nations afar off.

22 And they heard him until this word, and lifted up their voice, saying, Away with such a one as that from the earth, for it was not fit he should live. 23 And as they were crying, and throwing away their clothes, and casting dust into the air, 24 the chiliarch commanded him to be brought into the fortress, saying that he should be examined by scourging, that he might ascertain for what cause they cried thus against him. 25 But as they stretched him forward with the thongs, Paul said to the centurion who stood by, Is it lawful for you to scourge a man who is a Roman and uncondemned? 26 And the centurion, having heard it, went and reported it to the chiliarch, saying, What art thou going to do? for this man is a Roman. 27 And the chiliarch coming up said to him, Tell me, Art thou a Roman? And he said, Yes. 28 And the chiliarch answered, I, for a great sum, bought this citizenship. And Paul said, But I was also free born. 29 Immediately therefore those who were going to examine him left him, and the chiliarch also was afraid when he ascertained that he was a Roman, and because he had bound him. 30 And on the morrow, desirous to know the certainty of the matter why he was accused of the Jews, he loosed him, and commanded the chief priests and all the council to meet, and having brought Paul down set him before them.

Acts 23

1 And Paul, fixing his eyes on the council, said, Brethren, I have walked in all good conscience with God unto this day. 2 But the high priest Ananias ordered those standing by him to smite his mouth. 3 Then Paul said to him, God will smite thee, whited wall. And thou, dost thou sit judging me according to the law, and breaking the law commandest me to be smitten? 4 And those that stood by said, Dost thou rail against the high priest of God? 5 And Paul said, I was not conscious, brethren, that he was high priest; for it is written, Thou shalt not speak evilly of the ruler of thy people.

6 But Paul, knowing that the one part of them were of the Sadducees and the other of the Pharisees, cried out in the council, Brethren, I am a Pharisee, son of Pharisees: I am judged concerning the hope and resurrection of the dead. 7 And when he had spoken this, there was a tumult of the Pharisees and the Sadducees, and the multitude was divided. 8 For Sadducees say there is no resurrection, nor angel, nor spirit; but Pharisees confess both of them. 9 And there was a great clamour, and the scribes of the Pharisees' part rising up contended, saying, We find nothing evil in this man; and if a spirit has spoken to him, or an angel... 10 And a great tumult having arisen, the chiliarch, fearing lest Paul should have been torn in pieces by them, commanded the troop to come down and take him by force from the midst of them, and to bring him into the fortress. 11 But the following night the Lord stood by him, and said, Be of good courage; for as thou hast testified the things concerning me at Jerusalem, so thou must bear witness at Rome also.

12 And when it was day, the Jews, having banded together, put themselves under a curse, saying that they would neither eat nor drink till they should kill Paul. 13 And they were more than forty who had joined together in this oath; 14 and they went to the chief priests and elders, and said, We have cursed ourselves with a curse to taste nothing until we kill Paul. 15 Now therefore do ye with the council make a representation to the chiliarch so that he may bring him down to you, as about to determine more precisely what concerns him, and we, before he draws near, are ready to kill him. 16 But Paul's sister's son, having heard of the lying in wait, came and entered into the fortress and reported it to Paul. 17 And Paul, having called one of the centurions, said, Take this youth to the chiliarch, for he has something to report to him. 18 He therefore, having taken him with him, led him to the chiliarch, and says, The prisoner Paul called me to him and asked me to lead this youth to thee, who has something to say to thee. 19 And the chiliarch having taken him by the hand, and having gone apart in private, inquired, What is it that thou hast to report to me? 20 And he said, The Jews have agreed together to make a request to thee, that thou mayest bring Paul down to-morrow into the council, as about to inquire something more precise concerning him. 21 Do not thou then be persuaded by them, for there lie in wait for him of them more than forty men, who have put themselves under a curse neither to eat nor drink till they kill him; and now they are ready waiting the promise from thee. 22 The chiliarch then dismissed the youth, commanding him, Utter to no one that thou hast represented these things to me. 23 And having called to him certain two of the centurions, he said, Prepare two hundred soldiers that they may go as far as Caesarea, and seventy horsemen, and two hundred light-armed footmen, for the third hour of the night. 24 And he ordered them to provide beasts, that they might set Paul on them and carry him safe through to Felix the governor, 25 having written a letter, couched in this form: 26 Claudius Lysias to the most excellent governor Felix, greeting. 27 This man, having been taken by the Jews, and being about to be killed by them, I came up with the military and took out of their hands, having learned that he was a Roman. 28 And desiring to know the charge on which they accused him, I brought him down to their council; 29 whom I found to be accused of questions of their law, but to have no charge laid against him making him worthy of death or of bonds. 30 But having received information of a plot about to be put in execution against the man by the Jews, I have immediately sent him to thee, commanding also his accusers to say before thee the things that are against him. Farewell. 31 The soldiers therefore, according to what was ordered them, took Paul and brought him by night to Antipatris, 32 and on the morrow, having left the horsemen to go with him, returned to the fortress. 33 And these, having entered into Caesarea, and given up the letter to the governor, presented Paul also to him. 34 And having read it, and asked of what eparchy he was, and learned that he was of Cilicia, 35 he said, I will hear thee fully when thine accusers also are arrived. And he commanded him to be kept in Herod's praetorium.

Acts 24

1 And after five days came down the high priest Ananias, with the elders, and a certain orator called Tertullus, and laid their informations against Paul before the governor. 2 And he having been called, Tertullus began to accuse, saying, Seeing we enjoy great peace through thee, and that excellent measures are executed for this nation by thy forethought, 3 we receive it always and everywhere, most excellent Felix, with all thankfulness. 4 But that I may not too much intrude on thy time, I beseech thee to hear us briefly in thy kindness. 5 For finding this man a pest, and moving sedition among all the Jews throughout the world, and a leader of the sect of the Nazaraeans; 6 who also attempted to profane the temple; whom we also had seized, and would have judged according to our law; 7 but Lysias, the chiliarch, coming up, took him away with great force out of our hands, 8 having commanded his accusers to come to thee; 9 And the Jews also joined in pressing the matter against Paul, saying that these things were so.

10 But Paul, the governor having beckoned to him to speak, answered, Knowing that for many years thou hast been judge to this nation, I answer readily as to the things which concern myself. 11 As thou mayest know that there are not more than twelve days since I went up to worship at Jerusalem, 12 and neither in the temple did they find me discoursing to any one, or making any tumultuous gathering together of the crowd, nor in the synagogues, nor in the city; 13 neither can they make good the things of which they now accuse me. 14 But this I avow to thee, that in the way which they call sect, so I serve my fathers' God, believing all things which are written throughout the law, and in the prophets; 15 having hope towards God, which they themselves also receive, that there is to be a resurrection both of just and unjust. 16 For this cause I also exercise myself to have in everything a conscience without offence towards God and men. 17 And after a lapse of many years I arrived, bringing alms to my nation, and offerings. 18 Whereupon they found me purified in the temple, with neither crowd nor tumult. But it was certain Jews from Asia, 19 who ought to appear before thee and accuse, if they have anything against me; 20 or let these themselves say what wrong they found in me when I stood before the council, 21 other than concerning this one voice which I cried standing amongst them: I am judged this day by you touching the resurrection of the dead.

22 And Felix, knowing accurately the things concerning the way, adjourned them, saying, When Lysias the chiliarch is come down I will determine your affair; 23 ordering the centurion to keep him, and that he should have freedom, and to hinder none of his friends to minister to him. 24 And after certain days, Felix having arrived with Drusilla his wife, who was a Jewess, he sent for Paul and heard him concerning the faith in Christ. 25 And as he reasoned concerning righteousness, and temperance, and the judgment about to come, Felix, being filled with fear, answered, Go for the present, and when I get an opportunity I will send for thee; 26 hoping at the same time that money would be given him by Paul: wherefore also he sent for him the oftener and communed with him. 27 But when two years were completed, Felix was relieved by Porcius Festus as his successor; and Felix, desirous to oblige the Jews, to acquire their favour, left Paul bound.

Acts 25

1 Festus therefore, being come into the eparchy, after three days went up to Jerusalem from Caesarea. 2 And the chief priests and the chief of the Jews laid informations before him against Paul, and besought him, 3 asking as a grace against him that he would send for him to Jerusalem, laying people in wait to kill him on the way. 4 Festus therefore answered that Paul should be kept at Caesarea, and that he himself was about to set out shortly. 5 Let therefore the persons of authority among you, says he, going down too, if there be anything in this man, accuse him. 6 And having remained among them not more than eight or ten days, he went down to Caesarea; and on the next day, having sat down on the judgment-seat, commanded Paul to be brought. 7 And when he was come, the Jews who were come down from Jerusalem stood round, bringing many and grievous charges which they were not able to prove: 8 Paul answering for himself, Neither against the law of the Jews, nor against the temple, nor against Caesar, have I offended in anything. 9 But Festus, desirous of obliging the Jews, to acquire their favour, answering Paul, said, Art thou willing to go up to Jerusalem, there to be judged before me concerning these things? 10 But Paul said, I am standing before the judgment-seat of Caesar, where I ought to be judged. To the Jews have I done no wrong, as thou also very well knowest. 11 If then I have done any wrong and committed anything worthy of death, I do not deprecate dying; but if there is nothing of those things of which they accuse me, no man can give me up to them. I appeal to Caesar. 12 Then Festus, having conferred with the council, answered, Thou hast appealed to Caesar. To Caesar shalt thou go.

13 And when certain days had elapsed, Agrippa the king and Bernice arrived at Caesarea to salute Festus. 14 And when they had spent many days there, Festus laid before the king the matters relating to Paul, saying, There is a certain man left prisoner by Felix, 15 concerning whom, when I was at Jerusalem, the chief priests and the elders of the Jews laid informations, requiring judgment against him: 16 to whom I answered, It is not the custom of the Romans to give up any man before that the accused have the accusers face to face, and he have got opportunity of defence touching the charge. 17 When therefore they had come together here, without putting it off, I sat the next day on the judgment-seat and commanded the man to be brought: 18 concerning whom the accusers, standing up, brought no such accusation of guilt as I supposed; 19 but had against him certain questions of their own system of worship, and concerning a certain Jesus who is dead, whom Paul affirmed to be living. 20 And as I myself was at a loss as to an inquiry into these things, I said, Was he willing to go to Jerusalem and there to be judged concerning these things? 21 But Paul having appealed to be kept for the cognisance of Augustus, I commanded him to be kept till I shall send him to Caesar. 22 And Agrippa said to Festus, I myself also would desire to hear the man. To-morrow, said he, thou shalt hear him. 23 On the morrow therefore, Agrippa being come, and Bernice, with great pomp, and having entered into the hall of audience, with the chiliarchs and the men of distinction of the city, and Festus having given command, Paul was brought. 24 And Festus said, King Agrippa, and all men who are here present with us, ye see this person, concerning whom all the multitude of the Jews applied to me both in Jerusalem and here, crying out against him that he ought not to live any longer. 25 But I, having found that he had done nothing worthy of death, and this man himself having appealed to Augustus, I have decided to send him; 26 concerning whom I have nothing certain to write to my lord. Wherefore I have brought him before you, and specially before thee, king Agrippa, so that an examination having been gone into I may have something to write: 27 for it seems to me senseless, sending a prisoner, not also to signify the charges against him.

Acts 26

1 And Agrippa said to Paul, It is permitted thee to speak for thyself. Then Paul stretching out his hand answered in his defence: 2 I count myself happy, king Agrippa, in having to answer to-day before thee concerning all of which I am accused by the Jews, 3 especially because thou art acquainted with all the customs and questions which are among the Jews; wherefore I beseech thee to hear me patiently. 4 My manner of life then from my youth, which from its commencement was passed among my nation in Jerusalem, know all the Jews, 5 who knew me before from the outset of my life, if they would bear witness, that according to the strictest sect of our religion I lived a Pharisee. 6 And now I stand to be judged because of the hope of the promise made by God to our fathers, 7 to which our whole twelve tribes serving incessantly day and night hope to arrive; about which hope, O king, I am accused of the Jews. 8 Why should it be judged a thing incredible in your sight if God raises the dead? 9 I indeed myself thought that I ought to do much against the name of Jesus the Nazaraean. 10 Which also I did in Jerusalem, and myself shut up in prisons many of the saints, having received the authority from the chief priests; and when they were put to death I gave my vote. 11 And often punishing them in all the synagogues, I compelled them to blaspheme. And, being exceedingly furious against them, I persecuted them even to cities out of our own land.

12 And when, engaged in this, I was journeying to Damascus, with authority and power from the chief priests, 13 at mid-day, on the way, I saw, O king, a light above the brightness of the sun, shining from heaven round about me and those who were journeying with me. 14 And, when we were all fallen to the ground, I heard a voice saying to me in the Hebrew tongue, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? it is hard for thee to kick against goads. 15 And I said, Who art thou, Lord? And the Lord said, I am Jesus whom thou persecutest: 16 but rise up and stand on thy feet; for, for this purpose have I appeared to thee, to appoint thee to be a servant and a witness both of what thou hast seen, and of what I shall appear to thee in, 17 taking thee out from among the people, and the nations, to whom I send thee, 18 to open their eyes, that they may turn from darkness to light, and from the power of Satan to God, that they may receive remission of sins and inheritance among them that are sanctified by faith in me. 19 Whereupon, king Agrippa, I was not disobedient to the heavenly vision; 20 but have, first to those both in Damascus and Jerusalem, and to all the region of Judaea, and to the nations, announced that they should repent and turn to God, doing works worthy of repentance. 21 On account of these things the Jews, having seized me in the temple, attempted to lay hands on and destroy me. 22 Having therefore met with the help which is from God, I have stood firm unto this day, witnessing both to small and great, saying nothing else than those things which both the prophets and Moses have said should happen, 23 namely, whether Christ should suffer; whether he first, through resurrection of the dead, should announce light both to the people and to the nations.

24 And as he answered for his defence with these things, Festus says with a loud voice, Thou art mad, Paul; much learning turns thee to madness. 25 But Paul said, I am not mad, most excellent Festus, but utter words of truth and soberness; 26 for the king is informed about these things, to whom also I speak with all freedom. For I am persuaded that of these things nothing is hidden from him; for this was not done in a corner. 27 King Agrippa, believest thou the prophets? I know that thou believest. 28 And Agrippa said to Paul, In a little thou persuadest me to become a Christian. 29 And Paul said, I would to God, both in little and in much, that not only thou, but all who have heard me this day, should become such as I also am, except these bonds. 30 And the king stood up, and the governor and Bernice, and those who sat with them, 31 and having gone apart, they spoke to one another saying, This man does nothing worthy of death or of bonds. 32 And Agrippa said to Festus, This man might have been let go if he had not appealed to Caesar.

Acts 27

1 But when it had been determined that we should sail to Italy, they delivered up Paul and certain other prisoners to a centurion, by name Julius, of Augustus' company. 2 And going on board a ship of Adramyttium about to navigate by the places along Asia, we set sail, Aristarchus, a Macedonian of Thessalonica, being with us. 3 And the next day we arrived at Sidon. And Julius treated Paul kindly and suffered him to go to his friends and refresh himself. 4 And setting sail thence we sailed under the lee of Cyprus, because the winds were contrary. 5 And having sailed over the waters of Cilicia and Pamphylia we came to Myra in Lycia: 6 and there the centurion having found a ship of Alexandria sailing to Italy, he made us go on board her. 7 And sailing slowly for many days, and having with difficulty got abreast of Cnidus, the wind not suffering us, we sailed under the lee of Crete abreast of Salmone; 8 and coasting it with difficulty we came to a certain place called Fair Havens, near to which was the city of Lasaea. 9 And much time having now been spent, and navigation being already dangerous, because the fast also was already past, Paul counselled them, 10 saying, Men, I perceive that the navigation will be with disaster and much loss, not only of the cargo and the ship, but also of our lives. 11 But the centurion believed rather the helmsman and the shipowner than what was said by Paul.

12 And the harbour being ill adapted to winter in, the most counselled to set sail thence, if perhaps they might reach Phoenice to winter in, a port of Crete looking north-east and south-east. 13 And the south wind blowing gently, supposing that they had gained their object, having weighed anchor they sailed close in shore along Crete. 14 But not long after there came down it a hurricane called Euroclydon. 15 And the ship being caught and driven, and not able to bring her head to the wind, letting her go we were driven before it. 16 But running under the lee of a certain island called Clauda, we were with difficulty able to make ourselves masters of the boat; 17 which having hoisted up, they used helps, frapping the ship; and fearing lest they should run into Syrtis and run aground, and having lowered the gear they were so driven. 18 But the storm being extremely violent on us, on the next day they threw cargo overboard, 19 and on the third day with their own hands they cast away the ship furniture. 20 And neither sun nor stars appearing for many days, and no small storm lying on us, in the end all hope of our being saved was taken away.

21 And when they had been a long while without taking food, Paul then standing up in the midst of them said, Ye ought, O men, to have hearkened to me, and not have made sail from Crete and have gained this disaster and loss. 22 And now I exhort you to be of good courage, for there shall be no loss at all of life of any of you, only of the ship. 23 For an angel of the God, whose I am and whom I serve, stood by me this night, 24 saying, Fear not, Paul; thou must stand before Caesar; and behold, God has granted to thee all those that sail with thee. 25 Wherefore be of good courage, men, for I believe God that thus it shall be, as it has been said to me. 26 But we must be cast ashore on a certain island. 27 And when the fourteenth night was come, we being driven about in Adria, towards the middle of the night the sailors supposed that some land neared them, 28 and having sounded found twenty fathoms, and having gone a little farther and having again sounded they found fifteen fathoms; 29 and fearing lest we should be cast on rocky places, casting four anchors out of the stern, they wished that day were come. 30 But the sailors wishing to flee out of the ship, and having let down the boat into the sea under pretext of being about to carry out anchors from the prow, 31 Paul said to the centurion and the soldiers, Unless these abide in the ship ye cannot be saved. 32 Then the soldiers cut away the ropes of the boat and let her fall. 33 And while it was drawing on to daylight, Paul exhorted them all to partake of food, saying, Ye have passed the fourteenth day watching in expectation without taking food. 34 Wherefore I exhort you to partake of food, for this has to do with your safety; for not a hair from the head of any one of you shall perish. 35 And, having said these things and taken a loaf, he gave thanks to God before all, and having broken it began to eat. 36 And all taking courage, themselves also took food. 37 And we were in the ship, all the souls, two hundred and seventy-six. 38 And having satisfied themselves with food, they lightened the ship, casting out the wheat into the sea. 39 And when it was day they did not recognise the land; but they perceived a certain bay having a strand, on which they were minded, if they should be able, to run the ship ashore; 40 and, having cast off the anchors, they left them in the sea, at the same time loosening the lashings of the rudders, and hoisting the foresail to the wind, they made for the strand. 41 And falling into a place where two seas met they ran the ship aground, and the prow having stuck itself fast remained unmoved, but the stern was broken by the force of the waves. 42 And the counsel of the soldiers was that they should kill the prisoners, lest any one should swim off and escape. 43 But the centurion, desirous of saving Paul, hindered them of their purpose, and commanded those who were able to swim, casting themselves first into the sea, to get out on land; 44 and the rest, some on boards, some on some of the things that came from the ship; and thus it came to pass that all got safe to land.

Acts 28

1 And when we got safe to land we then knew that the island was called Melita. 2 But the barbarians shewed us no common kindness; for, having kindled a fire, they took us all in because of the rain that was falling and because of the cold. 3 And Paul having gathered a certain quantity of sticks together in a bundle and laid it on the fire, a viper coming out from the heat seized his hand. 4 And when the barbarians saw the beast hanging from his hand, they said to one another, This man is certainly a murderer, whom, though saved out of the sea, Nemesis has not allowed to live. 5 He however, having shaken off the beast into the fire, felt no harm. 6 But they expected that he would have swollen or fallen down suddenly dead. But when they had expected a long time and saw nothing unusual happen to him, changing their opinion, they said he was a god. 7 Now in the country surrounding that place were the lands belonging to the chief man of the island, by name Publius, who received us and gave us hospitality three days in a very friendly way. 8 And it happened that the father of Publius lay ill of fever and dysentery; to whom Paul entered in, and having prayed and laid his hands on him cured him. 9 But this having taken place, the rest also who had sicknesses in the island came and were healed: 10 who also honoured us with many honours, and on our leaving they made presents to us of what should minister to our wants.

11 And after three months we sailed in a ship which had wintered in the island, an Alexandrian, with the Dioscuri for its ensign. 12 And having come to Syracuse we remained three days. 13 Whence, going in a circuitous course, we arrived at Rhegium; and after one day, the wind having changed to south, on the second day we came to Puteoli, 14 where, having found brethren, we were begged to stay with them seven days. And thus we went to Rome. 15 And thence the brethren, having heard about us, came to meet us as far as Appii Forum and Tres Tabernae, whom when Paul saw, he thanked God and took courage. 16 And when we came to Rome, the centurion delivered up the prisoners to the praetorian prefect, but Paul was allowed to remain by himself with the soldier who kept him.

17 And it came to pass after three days, that he called together those who were the chief of the Jews; and when they had come together he said to them, Brethren, I having done nothing against the people or the customs of our forefathers, have been delivered a prisoner from Jerusalem into the hands of the Romans, 18 who having examined me were minded to let me go, because there was nothing worthy of death in me. 19 But the Jews speaking against it, I was compelled to appeal to Caesar, not as having anything to accuse my nation of. 20 For this cause therefore I have called you to me to see and to speak to you; for on account of the hope of Israel I have this chain about me. 21 And they said to him, For our part, we have neither received letters from Judaea concerning thee, nor has any one of the brethren who has arrived reported or said anything evil concerning thee. 22 But we beg to hear of thee what thou thinkest, for as concerning this sect it is known to us that it is everywhere spoken against.

23 And having appointed him a day many came to him to the lodging, to whom he expounded, testifying of the kingdom of God, and persuading them concerning Jesus, both from the law of Moses and the prophets, from early morning to evening. 24 And some were persuaded of the things which were said, but some disbelieved. 25 And being disagreed among themselves they left; Paul having spoken one word, Well spoke the Holy Spirit through Esaias the prophet to our fathers, 26 saying, Go to this people, and say, Hearing ye shall hear and not understand, and seeing ye shall see and not perceive. 27 For the heart of this people has become fat, and they hear heavily with their ears, and they have closed their eyes; lest they should see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with their heart, and be converted, and I should heal them. 28 Be it known to you therefore, that this salvation of God has been sent to the nations; they also will hear it. 29 And he having said this, the Jews went away, having great reasoning among themselves.

30 And he remained two whole years in his own hired lodging, and received all who came to him, 31 preaching the kingdom of God, and teaching the things concerning the Lord Jesus Christ, with all freedom unhinderedly.

Romans 1

1 Paul, bondman of Jesus Christ, a called apostle, separated to God's glad tidings, 2 (which he had before promised by his prophets in holy writings,) 3 concerning his Son (come of David's seed according to flesh, 4 marked out Son of God in power, according to the Spirit of holiness, by resurrection of the dead) Jesus Christ our Lord; 5 by whom we have received grace and apostleship in behalf of his name, for obedience of faith among all the nations, 6 among whom are ye also the called of Jesus Christ: 7 to all that are in Rome, beloved of God, called saints: Grace to you and peace from God our Father and our Lord Jesus Christ.

8 First, I thank my God through Jesus Christ for you all, that your faith is proclaimed in the whole world. 9 For God is my witness, whom I serve in my spirit in the glad tidings of his Son, how unceasingly I make mention of you, 10 always beseeching at my prayers, if any way now at least I may be prospered by the will of God to come to you. 11 For I greatly desire to see you, that I may impart to you some spiritual gift to establish you; 12 that is, to have mutual comfort among you, each by the faith which is in the other, both yours and mine. 13 But I do not wish you to be ignorant, brethren, that I often proposed to come to you, (and have been hindered until the present time,) that I might have some fruit among you too, even as among the other nations also. 14 I am a debtor both to Greeks and barbarians, both to wise and unintelligent: 15 so, as far as depends on me, am I ready to announce the glad tidings to you also who are in Rome.

16 For I am not ashamed of the glad tidings; for it is God's power to salvation, to every one that believes, both to Jew first and to Greek: 17 for righteousness of God is revealed therein, on the principle of faith, to faith: according as it is written, But the just shall live by faith. 18 For there is revealed wrath of God from heaven upon all impiety, and unrighteousness of men holding the truth in unrighteousness.

19 Because what is known of God is manifest among them, for God has manifested it to them, 20 --for from the world's creation the invisible things of him are perceived, being apprehended by the mind through the things that are made, both his eternal power and divinity, --so as to render them inexcusable. 21 Because, knowing God, they glorified him not as God, neither were thankful; but fell into folly in their thoughts, and their heart without understanding was darkened: 22 professing themselves to be wise, they became fools, 23 and changed the glory of the incorruptible God into the likeness of an image of corruptible man and of birds and quadrupeds and reptiles. 24 Wherefore God gave them up also in the lusts of their hearts to uncleanness, to dishonour their bodies between themselves: 25 who changed the truth of God into falsehood, and honoured and served the creature more than him who had created it, who is blessed for ever. Amen. 26 For this reason God gave them up to vile lusts; for both their females changed the natural use into that contrary to nature; 27 and in like manner the males also, leaving the natural use of the female, were inflamed in their lust towards one another; males with males working shame, and receiving in themselves the recompense of their error which was fit. 28 And according as they did not think good to have God in their knowledge, God gave them up to a reprobate mind to practise unseemly things; 29 being filled with all unrighteousness, wickedness, covetousness, malice; full of envy, murder, strife, deceit, evil dispositions; whisperers, 30 back-biters, hateful to God, insolent, proud, boasters, inventors of evil things, disobedient to parents, 31 void of understanding, faithless, without natural affection, unmerciful; 32 who knowing the righteous judgment of God, that they who do such things are worthy of death, not only practise them, but have fellow delight in those who do them.

Romans 2

1 Therefore thou art inexcusable, O man, every one who judgest, for in that in which thou judgest another, thou condemnest thyself; for thou that judgest doest the same things. 2 But we know that the judgment of God is according to truth upon those who do such things. 3 And thinkest thou this, O man, who judgest those that do such things, and practisest them thyself, that thou shalt escape the judgment of God? 4 or despisest thou the riches of his goodness, and forbearance, and long-suffering, not knowing that the goodness of God leads thee to repentance? 5 but, according to thy hardness and impenitent heart, treasurest up to thyself wrath, in the day of wrath and revelation of the righteous judgment of God, 6 who shall render to each according to his works: 7 to them who, in patient continuance of good works, seek for glory and honour and incorruptibility, life eternal. 8 But to those that are contentious, and are disobedient to the truth, but obey unrighteousness, there shall be wrath and indignation, 9 tribulation and distress, on every soul of man that works evil, both of Jew first, and of Greek; 10 but glory and honour and peace to every one that works good, both to Jew first and to Greek: 11 for there is no acceptance of persons with God. 12 For as many as have sinned without law shall perish also without law; and as many as have sinned under law shall be judged by law, 13 (for not the hearers of the law are just before God, but the doers of the law shall be justified. 14 For when those of the nations, which have no law, practise by nature the things of the law, these, having no law, are a law to themselves; 15 who shew the work of the law written in their hearts, their conscience also bearing witness, and their thoughts accusing or else excusing themselves between themselves;) 16 in the day when God shall judge the secrets of men, according to my glad tidings, by Jesus Christ.

17 But if thou art named a Jew, and restest in the law, and makest thy boast in God, 18 and knowest the will, and discerningly approvest the things that are more excellent, being instructed out of the law; 19 and hast confidence that thou thyself art a leader of the blind, a light of those who are in darkness, 20 an instructor of the foolish, a teacher of babes, having the form of knowledge and of truth in the law: 21 thou then that teachest another, dost thou not teach thyself? thou that preachest not to steal, dost thou steal? 22 thou that sayest man should not commit adultery, dost thou commit adultery? thou that abhorrest idols, dost thou commit sacrilege? 23 thou who boastest in law, dost thou by transgression of the law dishonour God? 24 For the name of God is blasphemed on your account among the nations, according as it is written. 25 For circumcision indeed profits if thou keep the law; but if thou be a law-transgressor, thy circumcision is become uncircumcision. 26 If therefore the uncircumcision keep the requirements of the law, shall not his uncircumcision be reckoned for circumcision, 27 and uncircumcision by nature, fulfilling the law, judge thee, who, with letter and circumcision, art a law-transgressor? 28 For he is not a Jew who is one outwardly, neither that circumcision which is outward in flesh; 29 but he is a Jew who is so inwardly; and circumcision, of the heart, in spirit, not in letter; whose praise is not of men, but of God.

Romans 3

1 What then is the superiority of the Jew? or what the profit of circumcision? 2 Much every way: and first, indeed, that to them were entrusted the oracles of God. 3 For what? if some have not believed, shall their unbelief make the faith of God of none effect? 4 Far be the thought: but let God be true, and every man false; according as it is written, So that thou shouldest be justified in thy words, and shouldest overcome when thou art in judgment. 5 But if our unrighteousness commend God's righteousness, what shall we say? Is God unrighteous who inflicts wrath? I speak according to man. 6 Far be the thought: since how shall God judge the world? 7 For if the truth of God, in my lie, has more abounded to his glory, why yet am I also judged as a sinner? 8 and not, according as we are injuriously charged, and according as some affirm that we say, Let us practise evil things, that good ones may come? whose judgment is just. 9 What then? are we better? No, in no wise: for we have before charged both Jews and Greeks with being all under sin: 10 according as it is written, There is not a righteous man, not even one; 11 there is not the man that understands, there is not one that seeks after God. 12 All have gone out of the way, they have together become unprofitable; there is not one that practises goodness, there is not so much as one: 13 their throat is an open sepulchre; with their tongues they have used deceit; asps' poison is under their lips: 14 whose mouth is full of cursing and bitterness; 15 swift their feet to shed blood; 16 ruin and misery are in their ways, 17 and way of peace they have not known: 18 there is no fear of God before their eyes.

19 Now we know that whatever the things the law says, it speaks to those under the law, that every mouth may be stopped, and all the world be under judgment to God. 20 Wherefore by works of law no flesh shall be justified before him; for by law is knowledge of sin. 21 But now without law righteousness of God is manifested, borne witness to by the law and the prophets; 22 righteousness of God by faith of Jesus Christ towards all, and upon all those who believe: for there is no difference; 23 for all have sinned, and come short of the glory of God; 24 being justified freely by his grace through the redemption which is in Christ Jesus; 25 whom God has set forth a mercy-seat, through faith in his blood, for the shewing forth of his righteousness, in respect of the passing by the sins that had taken place before, through the forbearance of God; 26 for the shewing forth of his righteousness in the present time, so that he should be just, and justify him that is of the faith of Jesus. 27 Where then is boasting? It has been excluded. By what law? of works? Nay, but by law of faith; 28 for we reckon that a man is justified by faith, without works of law. 29 Is God the God of Jews only? is he not of the nations also? Yea, of nations also: 30 since indeed it is one God who shall justify the circumcision on the principle of faith, and uncircumcision by faith. 31 Do we then make void law by faith? Far be the thought: no, but we establish law.

Romans 4

1 What shall we say then that Abraham our father according to flesh has found? 2 For if Abraham has been justified on the principle of works, he has whereof to boast: but not before God; 3 for what does the scripture say? And Abraham believed God, and it was reckoned to him as righteousness. 4 Now to him that works the reward is not reckoned as of grace, but of debt: 5 but to him who does not work, but believes on him who justifies the ungodly, his faith is reckoned as righteousness. 6 Even as David also declares the blessedness of the man to whom God reckons righteousness without works: 7 Blessed they whose lawlessnesses have been forgiven, and whose sins have been covered: 8 blessed the man to whom the Lord shall not at all reckon sin.

9 Does this blessedness then rest on the circumcision, or also on the uncircumcision? For we say that faith has been reckoned to Abraham as righteousness. 10 How then has it been reckoned? when he was in circumcision, or in uncircumcision? Not in circumcision, but in uncircumcision. 11 And he received the sign of circumcision as seal of the righteousness of faith which he had being in uncircumcision, that he might be the father of all them that believe being in uncircumcision, that righteousness might be reckoned to them also; 12 and father of circumcision, not only to those who are of the circumcision, but to those also who walk in the steps of the faith, during uncircumcision, of our father Abraham. 13 For it was not by law that the promise was to Abraham, or to his seed, that he should be heir of the world, but by righteousness of faith. 14 For if they which are of law be heirs, faith is made vain, and the promise made of no effect. 15 For law works wrath; but where no law is neither is there transgression. 16 Therefore it is on the principle of faith, that it might be according to grace, in order to the promise being sure to all the seed, not to that only which is of the law, but to that also which is of Abraham's faith, who is father of us all,

17 (according as it is written, I have made thee father of many nations,) before the God whom he believed, who quickens the dead, and calls the things which be not as being; 18 who against hope believed in hope to his becoming father of many nations, according to that which was spoken, So shall thy seed be: 19 and not being weak in faith, he considered not his own body already become dead, being about a hundred years old, and the deadening of Sarah's womb, 20 and hesitated not at the promise of God through unbelief; but found strength in faith, giving glory to God; 21 and being fully persuaded that what he has promised he is able also to do; 22 wherefore also it was reckoned to him as righteousness.

23 Now it was not written on his account alone that it was reckoned to him, 24 but on ours also, to whom, believing on him who has raised from among the dead Jesus our Lord, 25 who has been delivered for our offences and has been raised for our justification, it will be reckoned.

Romans 5

1 Therefore having been justified on the principle of faith, we have peace towards God through our Lord Jesus Christ; 2 by whom we have also access by faith into this favour in which we stand, and we boast in hope of the glory of God. 3 And not only that, but we also boast in tribulations, knowing that tribulation works endurance; 4 and endurance, experience; and experience, hope; 5 and hope does not make ashamed, because the love of God is shed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Spirit which has been given to us:

6 for we being still without strength, in the due time Christ has died for the ungodly. 7 For scarcely for the just man will one die, for perhaps for the good man some one might also dare to die; 8 but God commends his love to us, in that, we being still sinners, Christ has died for us. 9 Much rather therefore, having been now justified in the power of his blood, we shall be saved by him from wrath. 10 For if, being enemies, we have been reconciled to God through the death of his Son, much rather, having been reconciled, we shall be saved in the power of his life. 11 And not only that, but we are making our boast in God, through our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom now we have received the reconciliation. 12 For this cause, even as by one man sin entered into the world, and by sin death; and thus death passed upon all men, for that all have sinned: 13 (for until law sin was in the world; but sin is not put to account when there is no law; 14 but death reigned from Adam until Moses, even upon those who had not sinned in the likeness of Adam's transgression, who is the figure of him to come. 15 But shall not the act of favour be as the offence? For if by the offence of one the many have died, much rather has the grace of God, and the free gift in grace, which isby the one man Jesus Christ, abounded unto the many. 16 And shall not as by one that has sinned be the gift? For the judgment was of one to condemnation, but the act of favour, of many offences unto justification. 17 For if by the offence of the one death reigned by the one, much rather shall those who receive the abundance of grace, and of the free gift of righteousness, reign in life by the one Jesus Christ:) 18 so then as it was by one offence towards all men to condemnation, so by one righteousness towards all men for justification of life. 19 For as indeed by the disobedience of the one man the many have been constituted sinners, so also by the obedience of the one the many will be constituted righteous. 20 But law came in, in order that the offence might abound; but where sin abounded grace has overabounded, 21 in order that, even as sin has reigned in the power of death, so also grace might reign through righteousness to eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.

Romans 6

1 What then shall we say? Should we continue in sin that grace may abound? 2 Far be the thought. We who have died to sin, how shall we still live in it? 3 Are you ignorant that we, as many as have been baptised unto Christ Jesus, have been baptised unto his death? 4 We have been buried therefore with him by baptism unto death, in order that, even as Christ has been raised up from among the dead by the glory of the Father, so we also should walk in newness of life. 5 For if we are become identified with him in the likeness of his death, so also we shall be of his resurrection; 6 knowing this, that our old man has been crucified with him, that the body of sin might be annulled, that we should no longer serve sin. 7 For he that has died is justified from sin. 8 Now if we have died with Christ, we believe that we shall also live with him, 9 knowing that Christ having been raised up from among the dead dies no more: death has dominion over him no more. 10 For in that he has died, he has died to sin once for all; but in that he lives, he lives to God. 11 So also ye, reckon yourselves dead to sin and alive to God in Christ Jesus. 12 Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal body to obey its lusts. 13 Neither yield your members instruments of unrighteousness to sin, but yield yourselves to God as alive from among the dead, and your members instruments of righteousness to God. 14 For sin shall not have dominion over you, for ye are not under law but under grace. 15 What then? should we sin because we are not under law but under grace? Far be the thought. 16 Know ye not that to whom ye yield yourselves bondmen for obedience, ye are bondmen to him whom ye obey, whether of sin unto death, or of obedience unto righteousness? 17 But thanks be to God, that ye were bondmen of sin, but have obeyed from the heart the form of teaching into which ye were instructed. 18 Now, having got your freedom from sin, ye have become bondmen to righteousness. 19 I speak humanly on account of the weakness of your flesh. For even as ye have yielded your members in bondage to uncleanness and to lawlessness unto lawlessness, so now yield your members in bondage to righteousness unto holiness. 20 For when ye were bondmen of sin ye were free from righteousness. 21 What fruit therefore had ye then in the things of which ye are now ashamed? for the end of them is death. 22 But now, having got your freedom from sin, and having become bondmen to God, ye have your fruit unto holiness, and the end eternal life. 23 For the wages of sin is death; but the act of favour of God, eternal life in Christ Jesus our Lord.

Romans 7

1 Are ye ignorant, brethren, (for I speak to those knowing law,) that law rules over a man as long as he lives? 2 For the married woman is bound by law to her husband so long as he is alive; but if the husband should die, she is clear from the law of the husband: 3 so then, the husband being alive, she shall be called an adulteress if she be to another man; but if the husband should die, she is free from the law, so as not to be an adulteress, though she be to another man. 4 So that, my brethren, ye also have been made dead to the law by the body of the Christ, to be to another, who has been raised up from among the dead, in order that we might bear fruit to God. 5 For when we were in the flesh the passions of sins, which were by the law, wrought in our members to bring forth fruit to death; 6 but now we are clear from the law, having died in that in which we were held, so that we should serve in newness of spirit, and not in oldness of letter.

7 What shall we say then? is the law sin? Far be the thought. But I had not known sin, unless by law: for I had not had conscience also of lust unless the law had said, Thou shalt not lust; 8 but sin, getting a point of attack by the commandment, wrought in me every lust; for without law sin was dead. 9 But I was alive without law once; but the commandment having come, sin revived, but I died. 10 And the commandment, which was for life, was found, as to me, itself to be unto death: 11 for sin, getting a point of attack by the commandment, deceived me, and by it slew me. 12 So that the law indeed is holy, and the commandment holy, and just, and good. 13 Did then that which is good become death to me? Far be the thought. But sin, that it might appear sin, working death to me by that which is good; in order that sin by the commandment might become exceeding sinful.

14 For we know that the law is spiritual: but I am fleshly, sold under sin. 15 For that which I do, I do not own: for not what I will, this I do; but what I hate, this I practise. 16 But if what I do not will, this I practise, I consent to the law that it is right. 17 Now then it is no longer I that do it, but the sin that dwells in me. 18 For I know that in me, that is, in my flesh, good does not dwell: for to will is there with me, but to do right I find not. 19 For I do not practise the good that I will; but the evil I do not will, that I do. 20 But if what I do not will, this I practise, it is no longer I that do it, but the sin that dwells in me. 21 I find then the law upon me who will to practise what is right, that with me evil is there. 22 For I delight in the law of God according to the inward man: 23 but I see another law in my members, warring in opposition to the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity to the law of sin which exists in my members. 24 O wretched man that I am! who shall deliver me out of this body of death? 25 I thank God, through Jesus Christ our Lord. So then I myself with the mind serve God's law; but with the flesh sin's law.

Romans 8

1 There is then now no condemnation to those in Christ Jesus. 2 For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus has set me free from the law of sin and of death. 3 For what the law could not do, in that it was weak through the flesh, God, having sent his own Son, in likeness of flesh of sin, and for sin, has condemned sin in the flesh, 4 in order that the righteous requirement of the law should be fulfilled in us, who do not walk according to flesh but according to Spirit. 5 For they that are according to flesh mind the things of the flesh; and they that are according to Spirit, the things of the Spirit. 6 For the mind of the flesh is death; but the mind of the Spirit life and peace. 7 Because the mind of the flesh is enmity against God: for it is not subject to the law of God; for neither indeed can it be: 8 and they that are in flesh cannot please God. 9 But ye are not in flesh but in Spirit, if indeed God's Spirit dwell in you; but if any one has not the Spirit of Christ he is not of him:

10 but if Christ be in you, the body is dead on account of sin, but the Spirit life on account of righteousness. 11 But if the Spirit of him that has raised up Jesus from among the dead dwell in you, he that has raised up Christ from among the dead shall quicken your mortal bodies also on account of his Spirit which dwells in you. 12 So then, brethren, we are debtors, not to the flesh, to live according to flesh; 13 for if ye live according to flesh, ye are about to die; but if, by the Spirit, ye put to death the deeds of the body, ye shall live: 14 for as many as are led by the Spirit of God, these are sons of God. 15 For ye have not received a spirit of bondage again for fear, but ye have received a spirit of adoption, whereby we cry, Abba, Father. 16 The Spirit itself bears witness with our spirit, that we are children of God.

17 And if children, heirs also: heirs of God, and Christ's joint heirs; if indeed we suffer with him, that we may also be glorified with him. 18 For I reckon that the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the coming glory to be revealed to us. 19 For the anxious looking out of the creature expects the revelation of the sons of God: 20 for the creature has been made subject to vanity, not of its will, but by reason of him who has subjected the same, in hope 21 that the creature itself also shall be set free from the bondage of corruption into the liberty of the glory of the children of God. 22 For we know that the whole creation groans together and travails in pain together until now. 23 And not only that, but even we ourselves, who have the first-fruits of the Spirit, we also ourselves groan in ourselves, awaiting adoption, that is the redemption of our body. 24 For we have been saved in hope; but hope seen is not hope; for what any one sees, why does he also hope? 25 But if what we see not we hope, we expect in patience.

26 And in like manner the Spirit joins also its help to our weakness; for we do not know what we should pray for as is fitting, but the Spirit itself makes intercession with groanings which cannot be uttered. 27 But he who searches the hearts knows what is the mind of the Spirit, because he intercedes for saints according to God. 28 But we do know that all things work together for good to those who love God, to those who are called according to purpose.

29 Because whom he has foreknown, he has also predestinated to be conformed to the image of his Son, so that he should be the firstborn among many brethren. 30 But whom he has predestinated, these also he has called; and whom he has called, these also he has justified; but whom he has justified, these also he has glorified.

31 What shall we then say to these things? If God be for us, who against us? 32 He who, yea, has not spared his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how shall he not also with him grant us all things? 33 Who shall bring an accusation against God's elect? It is God who justifies: 34 who is he that condemns? It is Christ who has died, but rather has been also raised up; who is also at the right hand of God; who also intercedes for us. 35 Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? tribulation or distress, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or danger, or sword? 36 According as it is written, For thy sake we are put to death all the day long; we have been reckoned as sheep for slaughter. 37 But in all these things we more than conquer through him that has loved us. 38 For I am persuaded that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor things present, nor things to come, nor powers, 39 nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, shall be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.

Romans 9

1 I say the truth in Christ, I lie not, my conscience bearing witness with me in the Holy Spirit, 2 that I have great grief and uninterrupted pain in my heart, 3 for I have wished, I myself, to be a curse from the Christ for my brethren, my kinsmen, according to flesh; 4 who are Israelites; whose is the adoption, and the glory, and the covenants, and the law-giving, and the service, and the promises; 5 whose are the fathers; and of whom, as according to flesh, is the Christ, who is over all, God blessed for ever. Amen.

6 Not however as though the word of God had failed; for not all are Israel which are of Israel; 7 nor because they are seed of Abraham are all children: but, In Isaac shall a seed be called to thee. 8 That is, they that are the children of the flesh, these are not the children of God; but the children of the promise are reckoned as seed. 9 For this word is of promise, According to this time I will come, and there shall be a son to Sarah. 10 And not only that, but Rebecca having conceived by one, Isaac our father, 11 the children indeed being not yet born, or having done anything good or worthless (that the purpose of God according to election might abide, not of works, but of him that calls), 12 it was said to her, The greater shall serve the less: 13 according as it is written, I have loved Jacob, and I have hated Esau.

14 What shall we say then? Is there unrighteousness with God? Far be the thought. 15 For he says to Moses, I will shew mercy to whom I will shew mercy, and I will feel compassion for whom I will feel compassion. 16 So then it is not of him that wills, nor of him that runs, but of God that shews mercy. 17 For the scripture says to Pharaoh, For this very thing I have raised thee up from amongst men, that I might thus shew in thee my power, and so that my name should be declared in all the earth. 18 So then, to whom he will he shews mercy, and whom he will he hardens. 19 Thou wilt say to me then, Why does he yet find fault? for who resists his purpose? 20 Aye, but thou, O man, who art thou that answerest again to God? Shall the thing formed say to him that has formed it, Why hast thou made me thus? 21 Or has not the potter authority over the clay, out of the same lump to make one vessel to honour, and another to dishonour? 22 And if God, minded to shew his wrath and to make his power known, endured with much long-suffering vessels of wrath fitted for destruction; 23 and that he might make known the riches of his glory upon vessels of mercy, which he had before prepared for glory, 24 us, whom he has also called, not only from amongst the Jews, but also from amongst the nations?

25 As he says also in Hosea, I will call not-my-people My people; and the-not-beloved Beloved. 26 And it shall be, in the place where it was said to them, Ye are not my people, there shall they be called Sons of the living God. 27 But Esaias cries concerning Israel, Should the number of the children of Israel be as the sand of the sea, the remnant shall be saved: 28 for he is bringing the matter to an end, and cutting it short in righteousness; because a cutting short of the matter will the Lord accomplish upon the earth. 29 And according as Esaias said before, Unless the Lord of hosts had left us a seed, we had been as Sodom, and made like even as Gomorrha.

30 What then shall we say? That they of the nations, who did not follow after righteousness, have attained righteousness, but the righteousness that is on the principle of faith. 31 But Israel, pursuing after a law of righteousness, has not attained to that law. 32 Wherefore? Because it was not on the principle of faith, but as of works. They have stumbled at the stumblingstone, 33 according as it is written, Behold, I place in Zion a stone of stumbling and rock of offence: and he that believes on him shall not be ashamed.

Romans 10

1 Brethren, the delight of my own heart and my supplication which I address to God for them is for salvation. 2 For I bear them witness that they have zeal for God, but not according to knowledge. 3 For they, being ignorant of God's righteousness, and seeking to establish their own righteousness, have not submitted to the righteousness of God. 4 For Christ is the end of law for righteousness to every one that believes. 5 For Moses lays down in writing the righteousness which is of the law, The man who has practised those things shall live by them. 6 But the righteousness of faith speaks thus: Do not say in thine heart, Who shall ascend to the heavens? that is, to bring Christ down; 7 or, Who shall descend into the abyss? that is, to bring up Christ from among the dead. 8 But what says it? The word is near thee, in thy mouth and in thy heart: that is, the word of faith, which we preach: 9 that if thou shalt confess with thy mouth Jesus as Lord, and shalt believe in thine heart that God has raised him from among the dead, thou shalt be saved. 10 For with the heart is believed to righteousness; and with the mouth confession made to salvation. 11 For the scripture says, No one believing on him shall be ashamed.

12 For there is no difference of Jew and Greek; for the same Lord of all is rich towards all that call upon him. 13 For every one whosoever, who shall call on the name of the Lord, shall be saved. 14 How then shall they call upon him in whom they have not believed? and how shall they believe on him of whom they have not heard? and how shall they hear without one who preaches? 15 and how shall they preach unless they have been sent? according as it is written, How beautiful the feet of them that announce glad tidings of peace, of them that announce glad tidings of good things! 16 But they have not all obeyed the glad tidings. For Esaias says, Lord, who has believed our report? 17 So faith then is by a report, but the report by God's word. 18 But I say, Have they not heard? Yea, surely, Their voice has gone out into all the earth, and their words to the extremities of the habitable world. 19 But I say, Has not Israel known? First, Moses says, I will provoke you to jealousy through them that are not a nation: through a nation without understanding I will anger you. 20 But Esaias is very bold, and says, I have been found by those not seeking me; I have become manifest to those not inquiring after me. 21 But unto Israel he says, All the day long I have stretched out my hands unto a people disobeying and opposing.

Romans 11

1 I say then, Has God cast away his people? Far be the thought. For I also am an Israelite, of the seed of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin. 2 God has not cast away his people whom he foreknew. Know ye not what the scripture says in the history of Elias, how he pleads with God against Israel? 3 Lord, they have killed thy prophets, they have dug down thine altars; and I have been left alone, and they seek my life. 4 But what says the divine answer to him? I have left to myself seven thousand men, who have not bowed knee to Baal. 5 Thus, then, in the present time also there has been a remnant according to election of grace. 6 But if by grace, no longer of works: since otherwise grace is no more grace. 7 What is it then? What Israel seeks for, that he has not obtained; but the election has obtained, and the rest have been blinded, 8 according as it is written, God has given to them a spirit of slumber, eyes not to see, and ears not to hear, unto this day. 9 And David says, Let their table be for a snare, and for a gin, and for a fall-trap, and for a recompense to them: 10 let their eyes be darkened not to see, and bow down their back alway. 11 I say then, Have they stumbled in order that they might fall? Far be the thought: but by their fall there is salvation to the nations to provoke them to jealousy. 12 But if their fall be the world's wealth, and their loss the wealth of the nations, how much rather their fulness? 13 For I speak to you, the nations, inasmuch as I am apostle of nations, I glorify my ministry; 14 if by any means I shall provoke to jealousy them which are my flesh, and shall save some from among them. 15 For if their casting away be the world's reconciliation, what their reception but life from among the dead? 16 Now if the first-fruit be holy, the lump also; and if the root be holy, the branches also. 17 Now if some of the branches have been broken out, and thou, being a wild olive tree, hast been grafted in amongst them, and hast become a fellow-partaker of the root and of the fatness of the olive tree, 18 boast not against the branches; but if thou boast, it is not thou bearest the root, but the root thee. 19 Thou wilt say then, The branches have been broken out in order that I might be grafted in. 20 Right: they have been broken out through unbelief, and thou standest through faith. Be not high-minded, but fear: 21 if God indeed has not spared the natural branches; lest it might be he spare not thee either. 22 Behold then the goodness and severity of God: upon them who have fallen, severity; upon thee goodness of God, if thou shalt abide in goodness, since otherwisethou also wilt be cut away. 23 And they too, if they abide not in unbelief, shall be grafted in; for God is able again to graft them in. 24 For if thou hast been cut out of the olive tree wild by nature, and, contrary to nature, hast been grafted into the good olive tree, how much rather shall they, who are according to nature be grafted into their own olive tree? 25 For I do not wish you to be ignorant, brethren, of this mystery, that ye may not be wise in your own conceits, that blindness in part is happened to Israel, until the fulness of the nations be come in; 26 and so all Israel shall be saved. According as it is written, The deliverer shall come out of Zion; he shall turn away ungodliness from Jacob. 27 And this is the covenant from me to them, when I shall have taken away their sins. 28 As regards the glad tidings, they are enemies on your account; but as regards election, beloved on account of the fathers. 29 For the gifts and the calling of God are not subject to repentance. 30 For as indeed ye also once have not believed in God, but now have been objects of mercy through the unbelief of these; 31 so these also have now not believed in your mercy, in order that they also may be objects of mercy. 32 For God hath shut up together all in unbelief, in order that he might shew mercy to all.

33 O depth of riches both of the wisdom and knowledge of God! how unsearchable his judgments, and untraceable his ways! 34 For who has known the mind of the Lord, or who has been his counsellor? 35 or who has first given to him, and it shall be rendered to him?

Romans 12

1 I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the compassions of God, to present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable to God, which is your intelligent service. 2 And be not conformed to this world, but be transformed by the renewing of your mind, that ye may prove what is the good and acceptable and perfect will of God. 3 For I say, through the grace which has been given to me, to every one that is among you, not to have high thoughts above what he should think; but to think so as to be wise, as God has dealt to each a measure of faith. 4 For, as in one body we have many members, but all the members have not the same office; 5 thus we, being many, are one body in Christ, and each one members one of the other. 6 But having different gifts, according to the grace which has been given to us, whether it be prophecy, let us prophesy according to the proportion of faith; 7 or service, let us occupy ourselves in service; or he that teaches, in teaching; 8 or he that exhorts, in exhortation; he that gives, in simplicity; he that leads, with diligence; he that shews mercy, with cheerfulness. 9 Let love be unfeigned; abhorring evil; cleaving to good: 10 as to brotherly love, kindly affectioned towards one another: as to honour, each taking the lead in paying it to the other: 11 as to diligent zealousness, not slothful; in spirit fervent; serving the Lord. 12 As regards hope, rejoicing: as regards tribulation, enduring: as regards prayer, persevering: 13 distributing to the necessities of the saints; given to hospitality. 14 Bless them that persecute you; bless, and curse not. 15 Rejoice with those that rejoice, weep with those that weep. 16 Have the same respect one for another, not minding high things, but going along with the lowly: be not wise in your own eyes: 17 recompensing to no one evil for evil: providing things honest before all men: 18 if possible, as far as depends on you, living in peace with all men; 19 not avenging yourselves, beloved, but give place to wrath; for it is written, Vengeance belongs to me, I will recompense, saith the Lord. 20 If therefore thine enemy should hunger, feed him; if he should thirst, give him drink; for, so doing, thou shalt heap coals of fire upon his head. 21 Be not overcome by evil, but overcome evil with good.

Romans 13

1 Let every soul be subject to the authorities that are above him. For there is no authority except from God; and those that exist are set up by God. 2 So that he that sets himself in opposition to the authority resists the ordinance of God; and they who thus resist shall bring sentence of guilt on themselves. 3 For rulers are not a terror to a good work, but to an evil one. Dost thou desire then not to be afraid of the authority? practise what is good, and thou shalt have praise from it; 4 for it is God's minister to thee for good. But if thou practisest evil, fear; for it bears not the sword in vain; for it is God's minister, an avenger for wrath to him that does evil. 5 Wherefore it is necessary to be subject, not only on account of wrath, but also on account of conscience. 6 For on this account ye pay tribute also; for they are God's officers, attending continually on this very thing.

7 Render to all their dues: to whom tribute is due, tribute; to whom custom, custom; to whom fear, fear; to whom honour, honour. 8 Owe no one anything, unless to love one another: for he that loves another has fulfilled the law. 9 For, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not kill, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not lust; and if there be any other commandment, it is summed up in this word, namely, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself. 10 Love works no ill to its neighbour; love therefore is the whole law.

11 This also, knowing the time, that it is already time that we should be aroused out of sleep; for now is our salvation nearer than when we believed. 12 The night is far spent, and the day is near; let us cast away therefore the works of darkness, and let us put on the armour of light. 13 As in the day, let us walk becomingly; not in rioting and drunkenness, not in chambering and lasciviousness, not in strife and emulation. 14 But put on the Lord Jesus Christ, and do not take forethought for the flesh to fulfil its lusts.

Romans 14

1 Now him that is weak in the faith receive, not to the determining of questions of reasoning. 2 One man is assured that he may eat all things; but the weak eats herbs. 3 Let not him that eats make little of him that eats not; and let not him that eats not judge him that eats: for God has received him. 4 Who art thou that judgest the servant of another? to his own master he stands or falls. And he shall be made to stand; for the Lord is able to make him stand. 5 One man esteems day more than day; another esteems every day alike. Let each be fully persuaded in his own mind. 6 He that regards the day, regards it to the Lord. And he that eats, eats to the Lord, for he gives God thanks; and he that does not eat, it is to the Lord he does not eat, and gives God thanks. 7 For none of us lives to himself, and none dies to himself. 8 For both if we should live, it is to the Lord we live; and if we should die, it is to the Lord we die: both if we should live then, and if we should die, we are the Lord's. 9 For to this end Christ has died and lived again, that he might rule over both dead and living. 10 But thou, why judgest thou thy brother? or again, thou, why dost thou make little of thy brother? for we shall all be placed before the judgment-seat of God. 11 For it is written, I live, saith the Lord, that to me shall bow every knee, and every tongue shall confess to God. 12 So then each of us shall give an account concerning himself to God. 13 Let us no longer therefore judge one another; but judge ye this rather, not to put a stumbling-block or a fall-trap before his brother. 14 I know, and am persuaded in the Lord Jesus, that nothing is unclean of itself; except to him who reckons anything to be unclean, to that man it is unclean. 15 For if on account of meat thy brother is grieved, thou walkest no longer according to love. Destroy not him with thy meat for whom Christ has died. 16 Let not then your good be evil spoken of; 17 for the kingdom of God is not eating and drinking, but righteousness, and peace, and joy in the Holy Spirit. 18 For he that in this serves the Christ is acceptable to God and approved of men. 19 So then let us pursue the things which tend to peace, and things whereby one shall build up another. 20 For the sake of meat do not destroy the work of God. All things indeed are pure; but it is evil to that man who eats while stumbling in doing so. 21 It is right not to eat meat, nor drink wine, nor do anything in which thy brother stumbles, or is offended, or is weak. 22 Hast thou faith? have it to thyself before God. Blessed is he who does not judge himself in what he allows. 23 But he that doubts, if he eat, is condemned; because it is not of faith; but whatever is not of faith is sin.

Romans 15

1 But we ought, we that are strong, to bear the infirmities of the weak, and not to please ourselves. 2 Let each one of us please his neighbour with a view to what is good, to edification. 3 For the Christ also did not please himself; but according as it is written, The reproaches of them that reproach thee have fallen upon me. 4 For as many things as have been written before have been written for our instruction, that through endurance and through encouragement of the scriptures we might have hope.

5 Now the God of endurance and of encouragement give to you to be like-minded one toward another, according to Christ Jesus; 6 that ye may with one accord, with one mouth, glorify the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.

7 Wherefore receive ye one another, according as the Christ also has received you to the glory of God. 8 For I say that Jesus Christ became a minister of the circumcision for the truth of God, to confirm the promises of the fathers; 9 and that the nations should glorify God for mercy; according as it is written, For this cause I will confess to thee among the nations, and will sing to thy name. 10 And again he says, Rejoice, nations, with his people. 11 And again, Praise the Lord, all ye nations, and let all the peoples laud him. 12 And again, Esaias says, There shall be the root of Jesse, and one that arises, to rule over the nations: in him shall the nations hope.

13 Now the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, so that ye should abound in hope by the power of the Holy Spirit.

14 But I am persuaded, my brethren, I myself also, concerning you, that yourselves also are full of goodness, filled with all knowledge, able also to admonish one another. 15 But I have written to you the more boldly, brethren, in part, as putting you in mind, because of the grace given to me by God, 16 for me to be minister of Christ Jesus to the nations, carrying on as a sacrificial service the message of glad tidings of God, in order that the offering up of the nations might be acceptable, sanctified by the Holy Spirit.

17 I have therefore whereof to boast in Christ Jesus in the things which pertain to God. 18 For I will not dare to speak anything of the things which Christ has not wrought by me, for the obedience of the nations, by word and deed, 19 in the power of signs and wonders, in the power of the Spirit of God; so that I, from Jerusalem, and in a circuit round to Illyricum, have fully preached the glad tidings of the Christ; 20 and so aiming to announce the glad tidings, not where Christ has been named, that I might not build upon another's foundation; 21 but according as it is written, To whom there was nothing told concerning him, they shall see; and they that have not heard shall understand.

22 Wherefore also I have been often hindered from coming to you. 23 But now, having no longer place in these regions, and having great desire to come to you these many years, 24 whenever I should go to Spain; (for I hope to see you as I go through, and by you to be set forward thither, if first I shall have been in part filled with your company;) 25 but now I go to Jerusalem, ministering to the saints; 26 for Macedonia and Achaia have been well pleased to make a certain contribution for the poor of the saints who are in Jerusalem. 27 They have been well pleased indeed, and they are their debtors; for if the nations have participated in their spiritual things, they ought also in fleshly to minister to them. 28 Having finished this therefore, and having sealed to them this fruit, I will set off by you into Spain. 29 But I know that, coming to you, I shall come in the fulness of the blessing of Christ.

30 But I beseech you, brethren, by our Lord Jesus Christ, and by the love of the Spirit, that ye strive together with me in prayers for me to God; 31 that I may be saved from those that do not believe in Judaea; and that my ministry which I have for Jerusalem may be acceptable to the saints; 32 in order that I may come to you in joy by God's will, and that I may be refreshed with you. 33 And the God of peace be with you all. Amen.

Romans 16

1 But I commend to you Phoebe, our sister, who is minister of the assembly which is in Cenchrea; 2 that ye may receive her in the Lord worthily of saints, and that ye may assist her in whatever matter she has need of you; for she also has been a helper of many, and of myself. 3 Salute Prisca and Aquila, my fellow-workmen in Christ Jesus, 4 (who for my life staked their own neck; to whom not I only am thankful, but also all the assemblies of the nations,) 5 and the assembly at their house. Salute Epaenetus, my beloved, who is the first-fruits of Asia for Christ. 6 Salute Maria, who laboured much for you. 7 Salute Andronicus and Junias, my kinsmen and fellow-captives, who are of note among the apostles; who were also in Christ before me. 8 Salute Amplias, my beloved in the Lord. 9 Salute Urbanus, our fellow-workman in Christ, and Stachys, my beloved. 10 Salute Apelles, approved in Christ. Salute those who belong to Aristobulus. 11 Salute Herodion, my kinsman. Salute those who belong to Narcissus, who are in the Lord. 12 Salute Tryphaena and Tryphosa, who labour in the Lord. Salute Persis, the beloved, who has laboured much in the Lord. 13 Salute Rufus, chosen in the Lord; and his mother and mine. 14 Salute Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermes, Patrobas, Hermas, and the brethren with them. 15 Salute Philologus, and Julia, Nereus, and his sister, and Olympas, and all the saints with them. 16 Salute one another with a holy kiss. All the assemblies of Christ salute you.

17 But I beseech you, brethren, to consider those who create divisions and occasions of falling, contrary to the doctrine which ye have learnt, and turn away from them. 18 For such serve not our Lord Christ, but their own belly, and by good words and fair speeches deceive the hearts of the unsuspecting. 19 For your obedience has reached to all. I rejoice therefore as it regards you; but I wish you to be wise as to that which is good, and simple as to evil. 20 But the God of peace shall bruise Satan under your feet shortly. The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.

21 Timotheus, my fellow-workman, and Lucius, and Jason, and Sosipater, my kinsmen, salute you. 22 I Tertius, who have written this epistle, salute you in the Lord. 23 Gaius, my host and of the whole assembly, salutes you. Erastus, the steward of the city, salutes you, and the brother Quartus. 24 The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.

25 Now to him that is able to establish you, according to my glad tidings and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the mystery, as to which silence has been kept in the times of the ages, 26 but which has now been made manifest, and by prophetic scriptures, according to commandment of the eternal God, made known for obedience of faith to all the nations-- 27 the only wise God, through Jesus Christ, to whom be glory for ever. Amen.

1 Corinthians 1

1 Paul, a called apostle of Jesus Christ, by God's will, and Sosthenes the brother, 2 to the assembly of God which is in Corinth, to those sanctified in Christ Jesus, called saints, with all that in every place call on the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, both theirs and ours: 3 Grace to you and peace from God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ. 4 I thank my God always about you, in respect of the grace of God given to you in Christ Jesus; 5 that in everything ye have been enriched in him, in all word of doctrine, and all knowledge, 6 (according as the testimony of the Christ has been confirmed in you,) 7 so that ye come short in no gift, awaiting the revelation of our Lord Jesus Christ; 8 who shall also confirm you to the end, unimpeachable in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ. 9 God is faithful, by whom ye have been called into the fellowship of his Son Jesus Christ our Lord.

10 Now I exhort you, brethren, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye all say the same thing, and that there be not among you divisions; but that ye be perfectly united in the same mind and in the same opinion. 11 For it has been shewn to me concerning you, my brethren, by those of the house of Chloe, that there are strifes among you. 12 But I speak of this, that each of you says, I am of Paul, and I of Apollos, and I of Cephas, and I of Christ. 13 Is the Christ divided? has Paul been crucified for you? or have ye been baptised unto the name of Paul?

14 I thank God that I have baptised none of you, unless Crispus and Gaius, 15 that no one may say that I have baptised unto my own name. 16 Yes, I baptised also the house of Stephanas; for the rest I know not if I have baptised any other.

17 For Christ has not sent me to baptise, but to preach glad tidings; not in wisdom of word, that the cross of the Christ may not be made vain. 18 For the word of the cross is to them that perish foolishness, but to us that are saved it is God's power. 19 For it is written, I will destroy the wisdom of the wise, and set aside the understanding of the understanding ones. 20 Where is the wise? where scribe? where disputer of this world? has not God made foolish the wisdom of the world? 21 For since, in the wisdom of God, the world by wisdom has not known God, God has been pleased by the foolishness of the preaching to save those that believe. 22 Since Jews indeed ask for signs, and Greeks seek wisdom; 23 but we preach Christ crucified, to Jews an offence, and to nations foolishness; 24 but to those that are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ God's power and God's wisdom. 25 Because the foolishness of God is wiser than men, and the weakness of God is stronger than men. 26 For consider your calling, brethren, that there are not many wise according to flesh, not many powerful, not many high-born. 27 But God has chosen the foolish things of the world, that he may put to shame the wise; and God has chosen the weak things of the world, that he may put to shame the strong things; 28 and the ignoble things of the world, and the despised, has God chosen, and things that are not, that he may annul the things that are; 29 so that no flesh should boast before God. 30 But of him are ye in Christ Jesus, who has been made to us wisdom from God, and righteousness, and holiness, and redemption; 31 that according as it is written, He that boasts, let him boast in the Lord.

1 Corinthians 3

1 And I, brethren, have not been able to speak to you as to spiritual, but as to fleshly; as to babes in Christ. 2 I have given you milk to drink, not meat, for ye have not yet been able, nor indeed are ye yet able; 3 for ye are yet carnal. For whereas there are among you emulation and strife, are ye not carnal, and walk according to man? 4 For when one says, I am of Paul, and another, I of Apollos, are ye not men?

5 Who then is Apollos, and who Paul? Ministering servants, through whom ye have believed, and as the Lord has given to each. 6 I have planted; Apollos watered; but God has given the increase. 7 So that neither the planter is anything, nor the waterer; but God the giver of the increase. 8 But the planter and the waterer are one; but each shall receive his own reward according to his own labour. 9 For we are God's fellow-workmen; ye are God's husbandry, God's building. 10 According to the grace of God which has been given to me, as a wise architect, I have laid the foundation, but another builds upon it. But let each see how he builds upon it.

11 For other foundation can no man lay besides that which is laid, which is Jesus Christ. 12 Now if any one build upon this foundation, gold, silver, precious stones, wood, grass, straw, 13 the work of each shall be made manifest; for the day shall declare it, because it is revealed in fire; and the fire shall try the work of each what it is. 14 If the work of any one which he has built upon the foundation shall abide, he shall receive a reward. 15 If the work of any one shall be consumed, he shall suffer loss, but he shall be saved, but so as through the fire.

16 Do ye not know that ye are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwells in you? 17 If any one corrupt the temple of God, him shall God destroy; for the temple of God is holy, and such are ye.

18 Let no one deceive himself: if any one thinks himself to be wise among you in this world, let him become foolish, that he may be wise. 19 For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God; for it is written, He who takes the wise in their craftiness. 20 And again, The Lord knows the reasonings of the wise that they are vain.

21 So that let no one boast in men; for all things are yours. 22 Whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things present, or things coming, all are yours; 23 and ye are Christ's, and Christ is God's.

1 Corinthians 4

1 Let a man so account of us as servants of Christ, and stewards of the mysteries of God. 2 Here, further, it is sought in stewards, that a man be found faithful. 3 But for me it is the very smallest matter that I be examined of you or of man's day. Nor do I even examine myself. 4 For I am conscious of nothing in myself; but I am not justified by this: but he that examines me is the Lord. 5 So that do not judge anything before the time, until the Lord shall come, who shall also both bring to light the hidden things of darkness, and shall make manifest the counsels of hearts; and then shall each have hispraise from God. 6 Now these things, brethren, I have transferred, in their application, to myself and Apollos, for your sakes, that ye may learn in us the lesson of not letting your thoughts goabove what is written, that ye may not be puffed up one for such a one against another.

7 For who makes thee to differ? and what hast thou which thou hast not received? but if also thou hast received, why boastest thou as not receiving? 8 Already ye are filled; already ye have been enriched; ye have reigned without us; and I would that ye reigned, that we also might reign with you. 9 For I think that God has set us the apostles for the last, as appointed to death. For we have become a spectacle to the world, both to angels and men. 10 We are fools for Christ's sake, but ye prudent in Christ: we weak, but ye strong: ye glorious, but we in dishonour. 11 To the present hour we both hunger and thirst, and are in nakedness, and buffeted, and wander without a home, 12 and labour, working with our own hands. Railed at, we bless; persecuted, we suffer it; 13 insulted, we entreat: we are become as the offscouring of the world, the refuse of all, until now.

14 Not as chiding do I write these things to you, but as my beloved children I admonish you. 15 For if ye should have ten thousand instructors in Christ, yet not many fathers; for in Christ Jesus I have begotten you through the glad tidings. 16 I entreat you therefore, be my imitators.

17 For this reason I have sent to you Timotheus, who is my beloved and faithful child in the Lord, who shall put you in mind of my ways as they are in Christ, according as I teach everywhere in every assembly. 18 But some have been puffed up, as if I were not coming to you; 19 but I will come quickly to you, if the Lord will; and I will know, not the word of those that are puffed up, but the power. 20 For the kingdom of God is not in word, but in power. 21 What will ye? that I come to you with a rod; or in love, and in a spirit of meekness?

1 Corinthians 5

1 It is universally reported that there is fornication among you, and such fornication as is not even among the nations, so that one should have his father's wife. 2 And ye are puffed up, and ye have not rather mourned, in order that he that has done this deed might be taken away out of the midst of you. 3 For I, as absent in body but present in spirit, have already judged as present, 4 to deliver, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ (ye and my spirit being gathered together, with the power of our Lord Jesus Christ), him that has so wrought this: 5 to deliver him, I say, being such, to Satan for destruction of the flesh, that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus. 6 Your boasting is not good. Do ye not know that a little leaven leavens the whole lump?

7 Purge out the old leaven, that ye may be a new lump, according as ye are unleavened. For also our passover, Christ, has been sacrificed; 8 so that let us celebrate the feast, not with old leaven, nor with leaven of malice and wickedness, but with unleavened bread of sincerity and truth.

9 I have written to you in the epistle not to mix with fornicators; 10 not altogether with the fornicators of this world, or with the avaricious and rapacious, or idolaters, since then ye should go out of the world. 11 But now I have written to you, if any one called brother be fornicator, or avaricious, or idolater, or abusive, or a drunkard, or rapacious, not to mix with him; with such a one not even to eat. 12 For what have I to do with judging those outside also? ye, do not ye judge them that are within? 13 But those without God judges. Remove the wicked person from amongst yourselves.

1 Corinthians 6

1 Dare any one of you, having a matter against another, prosecute his suit before the unjust, and not before the saints? 2 Do ye not then know that the saints shall judge the world? and if the world is judged by you, are ye unworthy of the smallest judgments? 3 Do ye not know that we shall judge angels? and not then matters of this life? 4 If then ye have judgments as to things of this life, set those to judge who are little esteemed in the assembly. 5 I speak to you to put you to shame. Thus there is not a wise person among you, not even one, who shall be able to decide between his brethren! 6 But brother prosecutes his suit with brother, and that before unbelievers. 7 Already indeed then it is altogether a fault in you that ye have suits between yourselves. Why do ye not rather suffer wrong? why are ye not rather defrauded? 8 But ye do wrong, and defraud, and this your brethren.

9 Do ye not know that unrighteous persons shall not inherit the kingdom of God? Do not err: neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor those who make women of themselves, nor who abuse themselves with men, 10 nor thieves, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor abusive persons, nor the rapacious, shall inherit the kingdom of God. 11 And these things were some of you; but ye have been washed, but ye have been sanctified, but ye have been justified in the name of the Lord Jesus, and by the Spirit of our God.

12 All things are lawful to me, but all things do not profit; all things are lawful to me, but I will not be brought under the power of any. 13 Meats for the belly, and the belly for meats; but God will bring to nothing both it and them: but the body is not for fornication, but for the Lord, and the Lord for the body. 14 And God has both raised up the Lord, and will raise us up from among the dead by his power. 15 Do ye not know that your bodies are members of Christ? Shall I then, taking the members of the Christ, make them members of a harlot? Far be the thought. 16 Do ye not know that he that is joined to the harlot is one body? for the two, he says, shall be one flesh. 17 But he that is joined to the Lord is one Spirit. 18 Flee fornication. Every sin which a man may practise is without the body, but he that commits fornication sins against his own body. 19 Do ye not know that your body is the temple of the Holy Spirit which is in you, which ye have of God; and ye are not your own? 20 for ye have been bought with a price: glorify now then God in your body.

1 Corinthians 7

1 But concerning the things of which ye have written to me: It is good for a man not to touch a woman; 2 but on account of fornications, let each have his own wife, and each woman have her own husband. 3 Let the husband render her due to the wife, and in like manner the wife to the husband. 4 The wife has not authority over her own body, but the husband: in like manner also the husband has not authority over his own body, but the wife. 5 Defraud not one another, unless, it may be, by consent for a time, that ye may devote yourselves to prayer, and again be together, that Satan tempt you not because of your incontinency. 6 But this I say, as consenting to, not as commanding it. 7 Now I wish all men to be even as myself: but every one has his own gift of God: one man thus, and another thus. 8 But I say to the unmarried and to the widows, It is good for them that they remain even as I. 9 But if they have not control over themselves, let them marry; for it is better to marry than to burn.

10 But to the married I enjoin, not I, but the Lord, Let not wife be separated from husband; 11 (but if also she shall have been separated, let her remain unmarried, or be reconciled to her husband;) and let not husband leave wife. 12 But as to the rest, I say, not the Lord, If any brother have an unbelieving wife, and she consent to dwell with him, let him not leave her. 13 And a woman who has an unbelieving husband, and he consents to dwell with her, let her not leave her husband. 14 For the unbelieving husband is sanctified in the wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified in the brother; since otherwise indeed your children are unclean, but now they are holy. 15 But if the unbeliever go away, let them go away; a brother or a sister is not bound in such cases, but God has called us in peace. 16 For what knowest thou, O wife, if thou shalt save thy husband? or what knowest thou, O husband, if thou shalt save thy wife?

17 However, as the Lord has divided to each, as God has called each, so let him walk; and thus I ordain in all the assemblies. 18 Has any one been called circumcised? let him not become uncircumcised: has any one been called in uncircumcision? let him not be circumcised. 19 Circumcision is nothing, and uncircumcision is nothing; but keeping God's commandments. 20 Let each abide in that calling in which he has been called. 21 Hast thou been called being a bondman, let it not concern thee; but and if thou canst become free, use it rather. 22 For the bondman that is called in the Lord is the Lord's freedman; in like manner also the freeman being called is Christ's bondman. 23 Ye have been bought with a price; do not be the bondmen of men. 24 Let each, wherein he is called, brethren, therein abide with God.

25 But concerning virgins, I have no commandment of the Lord; but I give my opinion, as having received mercy of the Lord to be faithful. 26 I think then that this is good, on account of the present necessity, that it is good for a man to remain so as he is. 27 Art thou bound to a wife? seek not to be loosed; art thou free from a wife? do not seek a wife. 28 But if thou shouldest also marry, thou hast not sinned; and if the virgin marry, they have not sinned: but such shall have tribulation in the flesh; but I spare you. 29 But this I say, brethren, the time is straitened. For the rest, that they who have wives, be as not having any: 30 and they that weep, as not weeping; and they that rejoice, as not rejoicing; and they that buy, as not possessing; 31 and they that use the world, as not disposing of it as their own; for the fashion of this world passes. 32 But I wish you to be without care. The unmarried cares for the things of the Lord, how he shall please the Lord; 33 but he that has married cares for the things of the world, how he shall please his wife. 34 There is a difference between the wife and the virgin. The unmarried cares for the things of the Lord, that she may be holy both in body and spirit; but she that has married cares for the things of the world, how she shall please her husband. 35 But I say this for your own profit; not that I may set a snare before you, but for what is seemly, and waiting on the Lord without distraction.

36 But if any one think that he behaves unseemly to his virginity, if he be beyond the flower of his age, and so it must be, let him do what he will, he does not sin: let them marry. 37 But he who stands firm in his heart, having no need, but has authority over his own will, and has judged this in his heart to keep his own virginity, he does well. 38 So that he that marries himself does well; and he that does not marry does better.

39 A wife is bound for whatever time her husband lives; but if the husband be fallen asleep, she is free to be married to whom she will, only in the Lord. 40 But she is happier if she so remain, according to my judgment; but I think that I also have God's Spirit.

1 Corinthians 8

1 But concerning things sacrificed to idols, we know, (for we all have knowledge: knowledge puffs up, but love edifies. 2 If any one think he knows anything, he knows nothing yet as he ought to know it. 3 But if any one love God, he is known of him):

4 --concerning then the eating of things sacrificed to idols, we know that an idol is nothing in the world, and that there is no other God save one. 5 For and if indeed there are those called gods, whether in heaven or on earth, (as there are gods many, and lords many,) 6 yet to us there is one God, the Father, of whom all things, and we for him; and one Lord, Jesus Christ, by whom are all things, and we by him.

7 But knowledge is not in all: but some, with conscience of the idol, until now eat as of a thing sacrificed to idols; and their conscience, being weak, is defiled. 8 But meat does not commend us to God; neither if we should not eat do we come short; nor if we should eat have we an advantage. 9 But see lest anywise this your right to eat itself be a stumbling-block to the weak. 10 For if any one see thee, who hast knowledge, sitting at table in an idol-house, shall not his conscience, he being weak, be emboldened to eat the things sacrificed to the idol? 11 and the weak one, the brother for whose sake Christ died, will perish through thy knowledge. 12 Now, thus sinning against the brethren, and wounding their weak conscience, ye sin against Christ. 13 Wherefore if meat be a fall-trap to my brother, I will eat no flesh for ever, that I may not be a fall-trap to my brother.

1 Corinthians 9

1 Am I not free? am I not an apostle? have I not seen Jesus our Lord? are not ye my work in the Lord? 2 If I am not an apostle to others, yet at any rate I am to you: for the seal of mine apostleship are ye in the Lord.

3 My defence to those who examine me is this: 4 Have we not a right to eat and to drink? 5 have we not a right to take round a sister as wife, as also the other apostles, and the brethren of the Lord, and Cephas? 6 Or I alone and Barnabas, have we not a right not to work? 7 Who ever carries on war at his own charges? who plants a vineyard and does not eat of its fruit? or who herds a flock and does not eat of the milk of the flock? 8 Do I speak these things as a man, or does not the law also say these things? 9 For in the law of Moses it is written, Thou shalt not muzzle the ox that is treading out corn. Is God occupied about the oxen, 10 or does he say it altogether for our sakes? For for our sakes it has been written, that the plougher should plough in hope, and he that treads out corn, in hope of partaking of it. 11 If we have sown to you spiritual things, is it a great thing if we shall reap your carnal things? 12 If others partake of this right over you, should not rather we? But we have not used this right, but we bear all things, that we may put no hindrance in the way of the glad tidings of the Christ. 13 Do ye not know that they who labour at sacred things eat of the offerings offered in the temple; they that attend at the altar partake with the altar? 14 So also the Lord has ordained to those that announce the glad tidings to live of the glad tidings.

15 But I have used none of these things. Now I have not written these things that it should be thus in my case; for it were good for me rather to die than that any one should make vain my boast. 16 For if I announce the glad tidings, I have nothing to boast of; for a necessity is laid upon me; for it is woe to me if I should not announce the glad tidings. 17 For if I do this voluntarily, I have a reward; but if not of my own will, I am entrusted with an administration. 18 What is the reward then that I have? That in announcing the glad tidings I make the glad tidings costless to others, so as not to have made use, as belonging to me, of my right in announcing the glad tidings.

19 For being free from all, I have made myself bondman to all, that I might gain the most possible. 20 And I became to the Jews as a Jew, in order that I might gain the Jews: to those under law, as under law, not being myself under law, in order that I might gain those under law: 21 to those without law, as without law, (not as without law to God, but as legitimately subject to Christ,) in order that I might gain those without law. 22 I became to the weak, as weak, in order that I might gain the weak. To all I have become all things, in order that at all events I might save some. 23 And I do all things for the sake of the glad tidings, that I may be fellow-partaker with them.

24 Know ye not that they who run in the race-course run all, but one receives the prize? Thus run in order that ye may obtain. 25 But every one that contends for a prize is temperate in all things: they then indeed that they may receive a corruptible crown, but we an incorruptible. 26 I therefore thus run, as not uncertainly; so I combat, as not beating the air. 27 But I buffet my body, and lead it captive, lest after having preached to others I should be myself rejected.

1 Corinthians 10

1 For I would not have you ignorant, brethren, that all our fathers were under the cloud, and all passed through the sea; 2 and all were baptised unto Moses in the cloud and in the sea; 3 and all ate the same spiritual food, 4 and all drank the same spiritual drink, for they drank of a spiritual rock which followed them: (now the rock was the Christ;) 5 yet God was not pleased with the most of them, for they were strewed in the desert.

6 But these things happened as types of us, that we should not be lusters after evil things, as they also lusted. 7 Neither be ye idolaters, as some of them; as it is written, The people sat down to eat and to drink, and rose up to play. 8 Neither let us commit fornication, as some of them committed fornication, and fell in one day three and twenty thousand. 9 Neither let us tempt the Christ, as some of them tempted, and perished by serpents. 10 Neither murmur ye, as some of them murmured, and perished by the destroyer. 11 Now all these things happened to them as types, and have been written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the ages are come. 12 So that let him that thinks that he stands take heed lest he fall. 13 No temptation has taken you but such as is according to man's nature; and God is faithful, who will not suffer you to be tempted above what ye are able to bear, but will with the temptation make the issue also, so that yeshould be able to bear it. 14 Wherefore, my beloved, flee from idolatry.

15 I speak as to intelligent persons: do ye judge what I say. 16 The cup of blessing which we bless, is it not the communion of the blood of the Christ? The bread which we break, is it not the communion of the body of the Christ? 17 Because we, being many, are one loaf, one body; for we all partake of that one loaf. 18 See Israel according to flesh: are not they who eat the sacrifices in communion with the altar? 19 What then do I say? that what is sacrificed to an idol is anything, or that an idol is anything? 20 But that what the nations sacrifice they sacrifice to demons, and not to God. Now I do not wish you to be in communion with demons. 21 Ye cannot drink the Lord's cup, and the cup of demons: ye cannot partake of the Lord's table, and of the table of demons. 22 Do we provoke the Lord to jealousy? are we stronger than he?

23 All things are lawful, but all are not profitable; all things are lawful, but all do not edify. 24 Let no one seek his own advantage, but that of the other. 25 Everything sold in the shambles eat, making no inquiry for conscience sake. 26 For the earth is the Lord's and its fulness. 27 But if any one of the unbelievers invite you, and ye are minded to go, all that is set before you eat, making no inquiry for conscience sake. 28 But if any one say to you, This is offered to holy purposes, do not eat, for his sake that pointed it out, and conscience sake; 29 but conscience, I mean, not thine own, but that of the other: for why is my liberty judged by another conscience? 30 If I partake with thanksgiving, why am I spoken evil of for what I give thanks for? 31 Whether therefore ye eat, or drink, or whatever ye do, do all things to God's glory. 32 Give no occasion to stumbling, whether to Jews, or Greeks, or the assembly of God. 33 Even as I also please all in all things; not seeking my own profit, but that of the many, that they may be saved.

1 Corinthians 11

1 Be my imitators, even as I also am of Christ. 2 Now I praise you, that in all things ye are mindful of me; and that as I have directed you, ye keep the directions. 3 But I wish you to know that the Christ is the head of every man, but woman's head is the man, and the Christ's head God. 4 Every man praying or prophesying, having anything on his head, puts his head to shame. 5 But every woman praying or prophesying with her head uncovered puts her own head to shame; for it is one and the same as a shaved woman. 6 For if a woman be not covered, let her hair also be cut off. But if it be shameful to a woman to have her hair cut off or to be shaved, let her be covered. 7 For man indeed ought not to have his head covered, being God's image and glory; but woman is man's glory. 8 For man is not of woman, but woman of man. 9 For also man was not created for the sake of the woman, but woman for the sake of the man. 10 Therefore ought the woman to have authority on her head, on account of the angels. 11 However, neither is woman without man, nor man without woman, in the Lord. 12 For as the woman is of the man, so also is the man by the woman, but all things of God. 13 Judge in yourselves: is it comely that a woman should pray to God uncovered? 14 Does not even nature itself teach you, that man, if he have long hair, it is a dishonour to him? 15 But woman, if she have long hair, it is glory to her; for the long hair is given to her in lieu of a veil. 16 But if any one think to be contentious, we have no such custom, nor the assemblies of God.

17 But in prescribing to you on this which I now enter on, I do not praise, namely, that ye come together, not for the better, but for the worse. 18 For first, when ye come together in assembly, I hear there exist divisions among you, and I partly give credit to it. 19 For there must also be sects among you, that the approved may become manifest among you. 20 When ye come therefore together into one place, it is not to eat the Lord's supper. 21 For each one in eating takes his own supper before others, and one is hungry and another drinks to excess. 22 Have ye not then houses for eating and drinking? or do ye despise the assembly of God, and put to shame them who have not? What shall I say to you? shall I praise you? In this point I do not praise.

23 For I received from the Lord, that which I also delivered to you, that the Lord Jesus, in the night in which he was delivered up, took bread, 24 and having given thanks broke it, and said, This is my body, which is for you: this do in remembrance of me. 25 In like manner also the cup, after having supped, saying, This cup is the new covenant in my blood: this do, as often as ye shall drink it, in remembrance of me. 26 For as often as ye shall eat this bread, and drink the cup, ye announce the death of the Lord, until he come. 27 So that whosoever shall eat the bread, or drink the cup of the Lord, unworthily, shall be guilty in respect of the body and of the blood of the Lord. 28 But let a man prove himself, and thus eat of the bread, and drink of the cup. 29 For the eater and drinker eats and drinks judgment to himself, not distinguishing the body. 30 On this account many among you are weak and infirm, and a good many are fallen asleep. 31 But if we judged ourselves, so were we not judged. 32 But being judged, we are disciplined of the Lord, that we may not be condemned with the world. 33 So that, my brethren, when ye come together to eat, wait for one another. 34 If any one be hungry, let him eat at home, that ye may not come together for judgment. But the other things, whenever I come, I will set in order.

1 Corinthians 12

1 But concerning spiritual manifestations, brethren, I do not wish you to be ignorant. 2 Ye know that when ye were of the nations ye were led away to dumb idols, in whatever way ye might be led. 3 I give you therefore to know, that no one, speaking in the power of the Spirit of God, says, Curse on Jesus; and no one can say, Lord Jesus, unless in the power of the Holy Spirit. 4 But there are distinctions of gifts, but the same Spirit; 5 and there are distinctions of services, and the same Lord; 6 and there are distinctions of operations, but the same God who operates all things in all. 7 But to each the manifestation of the Spirit is given for profit. 8 For to one, by the Spirit, is given the word of wisdom; and to another the word of knowledge, according to the same Spirit; 9 and to a different one faith, in the power of the same Spirit; and to another gifts of healing in the power of the same Spirit; 10 and to another operations of miracles; and to another prophecy; and to another discerning of spirits; and to a different one kinds of tongues; and to another interpretation of tongues. 11 But all these things operates the one and the same Spirit, dividing to each in particular according as he pleases.

12 For even as the body is one and has many members, but all the members of the body, being many, are one body, so also is the Christ. 13 For also in the power of one Spirit we have all been baptised into one body, whether Jews or Greeks, whether bondmen or free, and have all been given to drink of one Spirit. 14 For also the body is not one member but many. 15 If the foot say, Because I am not a hand I am not of the body, is it on account of this not indeed of the body? 16 And if the ear say, Because I am not an eye I am not of the body, is it on account of this not indeed of the body? 17 If the whole body were an eye, where the hearing? if all hearing, where the smelling? 18 But now God has set the members, each one of them in the body, according as it has pleased him. 19 But if all were one member, where the body? 20 But now the members are many, and the body one. 21 The eye cannot say to the hand, I have not need of thee; or again, the head to the feet, I have not need of you. 22 But much rather, the members of the body which seem to be weaker are necessary; 23 and those parts of the body which we esteem to be the more void of honour, these we clothe with more abundant honour; and our uncomely parts have more abundant comeliness; 24 but our comely parts have not need. But God has tempered the body together, having given more abundant honour to the part that lacked; 25 that there might be no division in the body, but that the members might have the same concern one for another. 26 And if one member suffer, all the members suffer with it; and if one member be glorified, all the members rejoice with it.

27 Now ye are Christ's body, and members in particular. 28 And God has set certain in the assembly: first, apostles; secondly, prophets; thirdly, teachers; then miraculous powers; then gifts of healings; helps; governments; kinds of tongues. 29 Are all apostles? are all prophets? are all teachers? are all in possession of miraculous powers? 30 have all gifts of healings? do all speak with tongues? do all interpret? 31 But desire earnestly the greater gifts, and yet shew I unto you a way of more surpassing excellence.

1 Corinthians 13

1 If I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, but have not love, I am become sounding brass or a clanging cymbal. 2 And if I have prophecy, and know all mysteries and all knowledge, and if I have all faith, so as to remove mountains, but have not love, I am nothing. 3 And if I shall dole out all my goods in food, and if I deliver up my body that I may be burned, but have not love, I profit nothing.

4 Love has long patience, is kind; love is not emulous of others; love is not insolent and rash, is not puffed up, 5 does not behave in an unseemly manner, does not seek what is its own, is not quickly provoked, does not impute evil, 6 does not rejoice at iniquity but rejoices with the truth, 7 bears all things, believes all things, hopes all things, endures all things.

8 Love never fails; but whether prophecies, they shall be done away; or tongues, they shall cease; or knowledge, it shall be done away. 9 For we know in part, and we prophesy in part: 10 but when that which is perfect has come, that which is in part shall be done away. 11 When I was a child, I spoke as a child, I felt as a child, I reasoned as a child; when I became a man, I had done with what belonged to the child. 12 For we see now through a dim window obscurely, but then face to face; now I know partially, but then I shall know according as I also have been known. 13 And now abide faith, hope, love; these three things; and the greater of these is love.

1 Corinthians 14

1 Follow after love, and be emulous of spiritual manifestations, but rather that ye may prophesy. 2 For he that speaks with a tongue does not speak to men but to God: for no one hears; but in spirit he speaks mysteries. 3 But he that prophesies speaks to men in edification, and encouragement, and consolation. 4 He that speaks with a tongue edifies himself; but he that prophesies edifies the assembly. 5 Now I desire that ye should all speak with tongues, but rather that ye should prophesy. But greater is he that prophesies than he that speaks with tongues, unless he interpret, that the assembly may receive edification.

6 And now, brethren, if I come to you speaking with tongues, what shall I profit you, unless I shall speak to you either in revelation, or in knowledge, or in prophecy, or in teaching? 7 Even lifeless things giving a sound, whether pipe or harp, if they give not distinction to the sounds, how shall it be known what is piped or harped? 8 For also, if the trumpet give an uncertain sound, who shall prepare himself for war? 9 Thus also ye with the tongue, unless ye give a distinct speech, how shall it be known what is spoken? for ye will be speaking to the air. 10 There are, it may be, so many kinds of voices in the world, and none of undistinguishable sound. 11 If therefore I do not know the power of the sound, I shall be to him that speaks a barbarian, and he that speaks a barbarian for me. 12 Thus ye also, since ye are desirous of spirits, seek that ye may abound for the edification of the assembly. 13 Wherefore let him that speaks with a tongue pray that he may interpret. 14 For if I pray with a tongue, my spirit prays, but my understanding is unfruitful.

15 What is it then? I will pray with the spirit, but I will pray also with the understanding; I will sing with the spirit, but I will sing also with the understanding. 16 Since otherwise, if thou blessest with the spirit, how shall he who fills the place of the simple Christian say Amen, at thy giving of thanks, since he does not know what thou sayest? 17 For thou indeed givest thanks well, but the other is not edified. 18 I thank God I speak in a tongue more than all of you: 19 but in the assembly I desire to speak five words with my understanding, that I may instruct others also, rather than ten thousand words in a tongue. 20 Brethren, be not children in your minds, but in malice be babes; but in your minds be grown men.

21 It is written in the law, By people of other tongues, and by strange lips, will I speak to this people; and neither thus will they hear me, saith the Lord. 22 So that tongues are for a sign, not to those who believe, but to unbelievers; but prophecy, not to unbelievers, but to those who believe. 23 If therefore the whole assembly come together in one place, and all speak with tongues, and simple persons enter in, or unbelievers, will not they say ye are mad? 24 But if all prophesy, and some unbeliever or simple person come in, he is convicted of all, he is judged of all; 25 the secrets of his heart are manifested; and thus, falling upon his face, he will do homage to God, reporting that God is indeed amongst you.

26 What is it then, brethren? whenever ye come together, each of you has a psalm, has a teaching, has a tongue, has a revelation, has an interpretation. Let all things be done to edification. 27 If any one speak with a tongue, let it be two, or at the most three, and separately, and let one interpret; 28 but if there be no interpreter, let him be silent in the assembly, and let him speak to himself and to God. 29 And let two or three prophets speak, and let the others judge. 30 But if there be a revelation to another sitting there, let the first be silent. 31 For ye can all prophesy one by one, that all may learn and all be encouraged. 32 And spirits of prophets are subject to prophets. 33 For God is not a God of disorder but of peace, as in all the assemblies of the saints.

34 Let your women be silent in the assemblies, for it is not permitted to them to speak; but to be in subjection, as the law also says. 35 But if they wish to learn anything, let them ask their own husbands at home; for it is a shame for a woman to speak in assembly.

36 Did the word of God go out from you, or did it come to you only? 37 If any one thinks himself to be a prophet or spiritual, let him recognise the things that I write to you, that it is the Lord's commandment. 38 But if any be ignorant, let him be ignorant. 39 So that, brethren, desire to prophesy, and do not forbid the speaking with tongues. 40 But let all things be done comelily and with order.

1 Corinthians 15

1 But I make known to you, brethren, the glad tidings which I announced to you, which also ye received, in which also ye stand, 2 by which also ye are saved, (if ye hold fast the word which I announced to you as the glad tidings,) unless indeed ye have believed in vain. 3 For I delivered to you, in the first place, what also I had received, that Christ died for our sins, according to the scriptures; 4 and that he was buried; and that he was raised the third day, according to the scriptures; 5 and that he appeared to Cephas, then to the twelve. 6 Then he appeared to above five hundred brethren at once, of whom the most remain until now, but some also have fallen asleep. 7 Then he appeared to James; then to all the apostles; 8 and last of all, as to an abortion, he appeared to me also. 9 For I am the least of the apostles, who am not fit to be called apostle, because I have persecuted the assembly of God. 10 But by God's grace I am what I am; and his grace, which was towards me, has not been vain; but I have laboured more abundantly than they all, but not I, but the grace of God which was with me. 11 Whether, therefore, I or they, thus we preach, and thus ye have believed.

12 Now if Christ is preached that he is raised from among the dead, how say some among you that there is not a resurrection of those that are dead? 13 But if there is not a resurrection of those that are dead, neither is Christ raised: 14 but if Christ is not raised, then, indeed, vain also is our preaching, and vain also your faith. 15 And we are found also false witnesses of God; for we have witnessed concerning God that he raised the Christ, whom he has not raised if indeed those that are dead are not raised. 16 For if those that are dead are not raised, neither is Christ raised; 17 but if Christ be not raised, your faith is vain; ye are yet in your sins. 18 Then indeed also those who have fallen asleep in Christ have perished. 19 If in this life only we have hope in Christ, we are the most miserable of all men.

20 (But now Christ is raised from among the dead, first-fruits of those fallen asleep. 21 For since by man came death, by man also resurrection of those that are dead. 22 For as in the Adam all die, thus also in the Christ all shall be made alive. 23 But each in his own rank: the first-fruits, Christ; then those that are the Christ's at his coming. 24 Then the end, when he gives up the kingdom to him who is God and Father; when he shall have annulled all rule and all authority and power. 25 For he must reign until he put all enemies under his feet. 26 The last enemy that is annulled is death. 27 For he has put all things in subjection under his feet. But when he says that all things are put in subjection, it is evident that it is except him who put all things in subjection to him. 28 But when all things shall have been brought into subjection to him, then the Son also himself shall be placed in subjection to him who put all things in subjection to him, that God may be all in all.) 29 Since what shall the baptised for the dead do if those that are dead rise not at all? why also are they baptised for them? 30 Why do we also endanger ourselves every hour? 31 Daily I die, by your boasting which I have in Christ Jesus our Lord. 32 If, to speak after the manner of man, I have fought with beasts in Ephesus, what is the profit to me if those that are dead do not rise? let us eat and drink; for to-morrow we die. 33 Be not deceived: evil communications corrupt good manners. 34 Awake up righteously, and sin not; for some are ignorant of God: I speak to you as a matter of shame.

35 But some one will say, How are the dead raised? and with what body do they come? 36 Fool; what thou sowest is not quickened unless it die. 37 And what thou sowest, thou sowest not the body that shall be, but a bare grain: it may be of wheat, or some one of the rest: 38 and God gives to it a body as he has pleased, and to each of the seeds its own body. 39 Every flesh is not the same flesh, but one is of men, and another flesh of beasts, and another flesh of birds, and another of fishes. 40 And there are heavenly bodies, and earthly bodies: but different is the glory of the heavenly, different that of the earthly: 41 one the sun's glory, and another the moon's glory, and another the stars' glory; for star differs from star in glory. 42 Thus also is the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in corruption, it is raised in incorruptibility. 43 It is sown in dishonour, it is raised in glory. It is sown in weakness, it is raised in power. 44 It is sown a natural body, it is raised a spiritual body: if there is a natural body, there is also a spiritual one. 45 Thus also it is written, The first man Adam became a living soul; the last Adam a quickening spirit. 46 But that which is spiritual was not first, but that which is natural, then that which is spiritual: 47 the first man out of the earth, made of dust; the second man, out of heaven. 48 Such as he made of dust, such also those made of dust; and such as the heavenly one, such also the heavenly ones. 49 And as we have borne the image of the one made of dust, we shall bear also the image of the heavenly one. 50 But this I say, brethren, that flesh and blood cannot inherit God's kingdom, nor does corruption inherit incorruptibility.

51 Behold, I tell you a mystery: We shall not all fall asleep, but we shall all be changed, 52 in an instant, in the twinkling of an eye, at the last trumpet; for the trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be raised incorruptible, and we shall be changed. 53 For this corruptible must needs put on incorruptibility, and this mortal put on immortality. 54 But when this corruptible shall have put on incorruptibility, and this mortal shall have put on immortality, then shall come to pass the word written: Death has been swallowed up in victory. 55 Where, O death, is thy sting? where, O death, thy victory? 56 Now the sting of death is sin, and the power of sin the law; 57 but thanks to God, who gives us the victory by our Lord Jesus Christ.

58 So then, my beloved brethren, be firm, immovable, abounding always in the work of the Lord, knowing that your toil is not in vain in the Lord.

1 Corinthians 16

1 Now concerning the collection for the saints, as I directed the assemblies of Galatia, so do ye do also. 2 On the first of the week let each of you put by at home, laying up in whatever degree he may have prospered, that there may be no collections when I come. 3 And when I am arrived, whomsoever ye shall approve, these I will send with letters to carry your bounty to Jerusalem: 4 and if it be suitable that I also should go, they shall go with me.

5 But I will come to you when I shall have gone through Macedonia; for I do go through Macedonia. 6 But perhaps I will stay with you, or even winter with you, that ye may set me forward wheresoever I may go. 7 For I will not see you now in passing, for I hope to remain a certain time with you, if the Lord permit. 8 But I remain in Ephesus until Pentecost. 9 For a great door is opened to me and an effectual one, and the adversaries many.

10 Now if Timotheus come, see that he may be with you without fear; for he works the work of the Lord, even as I. 11 Let not therefore any one despise him; but set him forward in peace, that he may come to me; for I expect him with the brethren. 12 Now concerning the brother Apollos, I begged him much that he would go to you with the brethren; but it was not at all his will to go now; but he will come when he shall have good opportunity.

13 Be vigilant; stand fast in the faith; quit yourselves like men; be strong. 14 Let all things ye do be done in love. 15 But I beseech you, brethren, (ye know the house of Stephanas, that it is the first-fruits of Achaia, and they have devoted themselves to the saints for service,) 16 that ye should also be subject to such, and to every one joined in the work and labouring. 17 But I rejoice in the coming of Stephanas and Fortunatus and Achaicus; because they have supplied what was lacking on your part. 18 For they have refreshed my spirit and yours: own therefore such.

19 The assemblies of Asia salute you. Aquila and Priscilla, with the assembly in their house, salute you much in the Lord. 20 All the brethren salute you. Salute one another with a holy kiss. 21 The salutation of me Paul with my own hand. 22 If any one love not the Lord Jesus Christ let him be Anathema Maranatha. 23 The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with you. 24 My love be with you all in Christ Jesus. Amen.

2 Corinthians 1

1 Paul, apostle of Jesus Christ by God's will, and the brother Timotheus, to the assembly of God which is in Corinth, with all the saints who are in the whole of Achaia. 2 Grace to you, and peace from God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ.

3 Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of compassions, and God of all encouragement; 4 who encourages us in all our tribulation, that we may be able to encourage those who are in any tribulation whatever, through the encouragement with which we ourselves are encouraged of God. 5 Because, even as the sufferings of the Christ abound towards us, so through the Christ does our encouragement also abound. 6 But whether we are in tribulation, it is for your encouragement and salvation, wrought in the endurance of the same sufferings which we also suffer,

7 (and our hope for you is sure;) or whether we are encouraged, it is for your encouragement and salvation: knowing that as ye are partakers of the sufferings, so also of the encouragement. 8 For we do not wish you to be ignorant, brethren, as to our tribulation which happened to us in Asia, that we were excessively pressed beyond our power, so as to despair even of living. 9 But we ourselves had the sentence of death in ourselves, that we should not have our trust in ourselves, but in God who raises the dead; 10 who has delivered us from so great a death, and does deliver; in whom we confide that he will also yet deliver; 11 ye also labouring together by supplication for us that the gift towards us, through means of many persons, may be the subject of the thanksgiving of many for us.

12 For our boasting is this, the testimony of our conscience, that in simplicity and sincerity before God, (not in fleshly wisdom but in God's grace,) we have had our conversation in the world, and more abundantly towards you. 13 For we do not write other things to you but what ye well know and recognise; and I hope that ye will recognise to the end, 14 even as also ye have recognised us in part, that we are your boast, even as ye are ours in the day of the Lord Jesus.

15 And with this confidence I purposed to come to you previously, that ye might have a second favour; 16 and to pass through to Macedonia by you, and again from Macedonia to come to you, and to be set forward by you to Judaea. 17 Having therefore this purpose, did I then use lightness? Or what I purpose, do I purpose according to flesh, that there should be with me yea yea, and nay nay? 18 Now God is faithful, that our word to you is not yea and nay. 19 For the Son of God, Jesus Christ, he who has been preached by us among you (by me and Silvanus and Timotheus), did not become yea and nay, but yea is in him. 20 For whatever promises of God there are, in him is the yea, and in him the amen, for glory to God by us. 21 Now he that establishes us with you in Christ, and has anointed us, is God, 22 who also has sealed us, and given the earnest of the Spirit in our hearts. 23 But I call God to witness upon my soul that to spare you I have not yet come to Corinth. 24 Not that we rule over your faith, but are fellow-workmen of your joy: for by faith ye stand.

2 Corinthians 2

1 But I have judged this with myself, not to come back to you in grief. 2 For if I grieve you, who also is it that gladdens me, if not he that is grieved through me? 3 And I have written this very letter to you, that coming I may not have grief from those from whom I ought to have joy; trusting in you all that my joy is that of you all. 4 For out of much tribulation and distress of heart I wrote to you, with many tears; not that ye may be grieved, but that ye may know the love which I have very abundantly towards you.

5 But if any one has grieved, he has grieved, not me, but in part (that I may not overcharge you) all of you. 6 Sufficient to such a one is this rebuke which has been inflicted by the many; 7 so that on the contrary ye should rather shew grace and encourage, lest perhaps such a one should be swallowed up with excessive grief. 8 Wherefore I exhort you to assure him of your love. 9 For to this end also I have written, that I might know, by putting you to the test, if as to everything ye are obedient. 10 But to whom ye forgive anything, I also; for I also, what I have forgiven, if I have forgiven anything, it is for your sakes in the person of Christ; 11 that we might not have Satan get an advantage against us, for we are not ignorant of his thoughts.

12 Now when I came to Troas for the publication of the glad tidings of the Christ, a door also being opened to me in the Lord, 13 I had no rest in my spirit at not finding Titus my brother; but bidding them adieu, I came away to Macedonia. 14 But thanks be to God, who always leads us in triumph in the Christ, and makes manifest the odour of his knowledge through us in every place. 15 For we are a sweet odour of Christ to God, in the saved and in those that perish: 16 to the one an odour from death unto death, but to the others an odour from life unto life; and who is sufficient for these things? 17 For we do not, as the many, make a trade of the word of God; but as of sincerity, but as of God, before God, we speak in Christ.

2 Corinthians 3

1 Do we begin again to commend ourselves? or do we need, as some, commendatory letters to you, or commendatory from you? 2 Ye are our letter, written in our hearts, known and read of all men, 3 being manifested to be Christ's epistle ministered by us, written, not with ink, but the Spirit of the living God; not on stone tables, but on fleshy tables of the heart. 4 And such confidence have we through the Christ towards God: 5 not that we are competent of ourselves to think anything as of ourselves, but our competency is of God;

6 who has also made us competent, as ministers of the new covenant; not of letter, but of spirit. For the letter kills, but the Spirit quickens. 7 (But if the ministry of death, in letters, graven in stones, began with glory, so that the children of Israel could not fix their eyes on the face of Moses, on account of the glory of his face, a glory which is annulled; 8 how shall not rather the ministry of the Spirit subsist in glory? 9 For if the ministry of condemnation be glory, much rather the ministry of righteousness abounds in glory. 10 For also that which was glorified is not glorified in this respect, on account of the surpassing glory. 11 For if that annulled was introduced with glory, much rather that which abides subsists in glory.

12 Having therefore such hope, we use much boldness: 13 and not according as Moses put a veil on his own face, so that the children of Israel should not fix their eyes on the end of that annulled. 14 But their thoughts have been darkened, for unto this day the same veil remains in reading the old covenant, unremoved, which in Christ is annulled. 15 But unto this day, when Moses is read, the veil lies upon their heart. 16 But when it shall turn to the Lord, the veil is taken away.) 17 Now the Lord is the Spirit, but where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty. 18 But we all, looking on the glory of the Lord, with unveiled face, are transformed according to the same image from glory to glory, even as by the Lord the Spirit.

2 Corinthians 5

1 For we know that if our earthly tabernacle house be destroyed, we have a building from God, a house not made with hands, eternal in the heavens. 2 For indeed in this we groan, ardently desiring to have put on our house which is from heaven; 3 if indeed being also clothed we shall not be found naked. 4 For indeed we who are in the tabernacle groan, being burdened; while yet we do not wish to be unclothed, but clothed, that what is mortal may be swallowed up by life. 5 Now he that has wrought us for this very thing is God, who also has given to us the earnest of the Spirit. 6 Therefore we are always confident, and know that while present in the body we are absent from the Lord, 7 (for we walk by faith, not by sight;) 8 we are confident, I say, and pleased rather to be absent from the body and present with the Lord. 9 Wherefore also we are zealous, whether present or absent, to be agreeable to him. 10 For we must all be manifested before the judgment-seat of the Christ, that each may receive the things done in the body, according to those he has done, whether it be good or evil. 11 Knowing therefore the terror of the Lord we persuade men, but have been manifested to God, and I hope also that we have been manifested in your consciences.

12 For we do not again commend ourselves to you, but we are giving to you occasion of boast in our behalf, that ye may have such with those boasting in countenance, and not in heart. 13 For whether we are beside ourselves, it is to God; or are sober, it is for you. 14 For the love of the Christ constrains us, having judged this: that one died for all, then all have died; 15 and he died for all, that they who live should no longer live to themselves, but to him who died for them and has been raised.

16 So that we henceforth know no one according to flesh; but if even we have known Christ according to flesh, yet now we know him thus no longer. 17 So if any one be in Christ, there is a new creation; the old things have passed away; behold all things have become new: 18 and all things are of the God who has reconciled us to himself by Jesus Christ, and given to us the ministry of that reconciliation: 19 how that God was in Christ, reconciling the world to himself, not reckoning to them their offences; and putting in us the word of that reconciliation. 20 We are ambassadors therefore for Christ, God as it were beseeching by us, we entreat for Christ, Be reconciled to God. 21 Him who knew not sin he has made sin for us, that we might become God's righteousness in him.

2 Corinthians 7

1 Having therefore these promises, beloved, let us purify ourselves from every pollution of flesh and spirit, perfecting holiness in God's fear. 2 Receive us: we have injured no one, we have ruined no one, we have made gain of no one. 3 I do not speak for condemnation, for I have already said that ye are in our hearts, to die together, and live together. 4 Great is my boldness towards you, great my exulting in respect of you; I am filled with encouragement; I overabound in joy under all our affliction.

5 For indeed, when we came into Macedonia, our flesh had no rest, but we were afflicted in every way; without combats, within fears. 6 But he who encourages those that are brought low, even God, encouraged us by the coming of Titus; 7 and not by his coming only, but also through the encouragement with which he was encouraged as to you; relating to us your ardent desire, your mourning, your zeal for me; so that I the more rejoiced. 8 For if also I grieved you in the letter, I do not regret it, if even I have regretted it; for I see that that letter, if even it were only for a time, grieved you. 9 Now I rejoice, not that ye have been grieved, but that ye have been grieved to repentance; for ye have been grieved according to God, that in nothing ye might be injured by us. 10 For grief according to God works repentance to salvation, never to be regretted; but the grief of the world works death. 11 For, behold, this same thing, your being grieved according to God, how much diligence it wrought in you, but what excusing of yourselves, but what indignation, but what fear, but what ardent desire, but what zeal, but what vengeance: in every way ye have proved yourselves to be pure in the matter.

12 So then, if also I wrote to you, it was not for the sake of him that injured, nor for the sake of him that was injured, but for the sake of our diligent zeal for you being manifested to you before God. 13 For this reason we have been encouraged. And we the rather rejoiced in our encouragement more abundantly by reason of the joy of Titus, because his spirit has been refreshed by you all. 14 Because if I boasted to him anything about you, I have not been put to shame; but as we have spoken to you all things in truth, so also our boasting to Titus has been the truth; 15 and his affections are more abundantly towards you, calling to mind the obedience of you all, how with fear and trembling ye received him. 16 I rejoice that in everything I am confident as to you.

2 Corinthians 8

1 But we make known to you, brethren, the grace of God bestowed in the assemblies of Macedonia; 2 that in a great trial of affliction the abundance of their joy and their deep poverty has abounded to the riches of their free-hearted liberality. 3 For according to their power, I bear witness, and beyond their power, they were willing of their own accord, 4 begging of us with much entreaty to give effect to the grace and fellowship of the service which was to be rendered to the saints. 5 And not according as we hoped, but they gave themselves first to the Lord, and to us by God's will. 6 So that we begged Titus that, according as he had before begun, so he would also complete as to you this grace also;

7 but even as ye abound in every way, in faith, and word, and knowledge, and all diligence, and in love from you to us, that ye may abound in this grace also. 8 I do not speak as commanding it, but through the zeal of others, and proving the genuineness of your love. 9 For ye know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, that for your sakes he, being rich, became poor, in order that ye by his poverty might be enriched. 10 And I give my opinion in this, for this is profitable for you who began before, not only to do, but also to be willing, a year ago. 11 But now also complete the doing of it; so that as there was the readiness to be willing, so also to complete out of what ye have. 12 For if the readiness be there, a man is accepted according to what he may have, not according to what he has not. 13 For it is not in order that there may be ease for others, and for you distress, 14 but on the principle of equality; in the present time your abundance for their lack, that their abundance may be for your lack, so that there should be equality. 15 According as it is written, He who gathered much had no excess, and he who gathered little was nothing short.

16 But thanks be to God, who gives the same diligent zeal for you in the heart of Titus. 17 For he received indeed the entreaty, but, being full of zeal, he went of his own accord to you; 18 but we have sent with him the brother whose praise is in the glad tidings through all the assemblies; 19 and not only so, but is also chosen by the assemblies as our fellow-traveller with this grace, ministered by us to the glory of the Lord himself, and a witness of our readiness; 20 avoiding this, that any one should blame us in this abundance which is administered by us; 21 for we provide for things honest, not only before the Lord, but also before men. 22 And we have sent with them our brother whom we have often proved to be of diligent zeal in many things, and now more diligently zealous through the great confidence he has as to you. 23 Whether as regards Titus, he is my companion and fellow-labourer in your behalf; or our brethren, they are deputed messengers of assemblies, Christ's glory. 24 Shew therefore to them, before the assemblies, the proof of your love, and of our boasting about you.

2 Corinthians 10

1 But I myself, Paul, entreat you by the meekness and gentleness of the Christ, who, as to appearance, when present am mean among you, but absent am bold towards you; 2 but I beseech that present I may not be bold with the confidence with which I think to be daring towards some who think of us as walking according to flesh. 3 For walking in flesh, we do not war according to flesh. 4 For the arms of our warfare are not fleshly, but powerful according to God to the overthrow of strongholds; 5 overthrowing reasonings and every high thing that lifts itself up against the knowledge of God, and leading captive every thought into the obedience of the Christ; 6 and having in readiness to avenge all disobedience when your obedience shall have been fulfilled.

7 Do ye look at what concerns appearance? If any one has confidence in himself that he is of Christ, let him think this again in himself, that even as he is of Christ, so also are we. 8 For and if I should boast even somewhat more abundantly of our authority, which the Lord has given to us for building up and not for your overthrowing, I shall not be put to shame; 9 that I may not seem as if I was frightening you by letters: 10 because his letters, he says, are weighty and strong, but his presence in the body weak, and his speech naught. 11 Let such a one think this, that such as we are in word by letters when absent, such also present in deed.

12 For we dare not class ourselves or compare ourselves with some who commend themselves; but these, measuring themselves by themselves, and comparing themselves with themselves, are not intelligent. 13 Now we will not boast out of measure, but according to the measure of the rule which the God of measure has apportioned to us, to reach to you also. 14 For we do not, as not reaching to you, overstretch ourselves, (for we have come to you also in the glad tidings of the Christ;) 15 not boasting out of measure in other people's labours, but having hope, your faith increasing, to be enlarged amongst you, according to our rule, yet more abundantly 16 to announce the glad tidings to that which is beyond you, not to be boasting in another's rule of things made ready to hand. 17 But he that boasts, let him boast in the Lord. 18 For not he that commends himself is approved, but whom the Lord commends.

2 Corinthians 11

1 Would that ye would bear with me in a little folly; but indeed bear with me. 2 For I am jealous as to you with a jealousy which is of God; for I have espoused you unto one man, to present you a chaste virgin to Christ. 3 But I fear lest by any means, as the serpent deceived Eve by his craft, so your thoughts should be corrupted from simplicity as to the Christ. 4 For if indeed he that comes preaches another Jesus, whom we have not preached, or ye get a different Spirit, which ye have not got, or a different glad tidings, which ye have not received, ye might well bear with it.

5 For I reckon that in nothing I am behind those who are in surpassing degree apostles. 6 But if I am a simple person in speech, yet not in knowledge, but in everything making the truth manifest in all things to you. 7 Have I committed sin, abasing myself in order that ye might be exalted, because I gratuitously announced to you the glad tidings of God? 8 I spoiled other assemblies, receiving hire for ministry towards you. 9 And being present with you and lacking, I did not lazily burden any one, (for the brethren who came from Macedonia supplied what I lacked,) and in everything I kept myself from being a burden to you, and will keep myself. 10 The truth of Christ is in me that this boasting shall not be stopped as to me in the regions of Achaia. 11 Why? because I do not love you? God knows. 12 But what I do, I will also do, that I may cut off the opportunity of those wishing for an opportunity, that wherein they boast they may be found even as we. 13 For such are false apostles, deceitful workers, transforming themselves into apostles of Christ. 14 And it is not wonderful, for Satan himself transforms himself into an angel of light. 15 It is no great thing therefore if his ministers also transform themselves as ministers of righteousness; whose end shall be according to their works.

16 Again I say, Let not any one think me to be a fool; but if otherwise, receive me then even as a fool, that I also may boast myself some little. 17 What I speak I do not speak according to the Lord, but as in folly, in this confidence of boasting. 18 Since many boast according to flesh, I also will boast. 19 For ye bear fools readily, being wise. 20 For ye bear if any one bring you into bondage, if any one devour you, if any one get your money, if any one exalt himself, if any one beat you on the face. 21 I speak as to dishonour, as though we had been weak; but wherein any one is daring, (I speak in folly,) I also am daring.

22 Are they Hebrews? I also. Are they Israelites? I also. Are they seed of Abraham? I also. 23 Are they ministers of Christ? (I speak as being beside myself) I above measure so; in labours exceedingly abundant, in stripes to excess, in prisons exceedingly abundant, in deaths oft. 24 From the Jews five times have I received forty stripes, save one. 25 Thrice have I been scourged, once I have been stoned, three times I have suffered shipwreck, a night and day I passed in the deep: 26 in journeyings often, in perils of rivers, in perils of robbers, in perils from my own race, in perils from the nations, in perils in the city, in perils in thedesert, in perils on the sea, in perils among false brethren; 27 in labour and toil, in watchings often, in hunger and thirst, in fastings often, in cold and nakedness. 28 Besides those things that are without, the crowd of cares pressing on me daily, the burden of all the assemblies. 29 Who is weak, and I am not weak? Who is stumbled, and I burn not? 30 If it is needful to boast, I will boast in the things which concern my infirmity. 31 The God and Father of the Lord Jesus knows--he who is blessed for ever--that I do not lie. 32 In Damascus the ethnarch of Aretas the king kept the city of the Damascenes shut up, wishing to take me; 33 and through a window in a basket I was let down by the wall, and escaped his hands.

2 Corinthians 13

1 This third time I am coming to you. In the mouth of two or three witnesses shall every matter be established. 2 I have declared beforehand, and I say beforehand as present the second time, and now absent, to those that have sinned before, and to all the rest, that if I come again I will not spare. 3 Since ye seek a proof of Christ speaking in me, (who is not weak towards you, but is powerful among you, 4 for if indeed he has been crucified in weakness, yet he lives by God's power; for indeed we are weak in him, but we shall live with him by God's power towards you,) 5 examine your own selves if ye be in the faith; prove your own selves: do ye not recognise yourselves, that Jesus Christ is in you, unless indeed ye be reprobates? 6 Now I hope that ye will know that we are not reprobates.

7 But we pray to God that ye may do nothing evil; not that we may appear approved, but that ye may do what is right, and we be as reprobates. 8 For we can do nothing against the truth, but for the truth. 9 For we rejoice when we may be weak and ye may be powerful. But this also we pray for, your perfecting. 10 On this account I write these things being absent, that being present I may not use severity according to the authority which the Lord has given me for building up, and not for overthrowing.

11 For the rest, brethren, rejoice; be perfected; be encouraged; be of one mind; be at peace; and the God of love and peace shall be with you. 12 Salute one another with a holy kiss. 13 All the saints salute you. 14 The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ, and the love of God, and the communion of the Holy Spirit, be with you all.

Galatians 1

1 Paul, apostle, not from men nor through man, but through Jesus Christ, and God the Father who raised him from among the dead, 2 and all the brethren with me, to the assemblies of Galatia. 3 Grace to you, and peace, from God the Father, and our Lord Jesus Christ, 4 who gave himself for our sins, so that he should deliver us out of the present evil world, according to the will of our God and Father; 5 to whom be glory to the ages of ages. Amen.

6 I wonder that ye thus quickly change, from him that called you in Christ's grace, to a different gospel, 7 which is not another one; but there are some that trouble you, and desire to pervert the glad tidings of the Christ. 8 But if even we or an angel out of heaven announce as glad tidings to you anything besides what we have announced as glad tidings to you, let him be accursed. 9 As we have said before, now also again I say, If any one announce to you as glad tidings anything besides what ye have received, let him be accursed.

10 For do I now seek to satisfy men or God? or do I seek to please men? If I were yet pleasing men, I were not Christ's bondman. 11 But I let you know, brethren, as to the glad tidings which were announced by me, that they are not according to man. 12 For neither did I receive them from man, neither was I taught them, but by revelation of Jesus Christ. 13 For ye have heard what was my conversation formerly in Judaism, that I excessively persecuted the assembly of God, and ravaged it; 14 and advanced in Judaism beyond many my contemporaries in my nation, being exceedingly zealous of the doctrines of my fathers. 15 But when God, who set me apart even from my mother's womb, and called me by his grace, 16 was pleased to reveal his Son in me, that I may announce him as glad tidings among the nations, immediately I took not counsel with flesh and blood, 17 nor went I up to Jerusalem to those who were apostles before me; but I went to Arabia, and again returned to Damascus. 18 Then after three years I went up to Jerusalem to make acquaintance with Peter, and I remained with him fifteen days; 19 but I saw none other of the apostles, but James the brother of the Lord. 20 Now what I write to you, behold, before God, I do not lie. 21 Then I came into the regions of Syria and Cilicia. 22 But I was unknown personally to the assemblies of Judaea which are in Christ; 23 only they were hearing that he who persecuted us formerly now announces the glad tidings of the faith which formerly he ravaged: 24 and they glorified God in me.

Galatians 3

1 O senseless Galatians, who has bewitched you; to whom, as before your very eyes, Jesus Christ has been portrayed, crucified among you? 2 This only I wish to learn of you, Have ye received the Spirit on the principle of works of law, or of the report of faith? 3 Are ye so senseless? having begun in Spirit, are ye going to be made perfect in flesh? 4 Have ye suffered so many things in vain, if indeed also in vain? 5 He therefore who ministers to you the Spirit, and works miracles among you, is it on the principle of works of law, or of the report of faith?

6 Even as Abraham believed God, and it was reckoned to him as righteousness. 7 Know then that they that are on the principle of faith, these are Abraham's sons; 8 and the scripture, foreseeing that God would justify the nations on the principle of faith, announced beforehand the glad tidings to Abraham: In thee all the nations shall be blessed. 9 So that they who are on the principle of faith are blessed with believing Abraham. 10 For as many as are on the principle of works of law are under curse. For it is written, Cursed is every one who does not continue in all things which are written in the book of the law to do them; 11 but that by law no one is justified with God is evident, because The just shall live on the principle of faith; 12 but the law is not on the principle of faith; but, He that shall have done these things shall live by them. 13 Christ has redeemed us out of the curse of the law, having become a curse for us, (for it is written, Cursed is every one hanged upon a tree,) 14 that the blessing of Abraham might come to the nations in Christ Jesus, that we might receive the promise of the Spirit through faith. 15 Brethren, (I speak according to man,) even man's confirmed covenant no one sets aside, or adds other dispositions to. 16 But to Abraham were the promises addressed, and to his seed: he does not say, And to seeds, as of many; but as of one, And to thy seed; which is Christ. 17 Now I say this, A covenant confirmed beforehand by God, the law, which took place four hundred and thirty years after, does not annul, so as to make the promise of no effect. 18 For if the inheritance be on the principle of law, it is no longer on the principle of promise; but God gave it in grace to Abraham by promise.

19 Why then the law? It was added for the sake of transgressions, until the seed came to whom the promise was made, ordained through angels in the hand of a mediator. 20 But a mediator is not of one, but God is one. 21 Is then the law against the promises of God? Far be the thought. For if a law had been given able to quicken, then indeed righteousness were on the principle of law; 22 but the scripture has shut up all things under sin, that the promise, on the principle of faith of Jesus Christ, should be given to those that believe. 23 But before faith came, we were guarded under law, shut up to faith which was about to be revealed. 24 So that the law has been our tutor up to Christ, that we might be justified on the principle of faith. 25 But, faith having come, we are no longer under a tutor; 26 for ye are all God's sons by faith in Christ Jesus. 27 For ye, as many as have been baptised unto Christ, have put on Christ. 28 There is no Jew nor Greek; there is no bondman nor freeman; there is no male and female; for ye are all one in Christ Jesus: 29 but if ye are of Christ, then ye are Abraham's seed, heirs according to promise.

Galatians 4

1 Now I say, As long as the heir is a child, he differs nothing from a bondman, though he be lord of all; 2 but he is under guardians and stewards until the period fixed by the father. 3 So we also, when we were children, were held in bondage under the principles of the world; 4 but when the fulness of the time was come, God sent forth his Son, come of woman, come under law, 5 that he might redeem those under law, that we might receive sonship. 6 But because ye are sons, God has sent out the Spirit of his Son into our hearts, crying, Abba, Father. 7 So thou art no longer bondman, but son; but if son, heir also through God.

8 But then indeed, not knowing God, ye were in bondage to those who by nature are not gods; 9 but now, knowing God, but rather being known by God, how do ye turn again to the weak and beggarly principles to which ye desire to be again anew in bondage? 10 Ye observe days and months and times and years. 11 I am afraid of you, lest indeed I have laboured in vain as to you.

12 Be as I am, for I also am as ye, brethren, I beseech you: ye have not at all wronged me. 13 But ye know that in weakness of the flesh I announced the glad tidings to you at the first; 14 and my temptation, which was in my flesh, ye did not slight nor reject with contempt; but ye received me as an angel of God, as Christ Jesus. 15 What then was your blessedness? for I bear you witness that, if possible, plucking out your own eyes ye would have given them to me. 16 So I have become your enemy in speaking the truth to you?

17 They are not rightly zealous after you, but desire to shut you out from us, that ye may be zealous after them. 18 But it is right to be zealous at all times in what is right, and not only when I am present with you--

19 my children, of whom I again travail in birth until Christ shall have been formed in you: 20 and I should wish to be present with you now, and change my voice, for I am perplexed as to you.

21 Tell me, ye who are desirous of being under law, do ye not listen to the law? 22 For it is written that Abraham had two sons; one of the maid servant, and one of the free woman. 23 But he that was of the maid servant was born according to flesh, and he that was of the free woman through the promise. 24 Which things have an allegorical sense; for these are two covenants: one from mount Sinai, gendering to bondage, which is Hagar. 25 For Hagar is mount Sinai in Arabia, and corresponds to Jerusalem which is now, for she is in bondage with her children; 26 but the Jerusalem above is free, which is our mother. 27 For it is written, Rejoice, thou barren that bearest not; break out and cry, thou that travailest not; because the children of the desolate are more numerous than those of her that has a husband. 28 But ye, brethren, after the pattern of Isaac, are children of promise. 29 But as then he that was born according to flesh persecuted him that was born according to Spirit, so also it is now. 30 But what says the scripture? Cast out the maid servant and her son; for the son of the maid servant shall not inherit with the son of the free woman. 31 So then, brethren, we are not maid servant's children, but children of the free woman.

Ephesians 4

1 I, the prisoner in the Lord, exhort you therefore to walk worthy of the calling wherewith ye have been called,

2 with all lowliness and meekness, with long-suffering, bearing with one another in love; 3 using diligence to keep the unity of the Spirit in the uniting bond of peace. 4 There is one body and one Spirit, as ye have been also called in one hope of your calling; 5 one Lord, one faith, one baptism; 6 one God and Father of all, who is over all, and through all, and in us all. 7 But to each one of us has been given grace according to the measure of the gift of the Christ. 8 Wherefore he says, Having ascended up on high, he has led captivity captive, and has given gifts to men. 9 But that he ascended, what is it but that he also descended into the lower parts of the earth? 10 He that descended is the same who has also ascended up above all the heavens, that he might fill all things; 11 and he has given some apostles, and some prophets, and some evangelists, and some shepherds and teachers, 12 for the perfecting of the saints; with a view to the work of the ministry, with a view to the edifying of the body of Christ; 13 until we all arrive at the unity of the faith and of the knowledge of the Son of God, at the full-grown man, at the measure of the stature of the fulness of the Christ; 14 in order that we may be no longer babes, tossed and carried about by every wind of that teaching which is in the sleight of men, in unprincipled cunning with a view to systematized error; 15 but, holding the truth in love, we may grow up to him in all things, who is the head, the Christ: 16 from whom the whole body, fitted together, and connected by every joint of supply, according to the working in its measure of each one part, works for itself the increase of the body to its self-building up in love.

17 This I say therefore, and testify in the Lord, that ye should no longer walk as the rest of the nations walk in the vanity of their mind, 18 being darkened in understanding, estranged from the life of God by reason of the ignorance which is in them, by reason of the hardness of their hearts, 19 who having cast off all feeling, have given themselves up to lasciviousness, to work all uncleanness with greedy unsatisfied lust. 20 But ye have not thus learnt the Christ, 21 if ye have heard him and been instructed in him according as the truth is in Jesus; 22 namely your having put off according to the former conversation the old man which corrupts itself according to the deceitful lusts; 23 and being renewed in the spirit of your mind; 24 and your having put on the new man, which according to God is created in truthful righteousness and holiness. 25 Wherefore, having put off falsehood, speak truth every one with his neighbour, because we are members one of another. 26 Be angry, and do not sin; let not the sun set upon your wrath, 27 neither give room for the devil. 28 Let the stealer steal no more, but rather let him toil, working what is honest with his hands, that he may have to distribute to him that has need. 29 Let no corrupt word go out of your mouth, but if there be any good one for needful edification, that it may give grace to those that hear it. 30 And do not grieve the Holy Spirit of God, with which ye have been sealed for the day of redemption. 31 Let all bitterness, and heat of passion, and wrath, and clamour, and injurious language, be removed from you, with all malice; 32 and be to one another kind, compassionate, forgiving one another, so as God also in Christ has forgiven you.

Ephesians 5

1 Be ye therefore imitators of God, as beloved children, 2 and walk in love, even as the Christ loved us, and delivered himself up for us, an offering and sacrifice to God for a sweet-smelling savour.

3 But fornication and all uncleanness or unbridled lust, let it not be even named among you, as it becomes saints; 4 and filthiness and foolish talking, or jesting, which are not convenient; but rather thanksgiving. 5 For this ye are well informed of, knowing that no fornicator, or unclean person, or person of unbridled lust, who is an idolater, has inheritance in the kingdom of the Christ and God. 6 Let no one deceive you with vain words, for on account of these things the wrath of God comes upon the sons of disobedience. 7 Be not ye therefore fellow-partakers with them; 8 for ye were once darkness, but now light in the Lord; walk as children of light, 9 (for the fruit of the light is in all goodness and righteousness and truth,) 10 proving what is agreeable to the Lord; 11 and do not have fellowship with the unfruitful works of darkness, but rather also reprove them, 12 for the things that are done by them in secret it is shameful even to say. 13 But all things having their true character exposed by the light are made manifest; for that which makes everything manifest is light. 14 Wherefore he says, Wake up, thou that sleepest, and arise up from among the dead, and the Christ shall shine upon thee. 15 See therefore how ye walk carefully, not as unwise but as wise, 16 redeeming the time, because the days are evil. 17 For this reason be not foolish, but understanding what is the will of the Lord. 18 And be not drunk with wine, in which is debauchery; but be filled with the Spirit, 19 speaking to yourselves in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing and chanting with your heart to the Lord; 20 giving thanks at all times for all things to him who is God and the Father in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ,

21 submitting yourselves to one another in the fear of Christ. 22 Wives, submit yourselves to your own husbands, as to the Lord, 23 for a husband is head of the wife, as also the Christ is head of the assembly. He is Saviour of the body. 24 But even as the assembly is subjected to the Christ, so also wives to their own husbands in everything. 25 Husbands, love your own wives, even as the Christ also loved the assembly, and has delivered himself up for it, 26 in order that he might sanctify it, purifying it by the washing of water by the word, 27 that he might present the assembly to himself glorious, having no spot, or wrinkle, or any of such things; but that it might be holy and blameless. 28 So ought men also to love their own wives as their own bodies: he that loves his own wife loves himself. 29 For no one has ever hated his own flesh, but nourishes and cherishes it, even as also the Christ the assembly: 30 for we are members of his body; we are of his flesh, and of his bones. 31 Because of this a man shall leave his father and mother, and shall be united to his wife, and the two shall be one flesh. 32 This mystery is great, but I speak as to Christ, and as to the assembly. 33 But ye also, every one of you, let each so love his own wife as himself; but as to the wife I speak that she may fear the husband.

Ephesians 6

1 Children, obey your parents in the Lord, for this is just. 2 Honour thy father and thy mother, which is the first commandment with a promise, 3 that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayest be long-lived on the earth. 4 And ye fathers, do not provoke your children to anger, but bring them up in the discipline and admonition of the Lord. 5 Bondmen, obey masters according to flesh, with fear and trembling, in simplicity of your heart as to the Christ; 6 not with eye-service as men-pleasers; but as bondmen of Christ, doing the will of God from the soul, 7 serving with good will as to the Lord, and not to men; 8 knowing that whatever good each shall do, this he shall receive of the Lord, whether bond or free. 9 And, masters, do the same things towards them, giving up threatening, knowing that both their and your Master is in heaven, and there is no acceptance of persons with him.

10 For the rest, brethren, be strong in the Lord, and in the might of his strength. 11 Put on the panoply of God, that ye may be able to stand against the artifices of the devil: 12 because our struggle is not against blood and flesh, but against principalities, against authorities, against the universal lords of this darkness, against spiritual power of wickedness in the heavenlies. 13 For this reason take to you the panoply of God, that ye may be able to withstand in the evil day, and, having accomplished all things, to stand. 14 Stand therefore, having girt about your loins with truth, and having put on the breastplate of righteousness, 15 and shod your feet with the preparation of the glad tidings of peace: 16 besides all these, having taken the shield of faith with which ye will be able to quench all the inflamed darts of the wicked one. 17 Have also the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the Spirit, which is God's word; 18 praying at all seasons, with all prayer and supplication in the Spirit, and watching unto this very thing with all perseverance and supplication for all the saints;

19 and for me in order that utterance may be given to me in the opening of my mouth to make known with boldness the mystery of the glad tidings, 20 for which I am an ambassador bound with a chain, that I may be bold in it as I ought to speak. 21 But in order that ye also may know what concerns me, how I am getting on, Tychicus, the beloved brother and faithful minister in the Lord, shall make all things known to you; 22 whom I have sent to you for this very thing, that ye may know of our affairs and that he may encourage your hearts. 23 Peace to the brethren, and love with faith, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. 24 Grace with all them that love our Lord Jesus Christ in incorruption.

Philippians 1

1 Paul and Timotheus, bondmen of Jesus Christ, to all the saints in Christ Jesus who are in Philippi, with the overseers and ministers; 2 grace to you, and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

3 I thank my God for my whole remembrance of you, 4 constantly in my every supplication, making the supplication for you all with joy, 5 because of your fellowship with the gospel, from the first day until now; 6 having confidence of this very thing, that he who has begun in you a good work will complete it unto Jesus Christ's day:

7 as it is righteous for me to think this as to you all, because ye have me in your hearts, and that both in my bonds and in the defence and confirmation of the glad tidings ye are all participators in my grace. 8 For God is my witness how I long after you all in the bowels of Christ Jesus.

9 And this I pray, that your love may abound yet more and more in full knowledge and all intelligence, 10 that ye may judge of and approve the things that are more excellent, in order that ye may be pure and without offence for Christ's day, 11 being complete as regards the fruit of righteousness, which is by Jesus Christ, to God's glory and praise.

12 But I would have you know, brethren, that the circumstances in which I am have turned out rather to the furtherance of the glad tidings, 13 so that my bonds have become manifest as being in Christ in all the praetorium and to all others; 14 and that the most of the brethren, trusting in the Lord through my bonds, dare more abundantly to speak the word of God fearlessly. 15 Some indeed also for envy and strife, but some also for good will, preach the Christ. 16 These indeed out of love, knowing that I am set for the defence of the glad tidings; 17 but those out of contention, announce the Christ, not purely, supposing to arouse tribulation for my bonds. 18 What is it then? at any rate, in every way, whether in pretext or in truth, Christ is announced; and in this I rejoice, yea, also I will rejoice; 19 for I know that this shall turn out for me to salvation, through your supplication and the supply of the Spirit of Jesus Christ; 20 according to my earnest expectation and hope, that in nothing I shall be ashamed, but in all boldness, as always, now also Christ shall be magnified in my body whether by life or by death.

21 For for me to live is Christ, and to die gain; 22 but if to live in flesh is my lot, this is for me worth the while: and what I shall choose I cannot tell. 23 But I am pressed by both, having the desire for departure and being with Christ, for it is very much better, 24 but remaining in the flesh is more necessary for your sakes; 25 and having confidence of this, I know that I shall remain and abide along with you all, for your progress and joy in faith; 26 that your boasting may abound in Christ Jesus through me by my presence again with you.

27 Only conduct yourselves worthily of the glad tidings of the Christ, in order that whether coming and seeing you, or absent, I may hear of what concerns you, that ye stand firm in one spirit, with one soul, labouring together in the same conflict with the faith of the glad tidings; 28 and not frightened in anything by the opposers, which is to them a demonstration of destruction, but of your salvation, and that from God; 29 because to you has been given, as regards Christ, not only the believing on him but the suffering for him also, 30 having the same conflict which ye have seen in me, and now hear of in me.

Philippians 2

1 If then there be any comfort in Christ, if any consolation of love, if any fellowship of the Spirit, if any bowels and compassions, 2 fulfil my joy, that ye may think the same thing, having the same love, joined in soul, thinking one thing; 3 let nothing be in the spirit of strife or vain glory, but, in lowliness of mind, each esteeming the other as more excellent than themselves; 4 regarding not each his own qualities, but each those of others also. 5 For let this mind be in you which was also in Christ Jesus; 6 who, subsisting in the form of God, did not esteem it an object of rapine to be on an equality with God; 7 but emptied himself, taking a bondman's form, taking his place in the likeness of men; 8 and having been found in figure as a man, humbled himself, becoming obedient even unto death, and that the death of the cross. 9 Wherefore also God highly exalted him, and granted him a name, that which is above every name, 10 that at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of heavenly and earthly and infernal beings, 11 and every tongue confess that Jesus Christ is Lord to God the Father's glory.

12 So that, my beloved, even as ye have always obeyed, not as in my presence only, but now much rather in my absence, work out your own salvation with fear and trembling, 13 for it is God who works in you both the willing and the working according to his good pleasure.

14 Do all things without murmurings and reasonings, 15 that ye may be harmless and simple, irreproachable children of God in the midst of a crooked and perverted generation; among whom ye appear as lights in the world, 16 holding forth the word of life, so as to be a boast for me in Christ's day, that I have not run in vain nor laboured in vain. 17 But if also I am poured out as a libation on the sacrifice and ministration of your faith, I rejoice, and rejoice in common with you all. 18 In like manner do ye also rejoice, and rejoice with me. 19 But I hope in the Lord Jesus to send Timotheus to you shortly, that I also may be refreshed, knowing how ye get on. 20 For I have no one like-minded who will care with genuine feeling how ye get on. 21 For all seek their own things, not the things of Jesus Christ. 22 But ye know the proof of him, that, as a child a father, he has served with me in the work of the glad tidings. 23 Him therefore I hope to send immediately, as soon as I shall see how it goes with me: 24 but I trust in the Lord that I myself also shall soon come; 25 but I have thought it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother and fellow-workman and fellow-soldier, but your messenger and minister to my need, 26 since he had a longing desire after you all, and was distressed because ye had heard that he was sick; 27 for he was also sick close to death, but God had mercy on him, and not indeed on him alone, but also on me, that I might not have sorrow upon sorrow. 28 I have sent him therefore the more diligently, that seeing him ye might again rejoice, and that I might be the less sorrowful. 29 Receive him therefore in the Lord with all joy, and hold such in honour; 30 because for the sake of the work he drew near even to death, venturing his life that he might fill up what lacked in your ministration toward me.

Philippians 3

1 For the rest, my brethren, rejoice in the Lord: to write the same things to you, to me is not irksome, and for you safe. 2 See to dogs, see to evil workmen, see to the concision. 3 For we are the circumcision, who worship by the Spirit of God, and boast in Christ Jesus, and do not trust in flesh.

4 Though I have my trust even in flesh; if any other think to trust in flesh, I rather: 5 as to circumcision, I received it the eighth day; of the race of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, Hebrew of Hebrews; as to the law, a Pharisee; 6 as to zeal, persecuting the assembly; as to righteousness which is in the law, found blameless; 7 but what things were gain to me these I counted, on account of Christ, loss. 8 But surely I count also all things to be loss on account of the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord, on account of whom I have suffered the loss of all, and count them to be filth, that I may gain Christ;

9 and that I may be found in him, not having my righteousness, which would be on the principle of law, but that which is by faith of Christ, the righteousness which is of God through faith, 10 to know him, and the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his sufferings, being conformed to his death, 11 if any way I arrive at the resurrection from among the dead. 12 Not that I have already obtained the prize, or am already perfected; but I pursue, if also I may get possession of it, seeing that also I have been taken possession of by Christ Jesus. 13 Brethren, I do not count to have got possession myself; but one thing--forgetting the things behind, and stretching out to the things before, 14 I pursue, looking towards the goal, for the prize of the calling on high of God in Christ Jesus.

15 As many therefore as are perfect, let us be thus minded; and if ye are any otherwise minded, this also God shall reveal to you. 16 But whereto we have attained, let us walk in the same steps.

17 Be imitators all together of me, brethren, and fix your eyes on those walking thus as you have us for a model; 18 (for many walk of whom I have told you often, and now tell you even weeping, that they are the enemies of the cross of Christ: 19 whose end is destruction, whose god is the belly, and their glory in their shame, who mind earthly things:) 20 for our commonwealth has its existence in the heavens, from which also we await the Lord Jesus Christ as Saviour, 21 who shall transform our body of humiliation into conformity to his body of glory, according to the working of the power which he has even to subdue all things to himself.

Philippians 4

1 So that, my brethren, beloved and longed for, my joy and crown, thus stand fast in the Lord, beloved. 2 I exhort Euodia, and exhort Syntyche, to be of the same mind in the Lord; 3 yea, I ask thee also, true yokefellow, assist them, who have contended along with me in the glad tidings, with Clement also, and my other fellow-labourers, whose names are in the book of life. 4 Rejoice in the Lord always: again I will say, Rejoice. 5 Let your gentleness be known of all men. The Lord is near. 6 Be careful about nothing; but in everything, by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving, let your requests be made known to God; 7 and the peace of God, which surpasses every understanding, shall guard your hearts and your thoughts by Christ Jesus. 8 For the rest, brethren, whatsoever things are true, whatsoever things are noble, whatsoever things are just, whatsoever things are pure, whatsoever things are amiable, whatsoever things areof good report; if there be any virtue and if any praise, think on these things. 9 What ye have both learned, and received, and heard, and seen in me, these things do; and the God of peace shall be with you.

10 But I rejoiced in the Lord greatly, that now however at length ye have revived your thinking of me, though surely ye did also think of me, but lacked opportunity. 11 Not that I speak as regards privation, for as to me I have learnt in those circumstances in which I am, to be satisfied in myself. 12 I know both how to be abased and I know how to abound. In everything and in all things I am initiated both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to suffer privation. 13 I have strength for all things in him that gives me power. 14 But ye have done well in taking part in my affliction. 15 And know also ye, O Philippians, that in the beginning of the gospel, when I came out of Macedonia, no assembly communicated anything to me in the way of giving and receiving save ye alone; 16 for also in Thessalonica once and even twice ye sent to me for my need. 17 Not that I seek gift, but I seek fruit abounding to your account. 18 But I have all things in full supply and abound; I am full, having received of Epaphroditus the things sent from you, an odour of sweet savour, an acceptable sacrifice, agreeable to God. 19 But my God shall abundantly supply all your need according to his riches in glory in Christ Jesus.

20 But to our God and Father be glory to the ages of ages. Amen. 21 Salute every saint in Christ Jesus. The brethren who are with me salute you. 22 All the saints salute you, and specially those of the household of Caesar. 23 The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.

Colossians 2

1 For I would have you know what combat I have for you, and those in Laodicea, and as many as have not seen my face in flesh; 2 to the end that their hearts may be encouraged, being united together in love, and unto all riches of the full assurance of understanding, to the full knowledge of the mystery of God; 3 in which are hid all the treasures of wisdom and of knowledge.

4 And I say this to the end that no one may delude you by persuasive speech. 5 For if indeed in the flesh I am absent, yet I am with you in spirit, rejoicing and seeing your order, and the firmness of your faith in Christ. 6 As therefore ye have received the Christ, Jesus the Lord, walk in him, 7 rooted and built up in him, and assured in the faith, even as ye have been taught, abounding in it with thanksgiving. 8 See that there be no one who shall lead you away as a prey through philosophy and vain deceit, according to the teaching of men, according to the elements of the world, and not according to Christ. 9 For in him dwells all the fulness of the Godhead bodily; 10 and ye are complete in him, who is the head of all principality and authority, 11 in whom also ye have been circumcised with circumcision not done by hand, in the putting off of the body of the flesh, in the circumcision of the Christ; 12 buried with him in baptism, in which ye have been also raised with him through faith of the working of God who raised him from among the dead.

13 And you, being dead in offences and in the uncircumcision of your flesh, he has quickened together with him, having forgiven us all the offences; 14 having effaced the handwriting in ordinances which stood out against us, which was contrary to us, he has taken it also out of the way, having nailed it to the cross; 15 having spoiled principalities and authorities, he made a show of them publicly, leading them in triumph by it.

16 Let none therefore judge you in meat or in drink, or in matter of feast, or new moon, or sabbaths, 17 which are a shadow of things to come; but the body is of Christ. 18 Let no one fraudulently deprive you of your prize, doing his own will in humility and worship of angels, entering into things which he has not seen, vainly puffed up by the mind of his flesh, 19 and not holding fast the head, from whom all the body, ministered to and united together by the joints and bands, increases with the increase of God. 20 If ye have died with Christ from the elements of the world, why as if alive in the world do ye subject yourselves to ordinances? 21 Do not handle, do not taste, do not touch, 22 (things which are all for destruction in the using of them:) according to the injunctions and teachings of men, 23 (which have indeed an appearance of wisdom in voluntary worship, and humility, and harsh treatment of the body, not in a certain honour,) to the satisfaction of the flesh.

Colossians 3

1 If therefore ye have been raised with the Christ, seek the things which are above, where the Christ is, sitting at the right hand of God: 2 have your mind on the things that are above, not on the things that are on the earth; 3 for ye have died, and your life is hid with the Christ in God. 4 When the Christ is manifested who is our life, then shall ye also be manifested with him in glory.

5 Put to death therefore your members which are upon the earth, fornication, uncleanness, vile passions, evil lust, and unbridled desire, which is idolatry. 6 On account of which things the wrath of God comes upon the sons of disobedience. 7 In which ye also once walked when ye lived in these things.

8 But now, put off, ye also, all these things, wrath, anger, malice, blasphemy, vile language out of your mouth. 9 Do not lie to one another, having put off the old man with his deeds, 10 and having put on the new, renewed into full knowledge according to the image of him that has created him; 11 wherein there is not Greek and Jew, circumcision and uncircumcision, barbarian, Scythian, bondman, freeman; but Christ is everything, and in all.

12 Put on therefore, as the elect of God, holy and beloved, bowels of compassion, kindness, lowliness, meekness, longsuffering; 13 forbearing one another, and forgiving one another, if any should have a complaint against any; even as the Christ has forgiven you, so also doye. 14 And to all these add love, which is the bond of perfectness. 15 And let the peace of Christ preside in your hearts, to which also ye have been called in one body, and be thankful. 16 Let the word of the Christ dwell in you richly, in all wisdom teaching and admonishing one another, in psalms, hymns, spiritual songs, singing with grace in your hearts to God. 17 And everything, whatever ye may do in word or in deed, do all things in the name of the Lord Jesus, giving thanks to God the Father by him.

18 Wives, be subject to your husbands, as is fitting in the Lord. 19 Husbands, love your wives, and be not bitter against them. 20 Children, obey your parents in all things, for this is well-pleasing in the Lord. 21 Fathers, do not vex your children, to the end that they be not disheartened. 22 Bondmen, obey in all things your masters according to flesh; not with eye-services, as men-pleasers, but in simplicity of heart, fearing the Lord. 23 Whatsoever ye do, labour at it heartily, as doing it to the Lord, and not to men; 24 knowing that of the Lord ye shall receive the recompense of the inheritance; ye serve the Lord Christ. 25 For he that does a wrong shall receive the wrong he has done, and there is no respect of persons.

Colossians 4

1 Masters, give to bondmen what is just and fair, knowing that ye also have a Master in the heavens.

2 Persevere in prayer, watching in it with thanksgiving; 3 praying at the same time for us also, that God may open to us a door of the word to speak the mystery of Christ, on account of which also I am bound, 4 to the end that I may make it manifest as I ought to speak.

5 Walk in wisdom towards those without, redeeming opportunities. 6 Let your word be always with grace, seasoned with salt, so as to know how ye ought to answer each one.

7 Tychicus, the beloved brother and faithful minister and fellow-bondman in the Lord, will make known to you all that concerns me; 8 whom I have sent to you for this very purpose, that he might know your state, and that he might encourage your hearts: 9 with Onesimus, the faithful and beloved brother, who is one of you. They shall make known to you everything here. 10 Aristarchus my fellow-captive salutes you, and Mark, Barnabas's cousin, concerning whom ye have received orders, (if he come to you, receive him,) 11 and Jesus called Justus, who are of the circumcision. These are the only fellow-workers for the kingdom of God who have been a consolation to me. 12 Epaphras, who is one of you, the bondman of Christ Jesus, salutes you, always combating earnestly for you in prayers, to the end that ye may stand perfect and complete in all the will of God. 13 For I bear him witness that he labours much for you, and them in Laodicea, and them in Hierapolis. 14 Luke, the beloved physician, salutes you, and Demas. 15 Salute the brethren in Laodicea, and Nymphas, and the assembly which is in his house. 16 And when the letter has been read among you, cause that it be read also in the assembly of Laodiceans, and that ye also read that from Laodicea. 17 And say to Archippus, Take heed to the ministry which thou hast received in the Lord, to the end that thou fulfil it. 18 The salutation by the hand of me Paul. Remember my bonds. Grace be with you.

1 Thessalonians 2

1 For ye know yourselves, brethren, our entering in which we had to you, that it has not been in vain; 2 but, having suffered before and been insulted, even as ye know, in Philippi, we were bold in our God to speak unto you the glad tidings of God with much earnest striving. 3 For our exhortation was not of deceit, nor of uncleanness, nor in guile; 4 but even as we have been approved of God to have the glad tidings entrusted to us, so we speak; not as pleasing men, but God, who proves our hearts. 5 For we have not at any time been among you with flattering discourse, even as ye know, nor with a pretext for covetousness, God is witness; 6 nor seeking glory from men, neither from you nor from others, when we might have been a charge as Christ's apostles;

7 but have been gentle in the midst of you, as a nurse would cherish her own children. 8 Thus, yearning over you, we had found our delight in having imparted to you not only the glad tidings of God, but our own lives also, because ye had become beloved of us. 9 For ye remember, brethren, our labour and toil: working night and day, not to be chargeable to any one of you, we have preached to you the glad tidings of God. 10 Ye are witnesses, and God, how piously and righteously and blamelessly we have conducted ourselves with you that believe: 11 as ye know how, as a father his own children, we used to exhort each one of you, and comfort and testify, 12 that ye should walk worthy of God, who calls you to his own kingdom and glory.

13 And for this cause we also give thanks to God unceasingly that, having received the word of the report of God by us, ye accepted, not men's word, but, even as it is truly, God's word, which also works in you who believe. 14 For ye, brethren, have become imitators of the assemblies of God which are in Judaea in Christ Jesus; for ye also have suffered the same things of your own countrymen as also they of the Jews, 15 who have both slain the Lord Jesus and the prophets, and have driven us out by persecution, and do not please God, and are against all men, 16 forbidding us to speak to the nations that they may be saved, that they may fill up their sins always: but wrath has come upon them to the uttermost.

17 But we, brethren, having been bereaved of you and separated for a little moment in person, not in heart, have used more abundant diligence to see your face with much desire; 18 wherefore we have desired to come to you, even I Paul, both once and twice, and Satan has hindered us. 19 For what is our hope, or joy, or crown of boasting? are not ye also before our Lord Jesus at his coming? 20 for ye are our glory and joy.

1 Thessalonians 4

1 For the rest, then, brethren, we beg you and exhort you in the Lord Jesus, even as ye have received from us how ye ought to walk and please God, even as ye also do walk, that ye would abound still more. 2 For ye know what charges we gave you through the Lord Jesus. 3 For this is the will of God, even your sanctification, that ye should abstain from fornication; 4 that each of you know how to possess his own vessel in sanctification and honour, 5 (not in passionate desire, even as the nations who know not God,) 6 not overstepping the rights of and wronging his brother in the matter, because the Lord is the avenger of all these things, even as we also told you before, and have fully testified. 7 For God has not called us to uncleanness, but in sanctification. 8 He therefore that in this disregards his brother, disregards, not man, but God, who has given also his Holy Spirit to you.

9 Now concerning brotherly love ye have no need that we should write to you, for ye yourselves are taught of God to love one another. 10 For also ye do this towards all the brethren in the whole of Macedonia; but we exhort you, brethren, to abound still more, 11 and to seek earnestly to be quiet and mind your own affairs, and work with your own hands, even as we charged you, 12 that ye may walk reputably towards those without, and may have need of no one.

13 But we do not wish you to be ignorant, brethren, concerning them that are fallen asleep, to the end that ye be not grieved even as also the rest who have no hope. 14 For if we believe that Jesus has died and has risen again, so also God will bring with him those who have fallen asleep through Jesus. 15 (For this we say to you in the word of the Lord, that we, the living, who remain to the coming of the Lord, are in no way to anticipate those who have fallen asleep; 16 for the Lord himself, with an assembling shout, with archangel's voice and with trump of God, shall descend from heaven; and the dead in Christ shall rise first; 17 then we, the living who remain, shall be caught up together with them in the clouds, to meet the Lord in the air; and thus we shall be always with the Lord. 18 So encourage one another with these words.)

1 Thessalonians 5

1 But concerning the times and the seasons, brethren, ye have no need that ye should be written to, 2 for ye know perfectly well yourselves, that the day of the Lord so comes as a thief by night. 3 When they may say, Peace and safety, then sudden destruction comes upon them, as travail upon her that is with child; and they shall in no wise escape. 4 But ye, brethren, are not in darkness, that the day should overtake you as a thief: 5 for all ye are sons of light and sons of day; we are not of night nor of darkness.

6 So then do not let us sleep as the rest do, but let us watch and be sober; 7 for they that sleep sleep by night, and they that drink drink by night; 8 but we being of the day, let us be sober, putting on the breastplate of faith and love, and as helmet the hope of salvation; 9 because God has not set us for wrath, but for obtaining salvation through our Lord Jesus Christ, 10 who has died for us, that whether we may be watching or sleep, we may live together with him.

11 Wherefore encourage one another, and build up each one the other, even as also ye do. 12 But we beg you, brethren, to know those who labour among you, and take the lead among you in the Lord, and admonish you, 13 and to regard them exceedingly in love on account of their work. Be in peace among yourselves. 14 But we exhort you, brethren, admonish the disorderly, comfort the faint-hearted, sustain the weak, be patient towards all. 15 See that no one render to any evil for evil, but pursue always what is good towards one another and towards all;

16 rejoice always; 17 pray unceasingly; 18 in everything give thanks, for this is the will of God in Christ Jesus towards you; 19 quench not the Spirit; 20 do not lightly esteem prophecies; 21 but prove all things, hold fast the right; 22 hold aloof from every form of wickedness.

23 Now the God of peace himself sanctify you wholly: and your whole spirit, and soul, and body be preserved blameless at the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ. 24 He is faithful who calls you, who will also perform it. 25 Brethren, pray for us. 26 Greet all the brethren with a holy kiss. 27 I adjure you by the Lord that the letter be read to all the holy brethren. 28 The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.

2 Thessalonians 2

1 Now we beg you, brethren, by the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ and our gathering together to him, 2 that ye be not soon shaken in mind, nor troubled, neither by spirit, nor by word, nor by letter, as if it were by us, as that the day of the Lord is present.

3 Let not any one deceive you in any manner, because it will not be unless the apostasy have first come, and the man of sin have been revealed, the son of perdition; 4 who opposes and exalts himself on high against all called God, or object of veneration; so that he himself sits down in the temple of God, shewing himself that he is God. 5 Do ye not remember that, being yet with you, I said these things to you? 6 And now ye know that which restrains, that he should be revealed in his own time. 7 For the mystery of lawlessness already works; only there is he who restrains now until he be gone, 8 and then the lawless one shall be revealed, whom the Lord Jesus shall consume with the breath of his mouth, and shall annul by the appearing of his coming; 9 whose coming is according to the working of Satan in all power and signs and wonders of falsehood, 10 and in all deceit of unrighteousness to them that perish, because they have not received the love of the truth that they might be saved. 11 And for this reason God sends to them a working of error, that they should believe what is false, 12 that all might be judged who have not believed the truth, but have found pleasure in unrighteousness.

13 But we ought to give thanks to God always for you, brethren beloved of the Lord, that God has chosen you from the beginning to salvation in sanctification of the Spirit and belief of the truth: 14 whereto he has called you by our glad tidings, to the obtaining of the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ. 15 So then, brethren, stand firm, and hold fast the instructions which ye have been taught, whether by word or by our letter.

16 But our Lord Jesus Christ himself, and our God and Father, who has loved us, and given us eternal consolation and good hope by grace, 17 encourage your hearts, and establish you in every good work and word.

2 Thessalonians 3

1 For the rest, brethren, pray for us, that the word of the Lord may run and be glorified, even as also with you; 2 and that we may be delivered from bad and evil men, for faith is not the portion of all. 3 But the Lord is faithful, who shall establish you and keep you from evil. 4 But we trust in the Lord as to you, that the things which we enjoin, ye both do and will do. 5 But the Lord direct your hearts into the love of God, and into the patience of the Christ.

6 Now we enjoin you, brethren, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye withdraw from every brother walking disorderly and not according to the instruction which he received from us. 7 For ye know yourselves how ye ought to imitate us, because we have not walked disorderly among you; 8 nor have we eaten bread from any one without cost; but in toil and hardship working night and day not to be chargeable to any one of you: 9 not that we have not the right, but that we might give ourselves as an example to you, in order to your imitating us. 10 For also when we were with you we enjoined you this, that if any man does not like to work, neither let him eat. 11 For we hear that there are some walking among you disorderly, not working at all, but busybodies. 12 Now such we enjoin and exhort in the Lord Jesus Christ, that working quietly they eat their own bread. 13 But ye, brethren, do not faint in well-doing. 14 But if any one obey not our word by the letter, mark that man, and do not keep company with him, that he may be ashamed of himself; 15 and do not esteem him as an enemy, but admonish him as a brother.

16 But the Lord of peace himself give you peace continually in every way. The Lord be with you all. 17 The salutation by the hand of me, Paul, which is the mark in every letter; so I write. 18 The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all.

1 Timothy 1

1 Paul, apostle of Jesus Christ, according to the command of God our Saviour, and of Christ Jesus our hope, 2 to Timotheus, my true child in faith: grace, mercy, peace, from God our Father and Christ Jesus our Lord. 3 Even as I begged thee to remain in Ephesus, when I was going to Macedonia, that thou mightest enjoin some not to teach other doctrines, 4 nor to turn their minds to fables and interminable genealogies, which bring questionings rather than further God's dispensation, which is in faith.

5 But the end of what is enjoined is love out of a pure heart and a good conscience and unfeigned faith; 6 which things some having missed, have turned aside to vain discourse, 7 desiring to be law-teachers, not understanding either what they say or concerning what they so strenuously affirm. 8 Now we know that the law is good if any one uses it lawfully, 9 knowing this, that law has not its application to a righteous person, but to the lawless and insubordinate, to the impious and sinful, to the unholy and profane, to smiters of fathers and smiters of mothers; to murderers, 10 fornicators, sodomites, kidnappers, liars, perjurers; and if any other thing is opposed to sound teaching, 11 according to the glad tidings of the glory of the blessed God, with which I have been entrusted.

12 And I thank Christ Jesus our Lord, who has given me power, that he has counted me faithful, appointing to ministry him 13 who before was a blasphemer and persecutor, and an insolent overbearing man: but mercy was shewn me because I did it ignorantly, in unbelief. 14 But the grace of our Lord surpassingly over-abounded with faith and love, which is in Christ Jesus. 15 Faithful is the word, and worthy of all acceptation, that Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners, of whom I am the first. 16 But for this reason mercy was shewn me, that in me, the first, Jesus Christ might display the whole long-suffering, for a delineation of those about to believe on him to life eternal. 17 Now to the King of the ages, the incorruptible, invisible, only God, honour and glory to the ages of ages. Amen.

18 This charge, my child Timotheus, I commit to thee, according to the prophecies as to thee preceding, in order that thou mightest war by them the good warfare, 19 maintaining faith and a good conscience; which last some, having put away, have made shipwreck as to faith; 20 of whom is Hymenaeus and Alexander, whom I have delivered to Satan, that they may be taught by discipline not to blaspheme.

1 Timothy 3

1 The word is faithful: if any one aspires to exercise oversight, he desires a good work. 2 The overseer then must be irreproachable, husband of one wife, sober, discreet, decorous, hospitable, apt to teach; 3 not given to excesses from wine, not a striker, but mild, not addicted to contention, not fond of money, 4 conducting his own house well, having his children in subjection with all gravity; 5 (but if one does not know how to conduct his own house, how shall he take care of the assembly of God?) 6 not a novice, that he may not, being inflated, fall into the fault of the devil. 7 But it is necessary that he should have also a good testimony from those without, that he may fall not into reproach and the snare of the devil.

8 Ministers, in like manner, grave, not double-tongued, not given to much wine, not seeking gain by base means, 9 holding the mystery of the faith in a pure conscience. 10 And let these be first proved, then let them minister, being without charge against them. 11 The women in like manner grave, not slanderers, sober, faithful in all things. 12 Let the ministers be husbands of one wife, conducting their children and their own houses well: 13 for those who shall have ministered well obtain for themselves a good degree, and much boldness in faith which is in Christ Jesus.

14 These things I write to thee, hoping to come to thee more quickly; 15 but if I delay, in order that thou mayest know how one ought to conduct oneself in God's house, which is the assembly of the living God, the pillar and base of the truth. 16 And confessedly the mystery of piety is great. God has been manifested in flesh, has been justified in the Spirit, has appeared to angels, has been preached among the nations, has been believed on in the world, has been received up in glory.

1 Timothy 5

1 Rebuke not an elder sharply, but exhort him as a father, younger men as brethren, 2 elder women as mothers, younger women as sisters, with all purity.

3 Honour widows who are really widows; 4 but if any widow have children or descendants, let them learn first to be pious as regards their own house, and to render a return on their side to their parents; for this is acceptable in the sight of God. 5 Now she who is a widow indeed, and is left alone, has put her hope in God, and continues in supplications and prayers night and day. 6 But she that lives in habits of self-indulgence is dead while living. 7 And these things enjoin, that they may be irreproachable. 8 But if any one does not provide for his own, and specially for those of his house, he has denied the faith, and is worse than the unbeliever. 9 Let a widow be put upon the list, being of not less than sixty years, having been wife of one man, 10 borne witness to in good works, if she have brought up children, if she have exercised hospitality, if she have washed saints' feet, if she have imparted relief to the distressed, if she have diligently followed every good work. 11 But younger widows decline; for when they grow wanton against Christ, they desire to marry, 12 being guilty, because they have cast off their first faith. 13 And, at the same time, they learn also to be idle, going about to people's houses; and not only idle, but also gossipers and meddlers, speaking things not becoming. 14 I will therefore that the younger marry, bear children, rule the house, give no occasion to the adversary in respect of reproach. 15 For already some have turned aside after Satan. 16 If any believing man or woman have widows, let them impart relief to them, and let not the assembly be charged, that it may impart relief to those that are widows indeed.

17 Let the elders who take the lead among the saints well be esteemed worthy of double honour, specially those labouring in word and teaching; 18 for the scripture says, Thou shalt not muzzle an ox that treadeth out corn, and, The workman is worthy of his hire. 19 Against an elder receive not an accusation unless where there are two or three witnesses. 20 Those that sin convict before all, that the rest also may have fear. 21 I testify before God and Christ Jesus and the elect angels, that thou keep these things without prejudice, doing nothing by favour. 22 Lay hands quickly on no man, nor partake in others' sins. Keep thyself pure. 23 Drink no longer only water, but use a little wine on account of thy stomach and thy frequent illnesses. 24 Of some men the sins are manifest beforehand, going before to judgment, and some also they follow after. 25 In like manner good works also are manifest beforehand, and those that are otherwise cannot be hid.

1 Timothy 6

1 Let as many bondmen as are under yoke count their own masters worthy of all honour, that the name of God and the teaching be not blasphemed. 2 And they that have believing masters, let them not despise them because they are brethren; but let them the rather serve them with subjection, because they are faithful and beloved, who profit by the good and ready service rendered. These things teach and exhort. 3 If any one teach differently, and do not accede to sound words, those of our Lord Jesus Christ, and the teaching which is according to piety, 4 he is puffed up, knowing nothing, but sick about questions and disputes of words, out of which arise envy, strife, injurious words, evil suspicions, 5 constant quarrellings of men corrupted in mind and destitute of the truth, holding gain to be the end of piety.

6 But piety with contentment is great gain. 7 For we have brought nothing into the world: it is manifest that neither can we carry anything out. 8 But having sustenance and covering, we will be content with these. 9 But those who desire to be rich fall into temptation and a snare, and many unwise and hurtful lusts, which plunge men into destruction and ruin. 10 For the love of money is the root of every evil; which some having aspired after, have wandered from the faith, and pierced themselves with many sorrows. 11 But thou, O man of God, flee these things, and pursue righteousness, piety, faith, love, endurance, meekness of spirit. 12 Strive earnestly in the good conflict of faith. Lay hold of eternal life, to which thou hast been called, and hast confessed the good confession before many witnesses.

13 I enjoin thee before God who preserves all things in life, and Christ Jesus who witnessed before Pontius Pilate the good confession, 14 that thou keep the commandment spotless, irreproachable, until the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ; 15 which in its own time the blessed and only Ruler shall shew, the King of those that reign, and Lord of those that exercise lordship; 16 who only has immortality, dwelling in unapproachable light; whom no man has seen, nor is able to see; to whom be honour and eternal might. Amen. 17 Enjoin on those rich in the present age not to be high-minded, nor to trust on the uncertainty of riches; but in the God who affords us all things richly for our enjoyment; 18 to do good, to be rich in good works, to be liberal in distributing, disposed to communicate of their substance, 19 laying by for themselves a good foundation for the future, that they may lay hold of what is really life. 20 O Timotheus, keep the entrusted deposit, avoiding profane, vain babblings, and oppositions of false-named knowledge, 21 of which some having made profession, have missed the faith. Grace be with thee.

2 Timothy 1

1 Paul, apostle of Jesus Christ by God's will, according to promise of life, the life which is in Christ Jesus, 2 to Timotheus, my beloved child: grace, mercy, peace, from God the Father, and Christ Jesus our Lord. 3 I am thankful to God, whom I serve from my forefathers with pure conscience, how unceasingly I have the remembrance of thee in my supplications night and day, 4 earnestly desiring to see thee, remembering thy tears, that I may be filled with joy; 5 calling to mind the unfeigned faith which has been in thee, which dwelt first in thy grandmother Lois, and in thy mother Eunice, and I am persuaded that in thee also.

6 For which cause I put thee in mind to rekindle the gift of God which is in thee by the putting on of my hands. 7 For God has not given us a spirit of cowardice, but of power, and of love, and of wise discretion. 8 Be not therefore ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me his prisoner; but suffer evil along with the glad tidings, according to the power of God; 9 who has saved us, and has called us with a holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpose and grace, which was given to us in Christ Jesus before the ages of time, 10 but has been made manifest now by the appearing of our Saviour Jesus Christ, who has annulled death, and brought to light life and incorruptibility by the glad tidings; 11 to which I have been appointed a herald and apostle and teacher of the nations. 12 For which cause also I suffer these things; but I am not ashamed; for I know whom I have believed, and am persuaded that he is able to keep for that day the deposit I have entrusted to him. 13 Have an outline of sound words, which words thou hast heard of me, in faith and love which are in Christ Jesus. 14 Keep, by the Holy Spirit which dwells in us, the good deposit entrusted.

15 Thou knowest this, that all who are in Asia, of whom is Phygellus and Hermogenes, have turned away from me. 16 The Lord grant mercy to the house of Onesiphorus, for he has often refreshed me, and has not been ashamed of my chain; 17 but being in Rome sought me out very diligently, and found me-- 18 the Lord grant to him to find mercy from the Lord in that day--and how much service he rendered in Ephesus thou knowest best.

2 Timothy 2

1 Thou therefore, my child, be strong in the grace which is in Christ Jesus. 2 And the things thou hast heard of me in the presence of many witnesses, these entrust to faithful men, such as shall be competent to instruct others also. 3 Take thy share in suffering as a good soldier of Jesus Christ. 4 No one going as a soldier entangles himself with the affairs of life, that he may please him who has enlisted him as a soldier. 5 And if also any one contend in the games, he is not crowned unless he contend lawfully. 6 The husbandman must labour before partaking of the fruits. 7 Think of what I say, for the Lord will give thee understanding in all things.

8 Remember Jesus Christ raised from among the dead, of the seed of David, according to my glad tidings, 9 in which I suffer even unto bonds as an evil-doer: but the word of God is not bound. 10 For this cause I endure all things for the sake of the elect, that they also may obtain the salvation which is in Christ Jesus with eternal glory. 11 The word is faithful; for if we have died together with him, we shall also live together; 12 if we endure, we shall also reign together; if we deny, he also will deny us; 13 if we are unfaithful, he abides faithful, for he cannot deny himself.

14 Of these things put in remembrance, testifying earnestly before the Lord not to have disputes of words, profitable for nothing, to the subversion of the hearers. 15 Strive diligently to present thyself approved to God, a workman that has not to be ashamed, cutting in a straight line the word of truth. 16 But profane, vain babblings shun, for they will advance to greater impiety, 17 and their word will spread as a gangrene; of whom is Hymenaeus and Philetus; 18 men who as to the truth have gone astray, saying that the resurrection has taken place already; and overthrow the faith of some.

19 Yet the firm foundation of God stands, having this seal, The Lord knows those that are his; and, Let every one who names the name of the Lord withdraw from iniquity. 20 But in a great house there are not only gold and silver vessels, but also wooden and earthen; and some to honour, and some to dishonour. 21 If therefore one shall have purified himself from these, in separating himself from them, he shall be a vessel to honour, sanctified, serviceable to the Master, prepared for every good work.

22 But youthful lusts flee, and pursue righteousness, faith, love, peace, with those that call upon the Lord out of a pure heart. 23 But foolish and senseless questionings avoid, knowing that they beget contentions. 24 And a bondman of the Lord ought not to contend, but be gentle towards all; apt to teach; forbearing; 25 in meekness setting right those who oppose, if God perhaps may sometime give them repentance to acknowledgment of the truth, 26 and that they may awake up out of the snare of the devil, who are taken by him, for his will.

2 Timothy 4

1 I testify before God and Christ Jesus, who is about to judge living and dead, and by his appearing and his kingdom, 2 proclaim the word; be urgent in season and out of season, convict, rebuke, encourage, with all longsuffering and doctrine. 3 For the time shall be when they will not bear sound teaching; but according to their own lusts will heap up to themselves teachers, having an itching ear; 4 and they will turn away their ear from the truth, and will have turned aside to fables. 5 But thou, be sober in all things, bear evils, do the work of an evangelist, fill up the full measure of thy ministry. 6 For I am already being poured out, and the time of my release is come. 7 I have combated the good combat, I have finished the race, I have kept the faith. 8 Henceforth the crown of righteousness is laid up for me, which the Lord, the righteous Judge, will render to me in that day; but not only to me, but also to all who love his appearing.

9 Use diligence to come to me quickly; 10 for Demas has forsaken me, having loved the present age, and is gone to Thessalonica; Crescens to Galatia, Titus to Dalmatia. 11 Luke alone is with me. Take Mark, and bring him with thyself, for he is serviceable to me for ministry. 12 But Tychicus I have sent to Ephesus. 13 The cloak which I left behind me in Troas at Carpus's, bring when thou comest, and the books, especially the parchments. 14 Alexander the smith did many evil things against me. The Lord will render to him according to his works. 15 Against whom be thou also on thy guard, for he has greatly withstood our words.

16 At my first defence no man stood with me, but all deserted me. May it not be imputed to them. 17 But the Lord stood with me, and gave me power, that through me the proclamation might be fully made, and all those of the nations should hear; and I was delivered out of the lion's mouth. 18 The Lord shall deliver me from every wicked work, and shall preserve me for his heavenly kingdom; to whom be glory for the ages of ages. Amen. 19 Salute Prisca and Aquila, and the house of Onesiphorus. 20 Erastus remained in Corinth, but Trophimus I left behind in Miletus sick. 21 Use diligence to come before winter. Eubulus salutes thee, and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and the brethren all. 22 The Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Grace be with you.

Titus 1

1 Paul, bondman of God, and apostle of Jesus Christ according to the faith of God's elect, and knowledge of the truth which is according to piety; 2 in the hope of eternal life, which God, who cannot lie, promised before the ages of time, 3 but has manifested in its own due season his word, in the proclamation with which I have been entrusted, according to the commandment of our Saviour God; 4 to Titus, my own child according to the faith common to us: Grace and peace from God the Father, and Christ Jesus our Saviour.

5 For this cause I left thee in Crete, that thou mightest go on to set right what remained unordered, and establish elders in each city, as I had ordered thee:

6 if any one be free from all charge against him, husband of one wife, having believing children not accused of excess or unruly. 7 For the overseer must be free from all charge against him as God's steward; not headstrong, not passionate, not disorderly through wine, not a striker, not seeking gain by base means; 8 but hospitable, a lover of goodness, discreet, just, pious, temperate, 9 clinging to the faithful word according to the doctrine taught, that he may be able both to encourage with sound teaching and refute gainsayers. 10 For there are many and disorderly vain speakers and deceivers of people's minds, specially those of the circumcision, 11 who must have their mouths stopped, who subvert whole houses, teaching things which ought not to be taught for the sake of base gain. 12 One of themselves, a prophet of their own, has said, Cretans are always liars, evil wild beasts, lazy gluttons. 13 This testimony is true; for which cause rebuke them severely, that they may be sound in the faith, 14 not turning their minds to Jewish fables and commandments of men turning away from the truth. 15 All things are pure to the pure; but to the defiled and unbelieving nothing is pure; but both their mind and their conscience are defiled. 16 They profess to know God, but in works deny him, being abominable, and disobedient, and found worthless as to every good work.

Titus 3

1 Put them in mind to be subject to rulers, to authorities, to be obedient to rule, to be ready to do every good work, 2 to speak evil of no one, not to be contentious, to be mild, shewing all meekness towards all men. 3 For we were once ourselves also without intelligence, disobedient, wandering in error, serving various lusts and pleasures, living in malice and envy, hateful, and hating one another. 4 But when the kindness and love to man of our Saviour God appeared, 5 not on the principle of works which have been done in righteousness which we had done, but according to his own mercy he saved us through the washing of regeneration and renewal of the Holy Spirit, 6 which he poured out on us richly through Jesus Christ our Saviour; 7 that, having been justified by his grace, we should become heirs according to the hope of eternal life. 8 The word is faithful, and I desire that thou insist strenuously on these things, that they who have believed God may take care to pay diligent attention to good works. These things are good and profitable to men.

9 But foolish questions, and genealogies, and strifes, and contentions about the law, shun; for they are unprofitable and vain. 10 An heretical man after a first and second admonition have done with, 11 knowing that such a one is perverted, and sins, being self-condemned. 12 When I shall send Artemas to thee, or Tychicus, use diligence to come to me to Nicopolis; for I have decided to winter there. 13 Zenas the lawyer and Apollos set forward diligently on their way, that nothing may be lacking to them; 14 and let ours also learn to apply themselves to good works for necessary wants, that they may not be unfruitful. 15 All with me salute thee. Salute those who love us in the faith. Grace be with you all.

Philemon 1

1 Paul, prisoner of Christ Jesus, and Timotheus the brother, to Philemon the beloved and our fellow-workman, 2 and to the sister Apphia and to Archippus our fellow-soldier, and to the assembly which is in thine house. 3 Grace to you and peace from God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ. 4 I thank my God, always making mention of thee at my prayers, 5 hearing of thy love and the faith which thou hast towards the Lord Jesus, and towards all the saints, 6 in such sort that thy participation in the faith should become operative in the acknowledgment of every good thing which is in us towards Christ Jesus. 7 For we have great thankfulness and encouragement through thy love, because the bowels of the saints are refreshed by thee, brother.

8 Wherefore having much boldness in Christ to enjoin thee what is fitting, 9 for love's sake I rather exhort, being such a one as Paul the aged, and now also prisoner of Jesus Christ. 10 I exhort thee for my child, whom I have begotten in my bonds, Onesimus, 11 once unserviceable to thee, but now serviceable to thee and to me: 12 whom I have sent back to thee: but do thou receive him, that is, my bowels: 13 whom I was desirous of keeping with myself, that for thee he might minister to me in the bonds of the glad tidings; 14 but I have wished to do nothing without thy mind, that thy good might not be as of necessity but of willingness: 15 for perhaps for this reason he has been separated from thee for a time, that thou mightest possess him fully for ever; 16 not any longer as a bondman, but above a bondman, a beloved brother, specially to me, and how much rather to thee, both in the flesh and in the Lord? 17 If therefore thou holdest me to be a partner with thee, receive him as me; 18 but if he have wronged thee anything or owe anything to thee, put this to my account. 19 I Paul have written it with mine own hand; I will repay it: that I say not to thee that thou owest even thine own self also to me. 20 Yea, brother, I would have profit of thee in the Lord: refresh my bowels in Christ. 21 Being confident of thine obedience, I have written to thee, knowing that thou wilt do even more than I say. 22 But withal prepare me also a lodging; for I hope that I shall be granted to you through your prayers. 23 Epaphras salutes thee, my fellow-prisoner in Christ Jesus; 24 Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, Luke, my fellow-workmen. 25 The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit.

Hebrews 1

1 God having spoken in many parts and in many ways formerly to the fathers in the prophets, 2 at the end of these days has spoken to us in the person of the Son, whom he has established heir of all things, by whom also he made the worlds; 3 who being the effulgence of his glory and the expression of his substance, and upholding all things by the word of his power, having made by himself the purification of sins, set himself down on the right hand of the greatness on high,

4 taking a place by so much better than the angels, as he inherits a name more excellent than they. 5 For to which of the angels said he ever, Thou art my Son: this day have I begotten thee? and again, I will be to him for father, and he shall be to me for son? 6 and again, when he brings in the firstborn into the habitable world, he says, And let all God's angels worship him. 7 And as to the angels he says, Who makes his angels spirits and his ministers a flame of fire; 8 but as to the Son, Thy throne, O God, is to the age of the age, and a sceptre of uprightness is the sceptre of thy kingdom. 9 Thou hast loved righteousness and hast hated lawlessness; therefore God, thy God, has anointed thee with oil of gladness above thy companions. 10 And, Thou in the beginning, Lord, hast founded the earth, and works of thy hands are the heavens. 11 They shall perish, but thou continuest still; and they all shall grow old as a garment, 12 and as a covering shalt thou roll them up, and they shall be changed; but thou art the Same, and thy years shall not fail. 13 But as to which of the angels said he ever, Sit at my right hand until I put thine enemies as footstool of thy feet? 14 Are they not all ministering spirits, sent out for service on account of those who shall inherit salvation?

Hebrews 2

1 For this reason we should give heed more abundantly to the things we have heard, lest in any way we should slip away. 2 For if the word which was spoken by angels was firm, and every transgression and disobedience received just retribution, 3 how shall we escape if we have been negligent of so great salvation, which, having had its commencement in being spoken of by the Lord, has been confirmed to us by those who have heard; 4 God bearing, besides, witness with them to it, both by signs and wonders, and various acts of power, and distributions of the Holy Spirit, according to his will?

5 For he has not subjected to angels the habitable world which is to come, of which we speak; 6 but one has testified somewhere, saying, What is man, that thou rememberest him, or son of man that thou visitest him? 7 Thou hast made him some little inferior to the angels; thou hast crowned him with glory and honour, and hast set him over the works of thy hands; 8 thou hast subjected all things under his feet. For in subjecting all things to him, he has left nothing unsubject to him. But now we see not yet all things subjected to him, 9 but we see Jesus, who was made some little inferior to angels on account of the suffering of death, crowned with glory and honour; so that by the grace of God he should taste death for every thing.

10 For it became him, for whom are all things, and by whom are all things, in bringing many sons to glory, to make perfect the leader of their salvation through sufferings. 11 For both he that sanctifies and those sanctified are all of one; for which cause he is not ashamed to call them brethren, 12 saying, I will declare thy name to my brethren; in the midst of the assembly will I sing thy praises. 13 And again, I will trust in him. And again, Behold, I and the children which God has given me.

14 Since therefore the children partake of blood and flesh, he also, in like manner, took part in the same, that through death he might annul him who has the might of death, that is, the devil; 15 and might set free all those who through fear of death through the whole of their life were subject to bondage. 16 For he does not indeed take hold of angels by the hand, but he takes hold of the seed of Abraham. 17 Wherefore it behoved him in all things to be made like to his brethren, that he might be a merciful and faithful high priest in things relating to God, to make propitiation for the sins of the people; 18 for, in that himself has suffered, being tempted, he is able to help those that are being tempted.

Hebrews 3

1 Wherefore, holy brethren, partakers of the heavenly calling, consider the Apostle and High Priest of our confession, Jesus, 2 who is faithful to him that has constituted him, as Moses also in all his house. 3 For he has been counted worthy of greater glory than Moses, by how much he that has built it has more honour than the house. 4 For every house is built by some one; but he who has built all things is God. 5 And Moses indeed was faithful in all his house, as a ministering servant, for a testimony of the things to be spoken after; 6 but Christ, as Son over his house, whose house are we, if indeed we hold fast the boldness and the boast of hope firm to the end.

7 Wherefore, even as says the Holy Spirit, To-day if ye will hear his voice, 8 harden not your hearts, as in the provocation, in the day of temptation in the wilderness; 9 where your fathers tempted me, by proving me, and saw my works forty years. 10 Wherefore I was wroth with this generation, and said, They always err in heart; and they have not known my ways; 11 so I swore in my wrath, If they shall enter into my rest. 12 See, brethren, lest there be in any one of you a wicked heart of unbelief, in turning away from the living God. 13 But encourage yourselves each day, as long as it is called To-day, that none of you be hardened by the deceitfulness of sin. 14 For we are become companions of the Christ if indeed we hold the beginning of the assurance firm to the end; 15 in that it is said, To-day if ye will hear his voice, do not harden your hearts, as in the provocation; 16 (for who was it, who, having heard, provoked? but was it not all who came out of Egypt by Moses? 17 And with whom was he wroth forty years? Was it not with those who had sinned, whose carcases fell in the wilderness? 18 And to whom sware he that they should not enter into his rest, but to those who had not hearkened to the word? 19 And we see that they could not enter in on account of unbelief;)

Hebrews 4

1 Let us therefore fear, lest, a promise being left of entering into his rest, any one of you might seem to have failed of it. 2 For indeed we have had glad tidings presented to us, even as they also; but the word of the report did not profit them, not being mixed with faith in those who heard. 3 For we enter into the rest who have believed; as he said, As I have sworn in my wrath, If they shall enter into my rest; although the works had been completed from the foundation of the world. 4 For he has said somewhere of the seventh day thus, And God rested on the seventh day from all his works: 5 and in this again, If they shall enter into my rest. 6 Seeing therefore it remains that some enter into it, and those who first received the glad tidings did not enter in on account of not hearkening to the word, 7 again he determines a certain day, saying, in David, 'To-day,' after so long a time; (according as it has been said before), To-day, if ye will hear his voice, harden not your hearts. 8 For if Jesus had brought them into rest, he would not have spoken afterwards about another day. 9 There remains then a sabbatism to the people of God. 10 For he that has entered into his rest, he also has rested from his works, as God did from his own.

11 Let us therefore use diligence to enter into that rest, that no one may fall after the same example of not hearkening to the word. 12 For the word of God is living and operative, and sharper than any two-edged sword, and penetrating to the division of soul and spirit, both of joints and marrow, and a discerner of the thoughts and intents of theheart. 13 And there is not a creature unapparent before him; but all things are naked and laid bare to his eyes, with whom we have to do. 14 Having therefore a great high priest who has passed through the heavens, Jesus the Son of God, let us hold fast the confession. 15 For we have not a high priest not able to sympathise with our infirmities, but tempted in all things in like manner, sin apart. 16 Let us approach therefore with boldness to the throne of grace, that we may receive mercy, and find grace for seasonable help.

Hebrews 5

1 For every high priest taken from amongst men is established for men in things relating to God, that he may offer both gifts and sacrifices for sins; 2 being able to exercise forbearance towards the ignorant and erring, since he himself also is clothed with infirmity; 3 and, on account of this infirmity, he ought, even as for the people, so also for himself, to offer for sins. 4 And no one takes the honour to himself but as called by God, even as Aaron also. 5 Thus the Christ also has not glorified himself to be made a high priest; but he who had said to him, Thou art my Son, I have to-day begotten thee. 6 Even as also in another place he says, Thou art a priest for ever according to the order of Melchisedec. 7 Who in the days of his flesh, having offered up both supplications and entreaties to him who was able to save him out of death, with strong crying and tears; (and having been heard because of his piety;) 8 though he were Son, he learned obedience from the things which he suffered; 9 and having been perfected, became to all them that obey him, author of eternal salvation;

10 addressed by God as high priest according to the order of Melchisedec. 11 Concerning whom we have much to say, and hard to be interpreted in speaking of it, since ye are become dull in hearing. 12 For when for the time ye ought to be teachers, ye have again need that one should teach you what are the elements of the beginning of the oracles of God, and are become such as have need of milk, and not of solid food. 13 For every one that partakes of milk is unskilled in the word of righteousness, for he is a babe; 14 but solid food belongs to full-grown men, who, on account of habit, have their senses exercised for distinguishing both good and evil.

Hebrews 6

1 Wherefore, leaving the word of the beginning of the Christ, let us go on to what belongs to full growth, not laying again a foundation of repentance from dead works and faith in God, 2 of the doctrine of washings, and of imposition of hands, and of resurrection of the dead, and of eternal judgment; 3 and this will we do if God permit. 4 For it is impossible to renew again to repentance those once enlightened, and who have tasted of the heavenly gift, and have been made partakers of the Holy Spirit, 5 and have tasted the good word of God, and the works of power of the age to come, 6 and have fallen away, crucifying for themselves as they do the Son of God, and making a show of him. 7 For ground which drinks the rain which comes often upon it, and produces useful herbs for those for whose sakes also it is tilled, partakes of blessing from God; 8 but bringing forth thorns and briars, it is found worthless and nigh to a curse, whose end is to be burned.

9 But we are persuaded concerning you, beloved, better things, and connected with salvation, even if we speak thus. 10 For God is not unrighteous to forget your work, and the love which ye have shewn to his name, having ministered to the saints, and still ministering. 11 But we desire earnestly that each one of you shew the same diligence to the full assurance of hope unto the end; 12 that ye be not sluggish, but imitators of those who through faith and patience have been inheritors of the promises. 13 For God, having promised to Abraham, since he had no greater to swear by, swore by himself, 14 saying, Surely blessing I will bless thee, and multiplying I will multiply thee; 15 and thus, having had long patience, he got the promise. 16 For men indeed swear by a greater, and with them the oath is a term to all dispute, as making matters sure. 17 Wherein God, willing to shew more abundantly to the heirs of the promise the unchangeableness of his purpose, intervened by an oath, 18 that by two unchangeable things, in which it was impossible that God should lie, we might have a strong encouragement, who have fled for refuge to lay hold on the hope set before us, 19 which we have as anchor of the soul, both secure and firm, and entering into that within the veil, 20 where Jesus is entered as forerunner for us, become for ever a high priest according to the order of Melchisedec.

Hebrews 7

1 For this Melchisedec, King of Salem, priest of the most high God, who met Abraham returning from smiting the kings, and blessed him; 2 to whom Abraham gave also the tenth portion of all; first being interpreted King of righteousness, and then also King of Salem, which is King of peace; 3 without father, without mother, without genealogy; having neither beginning of days nor end of life, but assimilated to the Son of God, abides a priest continually. 4 Now consider how great this personage was, to whom even the patriarch Abraham gave a tenth out of the spoils. 5 And they indeed from among the sons of Levi, who receive the priesthood, have commandment to take tithes from the people according to the law, that is from their brethren, though these are come out of the loins of Abraham: 6 but he who has no genealogy from them has tithed Abraham, and blessed him who had the promises. 7 But beyond all gainsaying, the inferior is blessed by the better. 8 And here dying men receive tithes; but there one of whom the witness is that he lives; 9 and, so to speak, through Abraham, Levi also, who received tithes, has been made to pay tithes. 10 For he was yet in the loins of his father when Melchisedec met him.

11 If indeed then perfection were by the Levitical priesthood, for the people had their law given to them in connexion with it, what need was there still that a different priest should arise according to the order of Melchisedec, and not be named after the order of Aaron? 12 For, the priesthood being changed, there takes place of necessity a change of law also. 13 For he, of whom these things are said, belongs to a different tribe, of which no one has ever been attached to the service of the altar. 14 For it is clear that our Lord has sprung out of Juda, as to which tribe Moses spake nothing as to priests. 15 And it is yet more abundantly evident, since a different priest arises according to the similitude of Melchisedec, 16 who has been constituted not according to law of fleshly commandment, but according to power of indissoluble life. 17 For it is borne witness, Thou art a priest for ever according to the order of Melchisedec. 18 For there is a setting aside of the commandment going before for its weakness and unprofitableness, 19 (for the law perfected nothing,) and the introduction of a better hope by which we draw nigh to God. 20 And by how much it was not without the swearing of an oath; 21 (for they are become priests without the swearing of an oath, but he with the swearing of an oath, by him who said, as to him, The Lord has sworn, and will not repent of it, Thou art priest for ever according to the order of Melchisedec;) 22 by so much Jesus became surety of a better covenant. 23 And they have been many priests, on account of being hindered from continuing by death; 24 but he, because of his continuing for ever, has the priesthood unchangeable. 25 Whence also he is able to save completely those who approach by him to God, always living to intercede for them. 26 For such a high priest became us, holy, harmless, undefiled, separated from sinners, and become higher than the heavens: 27 who has not day by day need, as the high priests, first to offer up sacrifices for his own sins, then for those of the people; for this he did once for all in having offered up himself. 28 For the law constitutes men high priests, having infirmity; but the word of the swearing of the oath which is after the law, a Son perfected for ever.

Hebrews 8

1 Now a summary of the things of which we are speaking is, We have such a one high priest who has sat down on the right hand of the throne of the greatness in the heavens; 2 minister of the holy places and of the true tabernacle, which the Lord has pitched, and not man. 3 For every high priest is constituted for the offering both of gifts and sacrifices; whence it is needful that this one also should have something which he may offer. 4 If then indeed he were upon earth, he would not even be a priest, there being those who offer the gifts according to the law, 5 (who serve the representation and shadow of heavenly things, according as Moses was oracularly told when about to make the tabernacle; for See, saith He, that thou make all things according to the pattern which has been shewn to thee in the mountain.)

6 But now he has got a more excellent ministry, by so much as he is mediator of a better covenant, which is established on the footing of better promises. 7 For if that first was faultless, place had not been sought for a second. 8 For finding fault, he says to them, Behold, days come, saith the Lord, and I will consummate a new covenant as regards the house of Israel, and as regards the house of Juda; 9 not according to the covenant which I made to their fathers in the day of my taking their hand to lead them out of the land of Egypt; because they did not continue in my covenant, and I did not regard them, saith theLord. 10 Because this is the covenant that I will covenant to the house of Israel after those days, saith the Lord: Giving my laws into their mind, I will write them also upon their hearts; and I will be to them for God, and they shall be to me for people. 11 And they shall not teach each his fellow-citizen, and each his brother, saying, Know the Lord; because all shall know me in themselves, from the little one among them unto the great among them. 12 Because I will be merciful to their unrighteousnesses, and their sins and their lawlessnesses I will never remember any more. 13 In that he says New, he has made the first old; but that which grows old and aged is near disappearing.

Hebrews 9

1 The first therefore also indeed had ordinances of service, and the sanctuary, a worldly one. 2 For a tabernacle was set up; the first, in which were both the candlestick and the table and the exposition of the loaves, which is called Holy; 3 but after the second veil a tabernacle which is called Holy of holies, 4 having a golden censer, and the ark of the covenant, covered round in every part with gold, in which were the golden pot that had the manna, and the rod of Aaron that had sprouted, and the tables of the covenant; 5 and above over it the cherubim of glory shadowing the mercy-seat; concerning which it is not now the time to speak in detail. 6 Now these things being thus ordered, into the first tabernacle the priests enter at all times, accomplishing the services; 7 but into the second, the high priest only, once a year, not without blood, which he offers for himself and for the errors of the people:

8 the Holy Spirit shewing this, that the way of the holy of holies has not yet been made manifest while as yet the first tabernacle has its standing; 9 the which is an image for the present time, according to which both gifts and sacrifices, unable to perfect as to conscience him that worshipped, are offered, 10 consisting only of meats and drinks and divers washings, ordinances of flesh, imposed until the time of setting things right. 11 But Christ being come high priest of the good things to come, by the better and more perfect tabernacle not made with hand, (that is, not of this creation,) 12 nor by blood of goats and calves, but by his own blood, has entered in once for all into the holy of holies, having found an eternal redemption. 13 For if the blood of goats and bulls, and a heifer's ashes sprinkling the defiled, sanctifies for the purity of the flesh, 14 how much rather shall the blood of the Christ, who by the eternal Spirit offered himself spotless to God, purify your conscience from dead works to worship the living God?

15 And for this reason he is mediator of a new covenant, so that, death having taken place for redemption of the transgressions under the first covenant, the called might receive the promise of the eternal inheritance. 16 (For where there is a testament, the death of the testator must needs come in. 17 For a testament is of force when men are dead, since it is in no way of force while the testator is alive.) 18 Whence neither the first was inaugurated without blood. 19 For every commandment having been spoken according to the law by Moses to all the people; having taken the blood of calves and goats, with water and scarlet wool and hyssop, he sprinkled both the book itself and all the people, 20 saying, This is the blood of the covenant which God has enjoined to you. 21 And the tabernacle too and all the vessels of service he sprinkled in like manner with blood; 22 and almost all things are purified with blood according to the law, and without blood-shedding there is no remission.

23 It was necessary then that the figurative representations of the things in the heavens should be purified with these; but the heavenly things themselves with sacrifices better than these. 24 For the Christ is not entered into holy places made with hand, figures of the true, but into heaven itself, now to appear before the face of God for us: 25 nor in order that he should offer himself often, as the high priest enters into the holy places every year with blood not his own; 26 since he had then been obliged often to suffer from the foundation of the world. But now once in the consummation of the ages he has been manifested for the putting away of sin by his sacrifice. 27 And forasmuch as it is the portion of men once to die, and after this judgment; 28 thus the Christ also, having been once offered to bear the sins of many, shall appear to those that look for him the second time without sin for salvation.

Hebrews 10

1 For the law, having a shadow of the coming good things, not the image itself of the things, can never, by the same sacrifices which they offer continually yearly, perfect those who approach. 2 Since, would they not indeed have ceased being offered, on account of the worshippers once purged having no longer any conscience of sins? 3 But in these there is a calling to mind of sins yearly. 4 For blood of bulls and goats is incapable of taking away sins. 5 Wherefore coming into the world he says, Sacrifice and offering thou willedst not; but thou hast prepared me a body. 6 Thou tookest no pleasure in burnt-offerings and sacrifices for sin.

7 Then I said, Lo, I come (in the roll of the book it is written of me) to do, O God, thy will. 8 Above, saying Sacrifices and offerings and burnt-offerings and sacrifices for sin thou willedst not, neither tookest pleasure in (which are offered according to the law); 9 then he said, Lo, I come to do thy will. He takes away the first that he may establish the second; 10 by which will we have been sanctified through the offering of the body of Jesus Christ once for all. 11 And every priest stands daily ministering, and offering often the same sacrifices, which can never take away sins. 12 But he, having offered one sacrifice for sins, sat down in perpetuity at the right hand of God, 13 waiting from henceforth until his enemies be set for the footstool of his feet. 14 For by one offering he has perfected in perpetuity the sanctified. 15 And the Holy Spirit also bears us witness of it; for after what was said: 16 This is the covenant which I will establish towards them after those days, saith the Lord: Giving my laws into their hearts, I will write them also in their understandings; 17 and their sins and their lawlessnesses I will never remember any more. 18 But where there is remission of these, there is no longer a sacrifice for sin.

19 Having therefore, brethren, boldness for entering into the holy of holies by the blood of Jesus, 20 the new and living way which he has dedicated for us through the veil, that is, his flesh, 21 and having a great priest over the house of God, 22 let us approach with a true heart, in full assurance of faith, sprinkled as to our hearts from a wicked conscience, and washed as to our body with pure water. 23 Let us hold fast the confession of the hope unwavering, (for he is faithful who has promised;) 24 and let us consider one another for provoking to love and good works; 25 not forsaking the assembling of ourselves together, as the custom is with some; but encouraging one another, and by so much the more as ye see the day drawing near. 26 For where we sin wilfully after receiving the knowledge of the truth, there no longer remains any sacrifice for sins, 27 but a certain fearful expectation of judgment, and heat of fire about to devour the adversaries. 28 Any one that has disregarded Moses' law dies without mercy on the testimony of two or three witnesses: 29 of how much worse punishment, think ye, shall he be judged worthy who has trodden under foot the Son of God, and esteemed the blood of the covenant, whereby he has been sanctified, common, and has insulted the Spirit of grace? 30 For we know him that said, To me belongs vengeance; I will recompense, saith the Lord: and again, The Lord shall judge his people. 31 It is a fearful thing falling into the hands of the living God. 32 But call to mind the earlier days in which, having been enlightened, ye endured much conflict of sufferings; 33 on the one hand, when ye were made a spectacle both in reproaches and afflictions; and on the other, when ye became partakers with those who were passing through them. 34 For ye both sympathised with prisoners and accepted with joy the plunder of your goods, knowing that ye have for yourselves a better substance, and an abiding one. 35 Cast not away therefore your confidence, which has great recompense. 36 For ye have need of endurance in order that, having done the will of God, ye may receive the promise. 37 For yet a very little while he that comes will come, and will not delay. 38 But the just shall live by faith; and, if he draw back, my soul does not take pleasure in him. 39 But we are not drawers back to perdition, but of faith to saving the soul.

Hebrews 11

1 Now faith is the substantiating of things hoped for, the conviction of things not seen. 2 For in the power of this the elders have obtained testimony. 3 By faith we apprehend that the worlds were framed by the word of God, so that that which is seen should not take its origin from things which appear.

4 By faith Abel offered to God a more excellent sacrifice than Cain, by which he obtained testimony of being righteous, God bearing testimony to his gifts, and by it, having died, he yet speaks. 5 By faith Enoch was translated that he should not see death; and was not found, because God had translated him; for before his translation he has the testimony that he had pleased God. 6 But without faith it is impossible to please him. For he that draws near to God must believe that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them who seek him out. 7 By faith, Noah, oracularly warned concerning things not yet seen, moved with fear, prepared an ark for the saving of his house; by which he condemned the world, and became heir of the righteousness which is according to faith. 8 By faith Abraham, being called, obeyed to go out into the place which he was to receive for an inheritance, and went out, not knowing where he was going. 9 By faith he sojourned as a stranger in the land of promise as a foreign country, having dwelt in tents with Isaac and Jacob, the heirs with him of the same promise; 10 for he waited for the city which has foundations, of which God is the artificer and constructor. 11 By faith also Sarah herself received strength for the conception of seed, and that beyond a seasonable age; since she counted him faithful who promised. 12 Wherefore also there have been born of one, and that of one become dead, even as the stars of heaven in multitude, and as the countless sand which is by the sea shore. 13 All these died in faith, not having received the promises, but having seen them from afar off and embraced them, and confessed that they were strangers and sojourners on the earth. 14 For they who say such things shew clearly that they seek their country. 15 And if they had called to mind that from whence they went out, they had had opportunity to have returned; 16 but now they seek a better, that is, a heavenly; wherefore God is not ashamed of them, to be called their God; for he has prepared for them a city. 17 By faith Abraham, when tried, offered up Isaac, and he who had received to himself the promises offered up his only begotten son, 18 as to whom it had been said, In Isaac shall thy seed be called: 19 counting that God was able to raise him even from among the dead, whence also he received him in a figure. 20 By faith Isaac blessed Jacob and Esau concerning things to come. 21 By faith Jacob when dying blessed each of the sons of Joseph, and worshipped on the top of his staff. 22 By faith Joseph when dying called to mind the going forth of the sons of Israel, and gave commandment concerning his bones. 23 By faith Moses, being born, was hid three months by his parents, because they saw the child beautiful; and they did not fear the injunction of the king. 24 By faith Moses, when he had become great, refused to be called son of Pharaoh's daughter; 25 choosing rather to suffer affliction along with the people of God than to have the temporary pleasure of sin; 26 esteeming the reproach of the Christ greater riches than the treasures of Egypt, for he had respect to the recompense. 27 By faith he left Egypt, not fearing the wrath of the king; for he persevered, as seeing him who is invisible. 28 By faith he celebrated the passover and the sprinkling of the blood, that the destroyer of the firstborn might not touch them. 29 By faith they passed through the Red sea as through dry land; of which the Egyptians having made trial were swallowed up. 30 By faith the walls of Jericho fell, having been encircled for seven days. 31 By faith Rahab the harlot did not perish along with the unbelieving, having received the spies in peace.

32 And what more do I say? For the time would fail me telling of Gideon, and Barak, and Samson, and Jephthah, and David and Samuel, and of the prophets: 33 who by faith overcame kingdoms, wrought righteousness, obtained promises, stopped lions' mouths, 34 quenched the power of fire, escaped the edge of the sword, became strong out of weakness, became mighty in war, made the armies of strangers give way. 35 Women received their dead again by resurrection; and others were tortured, not having accepted deliverance, that they might get a better resurrection; 36 and others underwent trial of mockings and scourgings, yea, and of bonds and imprisonment. 37 They were stoned, were sawn asunder, were tempted, died by the death of the sword; they went about in sheepskins, in goatskins, destitute, afflicted, evil treated, 38 (of whom the world was not worthy,) wandering in deserts and mountains, and in dens and caverns of the earth. 39 And these all, having obtained witness through faith, did not receive the promise, 40 God having foreseen some better thing for us, that they should not be made perfect without us.

Hebrews 12

1 Let us also therefore, having so great a cloud of witnesses surrounding us, laying aside every weight, and sin which so easily entangles us, run with endurance the race that lies before us, 2 looking stedfastly on Jesus the leader and completer of faith: who, in view of the joy lying before him, endured the cross, having despised the shame, and is set down at the right hand of the throne of God. 3 For consider well him who endured so great contradiction from sinners against himself, that ye be not weary, fainting in your minds.

4 Ye have not yet resisted unto blood, wrestling against sin. 5 And ye have quite forgotten the exhortation which speaks to you as to sons: My son, despise not the chastening of the Lord, nor faint when reproved by him; 6 for whom the Lord loves he chastens, and scourges every son whom he receives. 7 Ye endure for chastening, God conducts himself towards you as towards sons; for who is the son that the father chastens not? 8 But if ye are without chastening, of which all have been made partakers, then are ye bastards, and not sons. 9 Moreover we have had the fathers of our flesh as chasteners, and we reverenced them; shall we not much rather be in subjection to the Father of spirits, and live? 10 For they indeed chastened for a few days, as seemed good to them; but he for profit, in order to the partaking of his holiness. 11 But no chastening at the time seems to be matter of joy, but of grief; but afterwards yields the peaceful fruit of righteousness to those exercised by it. 12 Wherefore lift up the hands that hang down, and the failing knees; 13 and make straight paths for your feet, that that which is lame be not turned aside; but that rather it may be healed. 14 Pursue peace with all, and holiness, without which no one shall see the Lord: 15 watching lest there be any one who lacks the grace of God; lest any root of bitterness springing up trouble you, and many be defiled by it; 16 lest there be any fornicator, or profane person, as Esau, who for one meal sold his birthright; 17 for ye know that also afterwards, desiring to inherit the blessing, he was rejected, (for he found no place for repentance) although he sought it earnestly with tears.

18 For ye have not come to the mount that might be touched and was all on fire, and to obscurity, and darkness, and tempest, 19 and trumpet's sound, and voice of words; which they that heard, excusing themselves, declined the word being addressed to them any more: 20 (for they were not able to bear what was enjoined: And if a beast should touch the mountain, it shall be stoned; 21 and, so fearful was the sight, Moses said, I am exceedingly afraid and full of trembling;) 22 but ye have come to mount Zion; and to the city of the living God, heavenly Jerusalem; and to myriads of angels, 23 the universal gathering; and to the assembly of the firstborn who are registered in heaven; and to God, judge of all; and to the spirits of just men made perfect; 24 and to Jesus, mediator of a new covenant; and to the blood of sprinkling, speaking better than Abel. 25 See that ye refuse not him that speaks. For if those did not escape who had refused him who uttered the oracles on earth, much more we who turn away from him who does so from heaven: 26 whose voice then shook the earth; but now he has promised, saying, Yet once will I shake not only the earth, but also the heaven. 27 But this Yet once, signifies the removing of what is shaken, as being made, that what is not shaken may remain. 28 Wherefore let us, receiving a kingdom not to be shaken, have grace, by which let us serve God acceptably with reverence and fear. 29 For also our God is a consuming fire.

Hebrews 13

1 Let brotherly love abide. 2 Be not forgetful of hospitality; for by it some have unawares entertained angels. 3 Remember prisoners, as bound with them; those that are evil-treated, as being yourselves also in the body. 4 Let marriage be held every way in honour, and the bed be undefiled; for fornicators and adulterers will God judge. 5 Let your conversation be without love of money, satisfied with your present circumstances; for he has said, I will not leave thee, neither will I forsake thee. 6 So that, taking courage, we may say, The Lord is my helper, and I will not be afraid: what will man do unto me? 7 Remember your leaders who have spoken to you the word of God; and considering the issue of their conversation, imitate their faith. 8 Jesus Christ is the same yesterday, and to-day, and to the ages to come. 9 Be not carried away with various and strange doctrines; for it is good that the heart be confirmed with grace, not meats; those who have walked in which have not been profited by them. 10 We have an altar of which they have no right to eat who serve the tabernacle; 11 for of those beasts whose blood is carried as sacrifices for sin into the holy of holies by the high priest, of these the bodies are burned outside the camp. 12 Wherefore also Jesus, that he might sanctify the people by his own blood, suffered without the gate: 13 therefore let us go forth to him without the camp, bearing his reproach: 14 for we have not here an abiding city, but we seek the coming one. 15 By him therefore let us offer the sacrifice of praise continually to God, that is, the fruit of the lips confessing his name. 16 But of doing good and communicating of your substance be not forgetful, for with such sacrifices God is well pleased. 17 Obey your leaders, and be submissive; for they watch over your souls as those that shall give account; that they may do this with joy, and not groaning, for this would be unprofitable for you.

18 Pray for us: for we persuade ourselves that we have a good conscience, in all things desirous to walk rightly. 19 But I much more beseech you to do this, that I may the more quickly be restored to you. 20 But the God of peace, who brought again from among the dead our Lord Jesus, the great shepherd of the sheep, in the power of the blood of the eternal covenant, 21 perfect you in every good work to the doing of his will, doing in you what is pleasing before him through Jesus Christ; to whom be glory for the ages of ages. Amen. 22 But I beseech you, brethren, bear the word of exhortation, for it is but in few words that I have written to you. 23 Know that our brother Timotheus is set at liberty; with whom, if he should come soon, I will see you. 24 Salute all your leaders, and all the saints. They from Italy salute you. 25 Grace be with you all. Amen.

James 1

1 James, bondman of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ, to the twelve tribes which are in the dispersion, greeting.

2 Count it all joy, my brethren, when ye fall into various temptations, 3 knowing that the proving of your faith works endurance. 4 But let endurance have its perfect work, that ye may be perfect and complete, lacking in nothing. 5 But if any one of you lack wisdom, let him ask of God, who gives to all freely and reproaches not, and it shall be given to him: 6 but let him ask in faith, nothing doubting. For he that doubts is like a wave of the sea driven by the wind and tossed about; 7 for let not that man think that he shall receive anything from the Lord; 8 he is a double-minded man, unstable in all his ways. 9 But let the brother of low degree glory in his elevation, 10 and the rich in his humiliation, because as the grass's flower he will pass away. 11 For the sun has risen with its burning heat, and has withered the grass, and its flower has fallen, and the comeliness of its look has perished: thus the rich also shall wither in his goings. 12 Blessed is the man who endures temptation; for, having been proved, he shall receive the crown of life, which He has promised to them that love him.

13 Let no man, being tempted, say, I am tempted of God. For God cannot be tempted by evil things, and himself tempts no one. 14 But every one is tempted, drawn away, and enticed by his own lust; 15 then lust, having conceived, gives birth to sin; but sin fully completed brings forth death. 16 Do not err, my beloved brethren. 17 Every good gift and every perfect gift comes down from above, from the Father of lights, with whom is no variation nor shadow of turning. 18 According to his own will begat he us by the word of truth, that we should be a certain first-fruits of his creatures.

19 So that, my beloved brethren, let every man be swift to hear, slow to speak, slow to wrath; 20 for man's wrath does not work God's righteousness. 21 Wherefore, laying aside all filthiness and abounding of wickedness, accept with meekness the implanted word, which is able to save your souls. 22 But be ye doers of the word and not hearers only, beguiling yourselves. 23 For if any man be a hearer of the word and not a doer, he is like to a man considering his natural face in a mirror: 24 for he has considered himself and is gone away, and straightway he has forgotten what he was like. 25 But he that fixes his view on the perfect law, that of liberty, and abides in it, being not a forgetful hearer but a doer of the work, he shall be blessed in his doing. 26 If any one think himself to be religious, not bridling his tongue, but deceiving his heart, this man's religion is vain. 27 Pure and undefiled religion before God and the Father is this: to visit orphans and widows in their affliction, to keep oneself unspotted from the world.

James 2

1 My brethren, do not have the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ, Lord of glory, with respect of persons: 2 for if there come unto your synagogue a man with a gold ring in splendid apparel, and a poor man also come in in vile apparel, 3 and ye look upon him who wears the splendid apparel, and say, Do thou sit here well, and say to the poor, Do thou stand there, or sit here under my footstool: 4 have ye not made a difference among yourselves, and become judges having evil thoughts? 5 Hear, my beloved brethren: Has not God chosen the poor as to the world, rich in faith, and heirs of the kingdom, which he has promised to them that love him? 6 But ye have despised the poor man. Do not the rich oppress you, and do notthey drag you before the tribunals? 7 And do notthey blaspheme the excellent name which has been called upon you?

8 If indeed ye keep the royal law according to the scripture, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself, ye do well. 9 But if ye have respect of persons, ye commit sin, being convicted by the law as transgressors. 10 For whoever shall keep the whole law and shall offend in one point, he has come under the guilt of breaking all. 11 For he who said, Thou shalt not commit adultery, said also, Thou shalt not kill. Now if thou dost not commit adultery, but killest, thou art become transgressor of the law. 12 So speak ye, and so act, as those that are to be judged by the law of liberty; 13 for judgment will be without mercy to him that has shewn no mercy. Mercy glories over judgment.

14 What is the profit, my brethren, if any one say he have faith, but have not works? can faith save him? 15 Now if a brother or a sister is naked and destitute of daily food, 16 and one from amongst you say to them, Go in peace, be warmed and filled; but give not to them the needful things for the body, what is the profit? 17 So also faith, if it have not works, is dead by itself. 18 But some one will say, Thou hast faith and I have works. Shew me thy faith without works, and I from my works will shew thee my faith. 19 Thou believest that God is one. Thou doest well. The demons even believe, and tremble. 20 But wilt thou know, O vain man, that faith without works is dead? 21 Was not Abraham our father justified by works when he had offered Isaac his son upon the altar? 22 Thou seest that faith wrought with his works, and that by works faith was perfected. 23 And the scripture was fulfilled which says, Abraham believed God, and it was reckoned to him as righteousness, and he was called Friend of God. 24 Ye see that a man is justified on the principle of works, and not on the principle of faith only. 25 But was not in like manner also Rahab the harlot justified on the principle of works, when she had received the messengers and put them forth by another way? 26 For as the body without a spirit is dead, so also faith without works is dead.

James 3

1 Be not many teachers, my brethren, knowing that we shall receive greater judgment. 2 For we all often offend. If any one offend not in word, he is a perfect man, able to bridle the whole body too. 3 Behold, we put the bits in the mouths of the horses, that they may obey us, and we turn round their whole bodies. 4 Behold also the ships, which are so great, and driven by violent winds, are turned about by a very small rudder, wherever the pleasure of the helmsman will. 5 Thus also the tongue is a little member, and boasts great things. See how little a fire, how large a wood it kindles! 6 and the tongue is fire, the world of unrighteousness; the tongue is set in our members, the defiler of the whole body, and which sets fire to the course of nature, and is set on fire of hell. 7 For every species both of beasts and of birds, both of creeping things and of sea animals, is tamed and has been tamed by the human species; 8 but the tongue can no one among men tame; it is an unsettled evil, full of death-bringing poison. 9 Therewith bless we the Lord and Father, and therewith curse we men made after the likeness of God. 10 Out of the same mouth goes forth blessing and cursing. It is not right, my brethren, that these things should be thus. 11 Does the fountain, out of the same opening, pour forth sweet and bitter? 12 Can, my brethren, a fig produce olives, or a vine figs? Neither can salt water make sweet water.

13 Who is wise and understanding among you; let him shew out of a good conversation his works in meekness of wisdom; 14 but if ye have bitter emulation and strife in your hearts, do not boast and lie against the truth. 15 This is not the wisdom which comes down from above, but earthly, natural, devilish. 16 For where emulation and strife are, there is disorder and every evil thing. 17 But the wisdom from above first is pure, then peaceful, gentle, yielding, full of mercy and good fruits, unquestioning, unfeigned. 18 But the fruit of righteousness in peace is sown for them that make peace.

James 4

1 Whence come wars and whence fightings among you? Is it not thence, --from your pleasures, which war in your members? 2 Ye lust and have not: ye kill and are full of envy, and cannot obtain; ye fight and war; ye have not because ye ask not. 3 Ye ask and receive not, because ye ask evilly, that ye may consume it in your pleasures. 4 Adulteresses, know ye not that friendship with the world is enmity with God? Whoever therefore is minded to be the friend of the world is constituted enemy of God. 5 Think ye that the scripture speaks in vain? Does the Spirit which has taken his abode in us desire enviously? 6 But he gives more grace. Wherefore he says, God sets himself against the proud, but gives grace to the lowly. 7 Subject yourselves therefore to God. Resist the devil, and he will flee from you. 8 Draw near to God, and he will draw near to you. Cleanse your hands, sinners, and purify your hearts, ye double-minded. 9 Be wretched, and mourn, and weep: let your laughter be turned to mourning, and your joy to heaviness. 10 Humble yourselves before the Lord, and he shall exalt you.

11 Speak not against one another, brethren. He that speaks against his brother, or judges his brother, speaks against the law and judges the law. But if thou judgest the law, thou art not doer of thelaw, but judge. 12 One is the lawgiver and judge, who is able to save and to destroy: but who art thou who judgest thy neighbour? 13 Go to now, ye who say, To-day or to-morrow will we go into such a city and spend a year there, and traffic and make gain, 14 ye who do not know what will be on the morrow, ( for what is your life? It is even a vapour, appearing for a little while, and then disappearing,) 15 instead of your saying, If the Lord should so will and we should live, we will also do this or that. 16 But now ye glory in your vauntings: all such glorying is evil. 17 To him therefore who knows how to do good, and does it not, to him it is sin.

James 5

1 Go to now, ye rich, weep, howling over your miseries that are coming upon you. 2 Your wealth is become rotten, and your garments moth-eaten. 3 Your gold and silver is eaten away, and their canker shall be for a witness against you, and shall eat your flesh as fire. Ye have heaped up treasure in the last days. 4 Behold, the wages of your labourers, who have harvested your fields, wrongfully kept back by you, cry, and the cries of those that have reaped are entered into the ears of the Lord of sabaoth. 5 Ye have lived luxuriously on the earth and indulged yourselves; ye have nourished your hearts as in a day of slaughter; 6 ye have condemned, ye have killed the just; he does not resist you. 7 Have patience, therefore, brethren, till the coming of the Lord. Behold, the labourer awaits the precious fruit of the earth, having patience for it until it receive the early and the latter rain. 8 Ye also have patience: stablish your hearts, for the coming of the Lord is drawn nigh. 9 Complain not one against another, brethren, that ye be not judged. Behold, the judge stands before the door. 10 Take as an example, brethren, of suffering and having patience, the prophets, who have spoken in the name of the Lord. 11 Behold, we call them blessed who have endured. Ye have heard of the endurance of Job, and seen the end of the Lord; that the Lord is full of tender compassion and pitiful.

12 But before all things, my brethren, swear not, neither by heaven, nor by the earth, nor by any other oath; but let your yea be yea, and your nay, nay, that ye do not fall under judgment. 13 Does any one among you suffer evil? let him pray. Is any happy? let him sing psalms. 14 Is any sick among you? let him call to him the elders of the assembly, and let them pray over him, anointing him with oil in the name of the Lord; 15 and the prayer of faith shall heal the sick, and the Lord shall raise him up; and if he be one who has committed sins, it shall be forgiven him. 16 Confess therefore your offences to one another, and pray for one another, that ye may be healed. The fervent supplication of the righteous man has much power. 17 Elias was a man of like passions to us, and he prayed with prayer that it should not rain; and it did not rain upon the earth three years and six months; 18 and again he prayed, and the heaven gave rain, and the earth caused its fruit to spring forth. 19 My brethren, if any one among you err from the truth, and one bring him back, 20 let him know that he that brings back a sinner from the error of his way shall save a soul from death and shall cover a multitude of sins.

1 Peter 1

1 Peter, apostle of Jesus Christ, to the sojourners of the dispersion of Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia, 2 elect according to the foreknowledge of God the Father, by sanctification of the Spirit, unto the obedience and sprinkling of the blood of Jesus Christ: Grace to you and peace be multiplied.

3 Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who, according to his great mercy, has begotten us again to a living hope through the resurrection of Jesus Christ from among the dead, 4 to an incorruptible and undefiled and unfading inheritance, reserved in the heavens for you, 5 who are kept guarded by the power of God through faith for salvation ready to be revealed in the last time.

6 Wherein ye exult, for a little while at present, if needed, put to grief by various trials, 7 that the proving of your faith, much more precious than of gold which perishes, though it be proved by fire, be found to praise and glory and honour in the revelation of Jesus Christ: 8 whom, having not seen, ye love; on whom though not now looking, but believing, ye exult with joy unspeakable and filled with the glory, 9 receiving the end of your faith, the salvation of your souls.

10 Concerning which salvation prophets, who have prophesied of the grace towards you, sought out and searched out; 11 searching what, or what manner of time, the Spirit of Christ which was in them pointed out, testifying before of the sufferings which belonged to Christ, and the glories after these. 12 To whom it was revealed, that not to themselves but to you they ministered those things, which have now been announced to you by those who have declared to you the glad tidings by theHoly Spirit, sent from heaven, which angels desire to look into.

13 Wherefore, having girded up the loins of your mind, be sober and hope with perfect stedfastness in the grace which will be brought to you at the revelation of Jesus Christ; 14 as children of obedience, not conformed to your former lusts in your ignorance; 15 but as he who has called you is holy, be ye also holy in all your conversation; 16 because it is written, Be ye holy, for I am holy. 17 And if ye invoke as Father him who, without regard of persons, judges according to the work of each, pass your time of sojourn in fear, 18 knowing that ye have been redeemed, not by corruptible things, as silver or gold, from your vain conversation handed down from your fathers, 19 but by precious blood, as of a lamb without blemish and without spot, the blood of Christ, 20 foreknown indeed before the foundation of the world, but who has been manifested at the end of times for your sakes, 21 who by him do believe on God, who has raised him from among the dead and given him glory, that your faith and hope should be in God. 22 Having purified your souls by obedience to the truth to unfeigned brotherly love, love one another out of a pure heart fervently; 23 being born again, not of corruptible seed, but of incorruptible, by the living and abiding word of God.

24 Because all flesh is as grass, and all its glory as the flower of grass. The grass has withered and its flower has fallen; 25 but the word of the Lord abides for eternity. But this is the word which in the glad tidings is preached to you.

1 Peter 2

1 Laying aside therefore all malice and all guile and hypocrisies and envyings and all evil speakings, 2 as newborn babes desire earnestly the pure mental milk of the word, that by it ye may grow up to salvation, 3 if indeed ye have tasted that the Lord is good.

4 To whom coming, a living stone, cast away indeed as worthless by men, but with God chosen, precious, 5 yourselves also, as living stones, are being built up a spiritual house, a holy priesthood, to offer spiritual sacrifices acceptable to God by Jesus Christ. 6 Because it is contained in the scripture: Behold, I lay in Zion a corner stone, elect, precious: and he that believes on him shall not be put to shame. 7 To you therefore who believe is the preciousness; but to the disobedient, the stone which the builders cast away as worthless, this is become head of the corner, 8 and a stone of stumbling and rock of offence; who stumble at the word, being disobedient to which also they have been appointed. 9 But ye are a chosen race, a kingly priesthood, a holy nation, a people for a possession, that ye might set forth the excellencies of him who has called you out of darkness to his wonderful light; 10 who once were not a people, but now God's people; who were not enjoying mercy, but now have found mercy. 11 Beloved, I exhort you, as strangers and sojourners, to abstain from fleshly lusts, which war against the soul; 12 having your conversation honest among the Gentiles, that as to that in which they speak against you as evildoers, they may through your good works, themselves witnessing them, glorify God in theday of visitation.

13 Be in subjection therefore to every human institution for the Lord's sake; whether to the king as supreme, 14 or to rulers as sent by him, for vengeance on evildoers, and praise to them that do well. 15 Because so is the will of God, that by well-doing ye put to silence the ignorance of senseless men; 16 as free, and not as having liberty as a cloak of malice, but as God's bondmen. 17 Shew honour to all, love the brotherhood, fear God, honour the king. 18 Servants, be subject with all fear to your masters, not only to the good and gentle, but also to the ill-tempered. 19 For this is acceptable, if one, for conscience sake towards God, endure griefs, suffering unjustly. 20 For what glory is it, if sinning and being buffeted ye shall bear it? but if, doing good and suffering, ye shall bear it, this is acceptable with God. 21 For to this have ye been called; for Christ also has suffered for you, leaving you a model that ye should follow in his steps: 22 who did no sin, neither was guile found in his mouth; 23 who, when reviled, reviled not again; when suffering, threatened not; but gave himself over into the hands of him who judges righteously; 24 who himself bore our sins in his body on the tree, in order that, being dead to sins, we may live to righteousness: by whose stripes ye have been healed. 25 For ye were going astray as sheep, but have now returned to the shepherd and overseer of your souls.

1 Peter 4

1 Christ, then, having suffered for us in the flesh, do ye also arm yourselves with the same mind; for he that has suffered in the flesh has done with sin, 2 no longer to live the rest of his time in the flesh to men's lusts, but to God's will. 3 For the time past is sufficient for us to have wrought the will of the Gentiles, walking in lasciviousness, lusts, wine-drinking, revels, drinkings, and unhallowed idolatries.

4 Wherein they think it strange that ye run not with them to the same sink of corruption, speaking injuriously of you; 5 who shall render account to him who is ready to judge the living and the dead. 6 For to this end were the glad tidings preached to the dead also, that they might be judged, as regards men, after the flesh, but live, as regards God, after the Spirit.

7 But the end of all things is drawn nigh: be sober therefore, and be watchful unto prayers; 8 but before all things having fervent love among yourselves, because love covers a multitude of sins; 9 hospitable one to another, without murmuring; 10 each according as he has received a gift, ministering it to one another, as good stewards of the various grace of God. 11 If any one speak--as oracles of God; if any one minister--as of strength which God supplies; that God in all things may be glorified through Jesus Christ, to whom is the glory and the might for the ages of ages. Amen.

12 Beloved, take not as strange the fire of persecution which has taken place amongst you for your trial, as if a strange thing was happening to you; 13 but as ye have share in the sufferings of Christ, rejoice, that in the revelation of his glory also ye may rejoice with exultation. 14 If ye are reproached in the name of Christ, blessed are ye; for the Spirit of glory and the Spirit of God rests upon you: on their part he is blasphemed, but on your part he is glorified. 15 Let none of you suffer indeed as murderer, or thief, or evildoer, or as overseer of other people's matters; 16 but if as a christian, let him not be ashamed, but glorify God in this name. 17 For the time of having the judgment begin from the house of God is come; but if first from us, what shall be the end of those who obey not the glad tidings of God? 18 And if the righteous is difficultly saved, where shall the impious and the sinner appear? 19 Wherefore also let them who suffer according to the will of God commit their souls in well-doing to a faithful Creator.

1 Peter 5

1 The elders which are among you I exhort, who am their fellow-elder and witness of the sufferings of the Christ, who also am partaker of the glory about to be revealed: 2 shepherd the flock of God which is among you, exercising oversight, not by necessity, but willingly; not for base gain, but readily; 3 not as lording it over your possessions, but being models for the flock. 4 And when the chief shepherd is manifested ye shall receive the unfading crown of glory.

5 Likewise ye younger, be subject to the elder, and all of you bind on humility towards one another; for God sets himself against the proud, but to the humble gives grace. 6 Humble yourselves therefore under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt you in the due time; 7 having cast all your care upon him, for he cares about you.

8 Be vigilant, watch. Your adversary the devil as a roaring lion walks about seeking whom he may devour. 9 Whom resist, stedfast in faith, knowing that the selfsame sufferings are accomplished in your brotherhood which is in the world.

10 But the God of all grace who has called you to his eternal glory in Christ Jesus, when ye have suffered for a little while, himself shall make perfect, stablish, strengthen, ground: 11 to him be the glory and the might for the ages of the ages. Amen. 12 By Silvanus, the faithful brother, as I suppose, I have written to you briefly; exhorting and testifying that this is the true grace of God in which ye stand. 13 She that is elected with you in Babylon salutes you, and Marcus my son. 14 Salute one another with a kiss of love. Peace be with you all who are in Christ.

2 Peter 1

1 Simon Peter, bondman and apostle of Jesus Christ, to them that have received like precious faith with us through the righteousness of our God and Saviour Jesus Christ: 2 Grace and peace be multiplied to you in the knowledge of God and of Jesus our Lord. 3 As his divine power has given to us all things which relate to life and godliness, through the knowledge of him that has called us by glory and virtue, 4 through which he has given to us the greatest and precious promises, that through these ye may become partakers of the divine nature, having escaped the corruption that is in the world through lust.

5 But for this very reason also, using therewith all diligence, in your faith have also virtue, in virtue knowledge, 6 in knowledge temperance, in temperance endurance, in endurance godliness, 7 in godliness brotherly love, in brotherly love love: 8 for these things existing and abounding in you make you to be neither idle nor unfruitful as regards the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ; 9 for he with whom these things are not present is blind, short-sighted, and has forgotten the purging of his former sins. 10 Wherefore the rather, brethren, use diligence to make your calling and election sure, for doing these things ye will never fall; 11 for thus shall the entrance into the everlasting kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ be richly furnished unto you.

12 Wherefore I will be careful to put you always in mind of these things, although knowing them and established in the present truth. 13 But I account it right, as long as I am in this tabernacle, to stir you up by putting you in remembrance, 14 knowing that the putting off of my tabernacle is speedily to take place, as also our Lord Jesus Christ has manifested to me; 15 but I will use diligence, that after my departure ye should have also, at any time, in your power to call to mind these things.

16 For we have not made known to you the power and coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, following cleverly imagined fables, but having been eyewitnesses of his majesty. 17 For he received from God the Father honour and glory, such a voice being uttered to him by the excellent glory: This is my beloved Son, in whom I have found my delight; 18 and this voice we heard uttered from heaven, being with him on the holy mountain.

19 And we have the prophetic word made surer, to which ye do well taking heed (as to a lamp shining in an obscure place) until the day dawn and the morning star arise in your hearts; 20 knowing this first, that the scope of no prophecy of scripture is had from its own particular interpretation, 21 for prophecy was not ever uttered by the will of man, but holy men of God spake under the power of the Holy Spirit.

2 Peter 3

1 This, a second letter, beloved, I already write to you, in both which I stir up, in the way of putting you in remembrance, your pure mind, 2 to be mindful of the words spoken before by the holy prophets, and of the commandment of the Lord and Saviour by your apostles;

3 knowing this first, that there shall come at the close of the days mockers with mocking, walking according to their own lusts, 4 and saying, Where is the promise of his coming? for from the time the fathers fell asleep all things remain thus from the beginning of the creation. 5 For this is hidden from them through their own wilfulness, that heavens were of old, and an earth, having its subsistence out of water and in water, by the word of God, 6 through which waters the then world, deluged with water, perished. 7 But the present heavens and the earth by his word are laid up in store, kept for fire unto a day of judgment and destruction of ungodly men.

8 But let not this one thing be hidden from you, beloved, that one day with the Lord is as a thousand years, and a thousand years as one day.

9 The Lord does not delay his promise, as some account of delay, but is longsuffering towards you, not willing that any should perish, but that all should come to repentance. 10 But the day of the Lord will come as a thief, in which the heavens will pass away with a rushing noise, and the elements, burning with heat, shall be dissolved, and the earth and the works in it shall be burnt up.

11 All these things then being to be dissolved, what ought ye to be in holy conversation and godliness, 12 waiting for and hastening the coming of the day of God, by reason of which the heavens, being on fire, shall be dissolved, and the elements, burning with heat, shall melt? 13 But, according to his promise, we wait for new heavens and a new earth, wherein dwells righteousness. 14 Wherefore, beloved, as ye wait for these things, be diligent to be found of him in peace, without spot and blameless; 15 and account the longsuffering of our Lord to be salvation; according as our beloved brother Paul also has written to you according to the wisdom given to him, 16 as also in all his epistles, speaking in them of these things; among which some things are hard to be understood, which the untaught and ill-established wrest, as also the other scriptures, to their own destruction. 17 Ye therefore, beloved, knowing these things before, take care lest, being led away along with the error of the wicked, ye should fall from your own stedfastness: 18 but grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ. To him be glory both now and to the day of eternity. Amen.

1 John 1

1 That which was from the beginning, that which we have heard, which we have seen with our eyes; that which we contemplated, and our hands handled, concerning the word of life; 2 (and the life has been manifested, and we have seen, and bear witness, and report to you the eternal life, which was with the Father, and has been manifested to us:) 3 that which we have seen and heard we report to you, that ye also may have fellowship with us; and our fellowship is indeed with the Father, and with his Son Jesus Christ. 4 And these things write we to you that your joy may be full.

5 And this is the message which we have heard from him, and declare to you, that God is light, and in him is no darkness at all. 6 If we say that we have fellowship with him, and walk in darkness, we lie, and do not practise the truth. 7 But if we walk in the light as he is in the light, we have fellowship with one another, and the blood of Jesus Christ his Son cleanses us from all sin.

8 If we say that we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and the truth is not in us. 9 If we confess our sins, he is faithful and righteous to forgive us our sins, and cleanse us from all unrighteousness. 10 If we say that we have not sinned, we make him a liar, and his word is not in us.

1 John 2

1 My children, these things I write to you in order that ye may not sin; and if any one sin, we have a patron with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous; 2 and he is the propitiation for our sins; but not for ours alone, but also for the whole world.

3 And hereby we know that we know him, if we keep his commandments. 4 He that says, I know him, and does not keep his commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in him; 5 but whoever keeps his word, in him verily the love of God is perfected. Hereby we know that we are in him. 6 He that says he abides in him ought, even as he walked, himself also so to walk.

7 Beloved, I write no new commandment to you, but an old commandment, which ye have had from the beginning. The old commandment is the word which ye heard. 8 Again, I write a new commandment to you, which thing is true in him and in you, because the darkness is passing and the true light already shines. 9 He who says he is in the light, and hates his brother, is in the darkness until now. 10 He that loves his brother abides in light, and there is no occasion of stumbling in him. 11 But he that hates his brother is in the darkness, and walks in the darkness, and knows not where he goes, because the darkness has blinded his eyes.

12 I write to you, children, because your sins are forgiven you for his name's sake. 13 I write to you, fathers, because ye have known him that is from the beginning. I write to you, young men, because ye have overcome the wicked one. I write to you, little children, because ye have known the Father. 14 I have written to you, fathers, because ye have known him that is from the beginning. I have written to you, young men, because ye are strong, and the word of God abides in you, and ye have overcome the wicked one. 15 Love not the world, nor the things in the world. If any one love the world, the love of the Father is not in him; 16 because all that is in the world, the lust of the flesh, and the lust of the eyes, and the pride of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world. 17 And the world is passing, and its lust, but he that does the will of God abides for eternity.

18 Little children, it is the last hour, and, according as ye have heard that antichrist comes, even now there have come many antichrists, whence we know that it is the last hour. 19 They went out from among us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would have surely remained with us, but that they might be made manifest that none are of us.

20 And ye have the unction from the holy one, and ye know all things. 21 I have not written to you because ye do not know the truth, but because ye know it, and that no lie is of the truth. 22 Who is the liar but he who denies that Jesus is the Christ? He is the antichrist who denies the Father and the Son. 23 Whoever denies the Son has not the Father either; he who confesses the Son has the Father also. 24 As for you let that which ye have heard from the beginning abide in you: if what ye have heard from the beginning abides in you, ye also shall abide in the Son and in the Father. 25 And this is the promise which he has promised us, life eternal. 26 These things have I written to you concerning those who lead you astray: 27 and yourselves, the unction which ye have received from him abides in you, and ye have not need that any one should teach you; but as the same unction teaches you as to all things, and is true and is not a lie, and even as it has taught you, ye shall abide in him.

28 And now, children, abide in him, that if he be manifested we may have boldness, and not be put to shame from before him at his coming. 29 If ye know that he is righteous, know that every one who practises righteousness is begotten of him.

1 John 3

1 See what love the Father has given to us, that we should be called the children of God. For this reason the world knows us not, because it knew him not. 2 Beloved, now are we children of God, and what we shall be has not yet been manifested; we know that if it is manifested we shall be like him, for we shall see him as he is. 3 And every one that has this hope in him purifies himself, even as he is pure.

4 Every one that practises sin practises also lawlessness; and sin is lawlessness. 5 And ye know that he has been manifested that he might take away our sins; and in him sin is not. 6 Whoever abides in him, does not sin: whoever sins, has not seen him or known him. 7 Children, let no man lead you astray; he that practises righteousness is righteous, even as he is righteous. 8 He that practises sin is of the devil; for from the beginning the devil sins. To this end the Son of God has been manifested, that he might undo the works of the devil. 9 Whoever has been begotten of God does not practise sin, because his seed abides in him, and he cannot sin, because he has been begotten of God. 10 In this are manifest the children of God and the children of the devil. Whoever does not practise righteousness is not of God, and he who does not love his brother.

11 For this is the message which ye have heard from the beginning, that we should love one another: 12 not as Cain was of the wicked one, and slew his brother; and on account of what slew he him? because his works were wicked, and those of his brother righteous. 13 Do not wonder, brethren, if the world hate you.

14 We know that we have passed from death to life, because we love the brethren. He who does not love his brother abides in death. 15 Every one that hates his brother is a murderer, and ye know that no murderer has eternal life abiding in him. 16 Hereby we have known love, because he has laid down his life for us; and we ought for the brethren to lay down our lives. 17 But whoso may have the world's substance, and see his brother having need, and shut up his bowels from him, how abides the love of God in him? 18 Children, let us not love with word, nor with tongue, but in deed and in truth. 19 And hereby we shall know that we are of the truth, and shall persuade our hearts before him--

20 that if our heart condemn us, God is greater than our heart and knows all things. 21 Beloved, if our heart condemn us not, we have boldness towards God, 22 and whatsoever we ask we receive from him, because we keep his commandments, and practise the things which are pleasing in his sight.

23 And this is his commandment, that we believe on the name of his Son Jesus Christ, and that we love one another, even as he has given us commandment. 24 And he that keeps his commandments abides in him, and he in him. And hereby we know that he abides in us, by the Spirit which he has given to us.

1 John 4

1 Beloved, believe not every spirit, but prove the spirits, if they are of God; because many false prophets are gone out into the world. 2 Hereby ye know the Spirit of God: every spirit which confesses Jesus Christ come in flesh is of God; 3 and every spirit which does not confess Jesus Christ come in flesh is not of God: and this is that power of the antichrist, of which ye have heard that it comes, and now it is already in the world.

4 Ye are of God, children, and have overcome them, because greater is he that is in you than he that is in the world. 5 They are of the world; for this reason they speak as of the world, and the world hears them. 6 We are of God; he that knows God hears us; he who is not of God does not hear us. From this we know the spirit of truth and the spirit of error.

7 Beloved, let us love one another; because love is of God, and every one that loves has been begotten of God, and knows God. 8 He that loves not has not known God; for God is love. 9 Herein as to us has been manifested the love of God, that God has sent his only begotten Son into the world, that we might live through him. 10 Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and sent his Son a propitiation for our sins. 11 Beloved, if God has so loved us, we also ought to love one another. 12 No one has seen God at any time: if we love one another, God abides in us, and his love is perfected in us. 13 Hereby we know that we abide in him and he in us, that he has given to us of his Spirit.

14 And we have seen, and testify, that the Father has sent the Son as Saviour of the world. 15 Whosoever shall confess that Jesus is the Son of God, God abides in him, and he in God. 16 And we have known and have believed the love which God has to us. God is love, and he that abides in love abides in God, and God in him.

17 Herein has love been perfected with us that we may have boldness in the day of judgment, that even as he is, we also are in this world. 18 There is no fear in love, but perfect love casts out fear; for fear has torment, and he that fears has not been made perfect in love. 19 We love because he has first loved us. 20 If any one say, I love God, and hate his brother, he is a liar: for he that loves not his brother whom he has seen, how can he love God whom he has not seen? 21 And this commandment have we from him, That he that loves God love also his brother.

1 John 5

1 Every one that believes that Jesus is the Christ is begotten of God; and every one that loves him that has begotten loves also him that is begotten of him. 2 Hereby know we that we love the children of God, when we love God and keep his commandments. 3 For this is the love of God, that we keep his commandments; and his commandments are not grievous. 4 For all that has been begotten of God gets the victory over the world; and this is the victory which has gotten the victory over the world, our faith. 5 Who is he that gets the victory over the world, but he that believes that Jesus is the Son of God?

6 This is he that came by water and blood, Jesus the Christ; not by water only, but by water and blood. And it is the Spirit that bears witness, for the Spirit is the truth. 7 For they that bear witness are three: 8 the Spirit, and the water, and the blood; and the three agree in one. 9 If we receive the witness of men, the witness of God is greater. For this is the witness of God which he has witnessed concerning his Son.

10 He that believes on the Son of God has the witness in himself; he that does not believe God has made him a liar, because he has not believed in the witness which God has witnessed concerning his Son. 11 And this is the witness, that God has given to us eternal life; and this life is in his Son. 12 He that has the Son has life: he that has not the Son of God has not life. 13 These things have I written to you that ye may know that ye have eternal life who believe on the name of the Son of God.

14 And this is the boldness which we have towards him, that if we ask him anything according to his will he hears us. 15 And if we know that he hears us, whatsoever we ask, we know that we have the petitions which we have asked of him. 16 If any one see his brother sinning a sin not unto death, he shall ask, and he shall give him life, for those that do not sin unto death. There is a sin to death: I do not say of that that he should make a request. 17 Every unrighteousness is sin; and there is a sin not to death.

18 We know that every one begotten of God does not sin, but he that has been begotten of God keeps himself, and the wicked one does not touch him. 19 We know that we are of God, and the whole world lies in the wicked one. 20 And we know that the Son of God has come, and has given us an understanding that we should know him that is true; and we are in him that is true, in his Son Jesus Christ. He is the true God and eternal life. 21 Children, keep yourselves from idols.

2 John 1

1 The elder to the elect lady and her children, whom I love in truth, and not I only but also all who have known the truth, 2 for the truth's sake which abides in us and shall be with us to eternity. 3 Grace shall be with you, mercy, peace from God the Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ, the Son of the Father, in truth and love. 4 I rejoiced greatly that I have found of thy children walking in truth, as we have received commandment from the Father.

5 And now I beseech thee, lady, not as writing to thee a new commandment, but that which we have had from the beginning, that we should love one another. 6 And this is love, that we should walk according to his commandments. This is the commandment, according as ye have heard from the beginning, that ye might walk in it.

7 For many deceivers have gone out into the world, they who do not confess Jesus Christ coming in flesh--this is the deceiver and the antichrist. 8 See to yourselves, that we may not lose what we have wrought, but may receive full wages. 9 Whosoever goes forward and abides not in the doctrine of the Christ has not God. He that abides in the doctrine, he has both the Father and the Son.

10 If any one come to you and bring not this doctrine, do not receive him into the house, and greet him not; 11 for he who greets him partakes in his wicked works.

12 Having many things to write to you, I would not with paper and ink; but hope to come to you, and to speak mouth to mouth, that our joy may be full. 13 The children of thine elect sister greet thee.

3 John 1

1 The elder to the beloved Gaius, whom I love in truth. 2 Beloved, I desire that in all things thou shouldest prosper and be in health, even as thy soul prospers.

3 For I rejoiced exceedingly when the brethren came and bore testimony to thy holding fast the truth, even as thou walkest in truth. 4 I have no greater joy than these things that I hear of my children walking in the truth. 5 Beloved, thou doest faithfully in whatever thou mayest have wrought towards the brethren and that strangers, 6 (who have witnessed of thy love before the assembly,) in setting forward whom on their journey worthily of God, thou wilt do well; 7 for for the name have they gone forth, taking nothing of those of the nations. 8 We therefore ought to receive such, that we may be fellow-workers with the truth.

9 I wrote something to the assembly; but Diotrephes, who loves to have the first place among them, receives us not. 10 For this reason, if I come, I will bring to remembrance his works which he does, babbling against us with wicked words; and not content with these, neither does he himself receive the brethren; and those who would he prevents, and casts them out of the assembly. 11 Beloved, do not imitate what is evil, but what is good. He that does good is of God. He that does evil has not seen God.

12 Demetrius has witness borne to him by all, and by the truth itself; and we also bear witness, and thou knowest that our witness is true. 13 I had many things to write to thee, but I will not with ink and pen write to thee; 14 but I hope soon to see thee, and we will speak mouth to mouth. Peace be to thee. The friends greet thee. Greet the friends by name.

Jude 1

1 Jude, bondman of Jesus Christ, and brother of James, to the called ones beloved in God the Father and preserved in Jesus Christ: 2 Mercy to you, and peace, and love be multiplied.

3 Beloved, using all diligence to write to you of our common salvation, I have been obliged to write to you exhorting you to contend earnestly for the faith once delivered to the saints. 4 For certain men have got in unnoticed, they who of old were marked out beforehand to this sentence, ungodly persons, turning the grace of our God into dissoluteness, and denying our only Master and Lord Jesus Christ. 5 But I would put you in remembrance, you who once knew all things, that the Lord, having saved a people out of the land of Egypt, in the second place destroyed those who had not believed. 6 And angels who had not kept their own original state, but had abandoned their own dwelling, he keeps in eternal chains under gloomy darkness, to the judgment of the great day; 7 as Sodom and Gomorrha, and the cities around them, committing greedily fornication, in like manner with them, and going after other flesh, lie there as an example, undergoing the judgment of eternal fire.

8 Yet in like manner these dreamers also defile the flesh, and despise lordship, and speak railingly against dignities. 9 But Michael the archangel, when disputing with the devil he reasoned about the body of Moses, did not dare to bring a railing judgment against him, but said, The Lord rebuke thee. 10 But these, whatever things they know not, they speak railingly against; but what even, as the irrational animals, they understand by mere nature, in these things they corrupt themselves. 11 Woe to them! because they have gone in the way of Cain, and given themselves up to the error of Balaam for reward, and perished in the gainsaying of Core. 12 These are spots in your love-feasts, feasting together with you without fear, pasturing themselves; clouds without water, carried along by the winds; autumnal trees, without fruit, twice dead, rooted up; 13 raging waves of the sea, foaming out their own shames; wandering stars, to whom has been reserved the gloom of darkness for eternity. 14 And Enoch, the seventh from Adam, prophesied also as to these, saying, Behold, the Lord has come amidst his holy myriads,

15 to execute judgment against all; and to convict all the ungodly of them of all their works of ungodliness, which they have wrought ungodlily, and of all the hard things which ungodly sinners have spoken against him. 16 These are murmurers, complainers, walking after their lusts; and their mouth speaks swelling words, admiring persons for the sake of profit. 17 But ye, beloved, remember the words spoken before by the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ, 18 that they said to you, that at the end of the time there should be mockers, walking after their own lusts of ungodlinesses. 19 These are they who set themselves apart, natural men, not having the Spirit. 20 But ye, beloved, building yourselves up on your most holy faith, praying in the Holy Spirit, 21 keep yourselves in the love of God, awaiting the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ unto eternal life. 22 And of some have compassion, making a difference, 23 but others save with fear, snatching them out of the fire; hating even the garment spotted by the flesh. 24 But to him that is able to keep you without stumbling, and to set you with exultation blameless before his glory, 25 to the only God our Saviour, through Jesus Christ our Lord, be glory, majesty, might, and authority, from before the whole age, and now, and to all the ages. Amen.

Revelation 1

1 Revelation of Jesus Christ, which God gave to him, to shew to his bondmen what must shortly take place; and he signified it, sending by his angel, to his bondman John, 2 who testified the word of God, and the testimony of Jesus Christ, all things that he saw.

3 Blessed is he that reads, and they that hear the words of the prophecy, and keep the things written in it; for the time is near. 4 John to the seven assemblies which are in Asia: Grace to you and peace from him who is, and who was, and who is to come; and from the seven Spirits which are before his throne; 5 and from Jesus Christ, the faithful witness, the firstborn from the dead, and the prince of the kings of the earth. To him who loves us, and has washed us from our sins in his blood, 6 and made us a kingdom, priests to his God and Father: to him be the glory and the might to the ages of ages. Amen. 7 Behold, he comes with the clouds, and every eye shall see him, and they which have pierced him, and all the tribes of the land shall wail because of him. Yea. Amen. 8 I am the Alpha and the Omega, saith the Lord God, he who is, and who was, and who is to come, the Almighty.

9 I John, your brother and fellow-partaker in the tribulation and kingdom and patience, in Jesus, was in the island called Patmos, for the word of God, and for the testimony of Jesus. 10 I became in the Spirit on the Lord's day, and I heard behind me a great voice as of a trumpet, 11 saying, What thou seest write in a book, and send to the seven assemblies: to Ephesus, and to Smyrna, and to Pergamos, and to Thyatira, and to Sardis, and to Philadelphia, and to Laodicea. 12 And I turned back to see the voice which spoke with me; and having turned, I saw seven golden lamps, 13 and in the midst of the seven lamps one like the Son of man, clothed with a garment reaching to the feet, and girt about at the breasts with a golden girdle: 14 his head and hair white like white wool, as snow; and his eyes as a flame of fire; 15 and his feet like fine brass, as burning in a furnace; and his voice as the voice of many waters; 16 and having in his right hand seven stars; and out of his mouth a sharp two-edged sword going forth; and his countenance as the sun shines in its power. 17 And when I saw him I fell at his feet as dead; and he laid his right hand upon me, saying, Fear not; I am the first and the last, 18 and the living one: and I became dead, and behold, I am living to the ages of ages, and have the keys of death and of hades. 19 Write therefore what thou hast seen, and the things that are, and the things that are about to be after these. 20 The mystery of the seven stars which thou hast seen on my right hand, and the seven golden lamps. --The seven stars are angels of the seven assemblies; and the seven lamps are seven assemblies.

Revelation 2

1 To the angel of the assembly in Ephesus write: These things says he that holds the seven stars in his right hand, who walks in the midst of the seven golden lamps: 2 I know thy works and thy labour, and thine endurance, and that thou canst not bear evil men; and thou hast tried them who say that themselves are apostles and are not, and hast found them liars; 3 and endurest, and hast borne for my name's sake, and hast not wearied: 4 but I have against thee, that thou hast left thy first love. 5 Remember therefore whence thou art fallen, and repent, and do the first works: but if not, I am coming to thee, and I will remove thy lamp out of its place, except thou shalt repent. 6 But this thou hast, that thou hatest the works of the Nicolaitanes, which I also hate. 7 He that has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies. To him that overcomes, I will give to him to eat of the tree of life which is in the paradise of God.

8 And to the angel of the assembly in Smyrna write: These things says the first and the last, who became dead, and lived: 9 I know thy tribulation and thy poverty; but thou art rich; and the railing of those who say that they themselves are Jews, and are not, but a synagogue of Satan. 10 Fear nothing of what thou art about to suffer. Behold, the devil is about to cast of you into prison, that ye may be tried; and ye shall have tribulation ten days. Be thou faithful unto death, and I will give to thee the crown of life. 11 He that has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies. He that overcomes shall in no wise be injured of the second death.

12 And to the angel of the assembly in Pergamos write: These things says he that has the sharp two-edged sword: 13 I know where thou dwellest, where the throne of Satan is; and thou holdest fast my name, and hast not denied my faith, even in the days in which Antipas my faithful witness was, who was slain among you, where Satan dwells. 14 But I have a few things against thee: that thou hast there those who hold the doctrine of Balaam, who taught Balak to cast a snare before the sons of Israel, to eat of idol sacrifices and commit fornication. 15 So thou also hast those who hold the doctrine of Nicolaitanes in like manner. 16 Repent therefore: but if not, I come to thee quickly, and I will make war with them with the sword of my mouth. 17 He that has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies. To him that overcomes, to him will I give of the hidden manna; and I will give to him a white stone, and on the stone a new name written, which no one knows but he that receives it.

18 And to the angel of the assembly in Thyatira write: These things says the Son of God, he that has his eyes as a flame of fire, and his feet are like fine brass: 19 I know thy works, and love, and faith, and service, and thine endurance, and thy last works to be more than the first. 20 But I have against thee that thou permittest the woman Jezebel, she who calls herself prophetess, and she teaches and leads astray my servants to commit fornication and eat of idol sacrifices. 21 And I gave her time that she should repent, and she will not repent of her fornication. 22 Behold, I cast her into a bed, and those that commit adultery with her into great tribulation, unless they repent of her works, 23 and her children will I kill with death; and all the assemblies shall know that I am he that searches the reins and the hearts; and I will give to you each according to your works. 24 But to you I say, the rest who are in Thyatira, as many as have not this doctrine, who have not known the depths of Satan, as they say, I do not cast upon you any other burden; 25 but what ye have hold fast till I shall come. 26 And he that overcomes, and he that keeps unto the end my works, to him will I give authority over the nations, 27 and he shall shepherd them with an iron rod; as vessels of pottery are they broken in pieces, as I also have received from my Father; 28 and I will give to him the morning star. 29 He that has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies.

Revelation 3

1 And to the angel of the assembly in Sardis write: These things saith he that has the seven Spirits of God, and the seven stars: I know thy works, that thou hast a name that thou livest, and art dead. 2 Be watchful, and strengthen the things that remain, which are about to die, for I have not found thy works complete before my God. 3 Remember therefore how thou hast received and heard, and keep it and repent. If therefore thou shalt not watch, I will come upon thee as a thief, and thou shalt not know at what hour I shall come upon thee. 4 But thou hast a few names in Sardis which have not defiled their garments, and they shall walk with me in white, because they are worthy. 5 He that overcomes, he shall be clothed in white garments, and I will not blot his name out of the book of life, and will confess his name before my Father and before his angels. 6 He that has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies.

7 And to the angel of the assembly in Philadelphia write: These things saith the holy, the true; he that has the key of David, he who opens and no one shall shut, and shuts and no one shall open: 8 I know thy works: behold, I have set before thee an opened door, which no one can shut, because thou hast a little power, and hast kept my word, and hast not denied my name. 9 Behold, I make them of the synagogue of Satan who say that they are Jews, and are not, but lie; behold, I will cause that they shall come and shall do homage before thy feet, and shall know that I have loved thee. 10 Because thou hast kept the word of my patience, I also will keep thee out of the hour of trial, which is about to come upon the whole habitable world, to try them that dwell upon the earth. 11 I come quickly: hold fast what thou hast, that no one take thy crown. 12 He that overcomes, him will I make a pillar in the temple of my God, and he shall go no more at all out; and I will write upon him the name of my God, and the name of the city of my God, the new Jerusalem, which comes down out of heaven, from my God, and my new name. 13 He that has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies.

14 And to the angel of the assembly in Laodicea write: These things says the Amen, the faithful and true witness, the beginning of the creation of God: 15 I know thy works, that thou art neither cold nor hot; I would thou wert cold or hot. 16 Thus because thou art lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I am about to spue thee out of my mouth. 17 Because thou sayest, I am rich, and am grown rich, and have need of nothing, and knowest not that thou art the wretched and the miserable, and poor, and blind, and naked; 18 I counsel thee to buy of me gold purified by fire, that thou mayest be rich; and white garments, that thou mayest be clothed, and that the shame of thy nakedness may not be made manifest; and eye-salve to anoint thine eyes, that thou mayest see. 19 I rebuke and discipline as many as I love; be zealous therefore and repent. 20 Behold, I stand at the door and am knocking; if any one hear my voice and open the door, I will come in unto him and sup with him, and he with me. 21 He that overcomes, to him will I give to sit with me in my throne; as I also have overcome, and have sat down with my Father in his throne. 22 He that has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies.

Revelation 6

1 And I saw when the Lamb opened one of the seven seals, and I heard one of the four living creatures saying, as a voice of thunder, Come and see. 2 And I saw: and behold, a white horse, and he that sat upon it having a bow; and a crown was given to him, and he went forth conquering and that he might conquer.

3 And when it opened the second seal, I heard the second living creature saying, Come and see. 4 And another, a red horse, went forth; and to him that sat upon it, to him it was given to take peace from the earth, and that they should slay one another; and there was given to him a great sword. 5 And when it opened the third seal, I heard the third living creature saying, Come and see. And I saw: and behold, a black horse, and he that sat upon it having a balance in his hand. 6 And I heard as a voice in the midst of the four living creatures saying, A choenix of wheat for a denarius, and three choenixes of barley for a denarius: and do not injure the oil and the wine. 7 And when it opened the fourth seal, I heard the voice of the fourth living creature saying, Come and see. 8 And I saw: and behold, a pale horse, and he that sat upon it, his name was Death, and hades followed with him; and authority was given to him over the fourth of the earth to slay with sword, and with hunger, and with death, and by the beasts of the earth.

9 And when it opened the fifth seal, I saw underneath the altar the souls of them that had been slain for the word of God, and for the testimony which they held; 10 and they cried with a loud voice, saying, How long, O sovereign Ruler, holy and true, dost thou not judge and avenge our blood on them that dwell upon the earth? 11 And there was given to them, to each one a white robe; and it was said to them that they should rest yet a little while, until both their fellow-bondmen and their brethren, who were about to be killed as they, should be fulfilled. 12 And I saw when it opened the sixth seal, and there was a great earthquake; and the sun became black as hair sackcloth, and the whole moon became as blood, 13 and the stars of heaven fell upon the earth, as a fig tree, shaken by a great wind, casts its unseasonable figs. 14 And the heaven was removed as a book rolled up, and every mountain and island were removed out of their places. 15 And the kings of the earth, and the great, and the chiliarchs, and the rich, and the strong, and every bondman and freeman, hid themselves in the caves and in the rocks of the mountains; 16 and they say to the mountains and to the rocks, Fall on us, and have us hidden from the face of him that sits upon the throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb; 17 because the great day of his wrath is come, and who is able to stand?

Revelation 11

1 And there was given to me a reed like a staff, saying, Rise, and measure the temple of God, and the altar, and them that worship in it. 2 And the court which is without the temple cast out, and measure it not; because it has been given up to the nations, and the holy city shall they tread under foot forty-two months.

3 And I will give power to my two witnesses, and they shall prophesy a thousand two hundred and sixty days, clothed in sackcloth. 4 These are the two olive trees and the two lamps which stand before the Lord of the earth; 5 and if any one wills to injure them, fire goes out of their mouth, and devours their enemies. And if any one wills to injure them, thus must he be killed. 6 These have power to shut the heaven that no rain may fall during the days of their prophecy; and they have power over the waters to turn them into blood, and to smite the earth as often as they will with every plague. 7 And when they shall have completed their testimony, the beast who comes up out of the abyss shall make war with them, and shall conquer them, and shall kill them: 8 and their body shall be on the street of the great city, which is called spiritually Sodom and Egypt, where also their Lord was crucified. 9 And men of the peoples and tribes and tongues and nations see their body three days and a half, and they do not suffer their bodies to be put into a sepulchre. 10 And they that dwell upon the earth rejoice over them, and are full of delight, and shall send gifts one to another, because these, the two prophets, tormented them that dwell upon the earth. 11 And after the three days and a half the spirit of life from God came into them, and they stood upon their feet; and great fear fell upon those beholding them. 12 And I heard a great voice out of the heaven saying to them, Come up here; and they went up to the heaven in the cloud, and their enemies beheld them. 13 And in that hour there was a great earthquake, and the tenth of the city fell, and seven thousand names of men were slain in the earthquake. And the remnant were filled with fear, and gave glory to the God of the heaven.

14 The second woe has passed; behold, the third woe comes quickly. 15 And the seventh angel sounded his trumpet: and there were great voices in the heaven, saying, The kingdom of the world of our Lord and of his Christ is come, and he shall reign to the ages of ages. 16 And the twenty-four elders, who sit on their thrones before God, fell upon their faces, and worshipped God, 17 saying, We give thee thanks, Lord God Almighty, He who is, and who was, that thou hast taken thy great power and hast reigned. 18 And the nations have been full of wrath, and thy wrath is come, and the time of the dead to be judged, and to give the recompense to thy servants the prophets, and to the saints, and to those who fear thy name, small and great; and to destroy those that destroy the earth. 19 And the temple of God in the heaven was opened, and the ark of his covenant was seen in his temple: and there were lightnings, and voices, and thunders, and an earthquake, and great hail.

Revelation 14

1 And I saw, and behold, the Lamb standing upon mount Zion, and with him a hundred and forty-four thousand, having his name and the name of his Father written upon their foreheads. 2 And I heard a voice out of the heaven as a voice of many waters, and as a voice of great thunder. And the voice which I heard was as of harp-singers harping with their harps; 3 and they sing a new song before the throne, and before the four living creatures and the elders. And no one could learn that song save the hundred and forty-four thousand who were bought from the earth. 4 These are they who have not been defiled with women, for they are virgins: these are they who follow the Lamb wheresoever it goes. These have been bought from men as first-fruits to God and to the Lamb: 5 and in their mouths was no lie found; for they are blameless.

6 And I saw another angel flying in mid-heaven, having the everlasting glad tidings to announce to those settled on the earth, and to every nation and tribe and tongue and people, 7 saying with a loud voice, Fear God and give him glory, for the hour of his judgment has come; and do homage to him who has made the heaven and the earth and the sea and fountains of waters. 8 And another, a second, angel followed, saying, Great Babylon has fallen, has fallen, which of the wine of the fury of her fornication has made all nations drink. 9 And another, a third, angel followed them, saying with a loud voice, If any one do homage to the beast and its image, and receive a mark upon his forehead or upon his hand, 10 he also shall drink of the wine of the fury of God prepared unmixed in the cup of his wrath, and he shall be tormented in fire and brimstone before the holy angels and before the Lamb. 11 And the smoke of their torment goes up to ages of ages, and they have no respite day and night who do homage to the beast and to its image, and if any one receive the mark of its name. 12 Here is the endurance of the saints, who keep the commandments of God and the faith of Jesus.

13 And I heard a voice out of the heaven saying, Write, Blessed the dead who die in the Lord from henceforth. Yea, saith the Spirit, that they may rest from their labours; for their works follow with them. 14 And I saw, and behold, a white cloud, and on the cloud one sitting like the Son of man, having upon his head a golden crown, and in his hand a sharp sickle. 15 And another angel came out of the temple, crying with a loud voice to him that sat on the cloud, Send thy sickle and reap; for the hour of reaping is come, for the harvest of the earth is dried. 16 And he that sat on the cloud put his sickle on the earth, and the earth was reaped. 17 And another angel came out of the temple which is in the heaven, he also having a sharp sickle. 18 And another angel came out of the altar, having power over fire, and called with a loud cry to him that had the sharp sickle, saying, Send thy sharp sickle, and gather the bunches of the vine of the earth; for her grapes are fully ripened. 19 And the angel put his sickle to the earth, and gathered the vine of the earth, and cast the bunches into the great wine-press of the fury of God; 20 and the wine-press was trodden without the city, and blood went out of the wine-press to the bits of the horses for a thousand six hundred stadia.

Revelation 16

1 And I heard a great voice out of the temple, saying to the seven angels, Go and pour out the seven bowls of the fury of God upon the earth. 2 And the first went and poured out his bowl on the earth; and there came an evil and grievous sore upon the men that had the mark of the beast, and those who worshipped its image. 3 And the second poured out his bowl on the sea; and it became blood, as of a dead man; and every living soul died in the sea. 4 And the third poured out his bowl on the rivers, and on the fountains of waters; and they became blood. 5 And I heard the angel of the waters saying, Thou art righteous, who art and wast, the holy one, that thou hast judged so; 6 for they have poured out the blood of saints and prophets, and thou hast given them blood to drink; they are worthy. 7 And I heard the altar saying, Yea, Lord God Almighty, true and righteous are thy judgments.

8 And the fourth poured out his bowl on the sun; and it was given to it to burn men with fire. 9 And the men were burnt with great heat, and blasphemed the name of God, who had authority over these plagues, and did not repent to give him glory. 10 And the fifth poured out his bowl on the throne of the beast; and its kingdom became darkened; and they gnawed their tongues with distress, 11 and blasphemed the God of the heaven for their distresses and their sores, and did not repent of their works.

12 And the sixth poured out his bowl on the great river Euphrates; and its water was dried up, that the way of the kings from the rising of the sun might be prepared. 13 And I saw out of the mouth of the dragon, and out of the mouth of the beast, and out of the mouth of the false prophet, three unclean spirits, as frogs; 14 for they are the spirits of demons, doing signs; which go out to the kings of the whole habitable world to gather them together to the war of that great day of God the Almighty. 15 (Behold, I come as a thief. Blessed is he that watches and keeps his garments, that he may not walk naked, and that they may not see his shame.) 16 And he gathered them together to the place called in Hebrew, Armagedon.

17 And the seventh poured out his bowl on the air; and there came out a great voice from the temple of the heaven, from the throne, saying, It is done. 18 And there were lightnings, and voices, and thunders; and there was a great earthquake, such as was not since men were upon the earth, such an earthquake, so great. 19 And the great city was divided into three parts; and the cities of the nations fell: and great Babylon was remembered before God to give her the cup of the wine of the fury of his wrath. 20 And every island fled, and mountains were not found; 21 and a great hail, as of a talent weight, comes down out of the heaven upon men; and men blasphemed God because of the plague of hail, for the plague of it is exceeding great.

Revelation 17

1 And one of the seven angels, which had the seven bowls, came and spoke with me, saying, Come here, I will shew thee the sentence of the great harlot who sits upon the many waters; 2 with whom the kings of the earth have committed fornication; and they that dwell on the earth have been made drunk with the wine of her fornication. 3 And he carried me away in spirit to a desert; and I saw a woman sitting upon a scarlet beast, full of names of blasphemy, having seven heads and ten horns. 4 And the woman was clothed in purple and scarlet, and had ornaments of gold and precious stones and pearls, having a golden cup in her hand full of abominations and the unclean things of her fornication; 5 and upon her forehead a name written, Mystery, great Babylon, the mother of the harlots, and of the abominations of the earth. 6 And I saw the woman drunk with the blood of the saints, and with the blood of the witnesses of Jesus. And I wondered, seeing her, with great wonder.

7 And the angel said to me, Why hast thou wondered? I will tell thee the mystery of the woman, and of the beast which carries her, which has the seven heads and the ten horns. 8 The beast which thou sawest was, and is not, and is about to come up out of the abyss and go into destruction: and they who dwell on the earth, whose names are not written from the founding of the world in the book of life, shall wonder, seeing the beast, that it was, and is not, and shall be present. 9 Here is the mind that has wisdom: The seven heads are seven mountains, whereon the woman sits. 10 And there are seven kings: five have fallen, one is, the other has not yet come; and when he comes he must remain only a little while. 11 And the beast that was and is not, he also is an eighth, and is of the seven, and goes into destruction. 12 And the ten horns which thou sawest are ten kings, which have not yet received a kingdom, but receive authority as kings one hour with the beast. 13 These have one mind, and give their power and authority to the beast.

14 These shall make war with the Lamb, and the Lamb shall overcome them; for he is Lord of lords and King of kings: and they that are with him called, and chosen, and faithful. 15 And he says to me, The waters which thou sawest, where the harlot sits, are peoples and multitudes and nations and tongues. 16 And the ten horns which thou sawest, and the beast, these shall hate the harlot, and shall make her desolate and naked, and shall eat her flesh, and shall burn her with fire; 17 for God has given to their hearts to do his mind, and to act with one mind, and to give their kingdom to the beast until the words of God shall be fulfilled. 18 And the woman which thou sawest is the great city, which has kingship over the kings of the earth.

Revelation 19

1 After these things I heard as a loud voice of a great multitude in the heaven, saying, Hallelujah: the salvation and the glory and the power of our God: 2 for true and righteous are his judgments; for he has judged the great harlot which corrupted the earth with her fornication, and has avenged the blood of his bondmen at her hand. 3 And a second time they said, Hallelujah. And her smoke goes up to the ages of ages. 4 And the twenty-four elders and the four living creatures fell down and did homage to God who sits upon the throne, saying, Amen, Hallelujah.

5 And a voice came out of the throne, saying, Praise our God, all ye his bondmen, and ye that fear him, small and great. 6 And I heard as a voice of a great crowd, and as a voice of many waters, and as a voice of strong thunders, saying, Hallelujah, for the Lord our God the Almighty has taken to himself kingly power. 7 Let us rejoice and exult, and give him glory; for the marriage of the Lamb is come, and his wife has made herself ready. 8 And it was given to her that she should be clothed in fine linen, bright and pure; for the fine linen is the righteousnesses of the saints. 9 And he says to me, Write, Blessed are they who are called to the supper of the marriage of the Lamb. And he says to me, These are the true words of God. 10 And I fell before his feet to do him homage. And he says to me, See thou do it not. I am thy fellow-bondman, and the fellow-bondman of thy brethren who have the testimony of Jesus. Do homage to God. For the spirit of prophecy is the testimony of Jesus.

11 And I saw the heaven opened, and behold, a white horse, and one sitting on it, called Faithful and True, and he judges and makes war in righteousness. 12 And his eyes are a flame of fire, and upon his head many diadems, having a name written which no one knows but himself; 13 and he is clothed with a garment dipped in blood; and his name is called The Word of God. 14 And the armies which are in the heaven followed him upon white horses, clad in white, pure, fine linen. 15 And out of his mouth goes a sharp two-edged sword, that with it he might smite the nations; and he shall shepherd them with an iron rod; and he treads the wine-press of the fury of the wrath of God the Almighty. 16 And he has upon his garment, and upon his thigh, a name written, King of kings, and Lord of lords. 17 And I saw an angel standing in the sun; and he cried with a loud voice, saying to all the birds that fly in mid-heaven, Come, gather yourselves to the great supper of God, 18 that ye may eat flesh of kings, and flesh of chiliarchs, and flesh of strong men, and flesh of horses and of those that sit upon them, and flesh of all, both free and bond, and small and great. 19 And I saw the beast and the kings of the earth and their armies gathered together to make war against him that sat upon the horse, and against his army. 20 And the beast was taken, and the false prophet that was with him, who wrought the signs before him by which he deceived them that received the mark of the beast, and those that worship his image. Alive were both cast into the lake of fire which burns with brimstone; 21 and the rest were slain with the sword of him that sat upon the horse, which goes out of his mouth; and all the birds were filled with their flesh.

Revelation 22

1 And he shewed me a river of water of life, bright as crystal, going out of the throne of God and of the Lamb. 2 In the midst of its street, and of the river, on this side and on that side, the tree of life, producing twelve fruits, in each month yielding its fruit; and the leaves of the tree for healing of the nations. 3 And no curse shall be any more; and the throne of God and of the Lamb shall be in it; and his servants shall serve him, 4 and they shall see his face; and his name is on their foreheads. 5 And night shall not be any more, and no need of a lamp, and light of the sun; for the Lord God shall shine upon them, and they shall reign to the ages of ages.

6 And he said to me, These words are faithful and true; and the Lord God of the spirits of the prophets has sent his angel to shew to his bondmen the things which must soon come to pass. 7 And behold, I come quickly. Blessed is he who keeps the words of the prophecy of this book. 8 And I, John, was he who heard and saw these things. And when I heard and saw, I fell down to do homage before the feet of the angel who shewed me these things. 9 And he says to me, See thou do it not. I am thy fellow-bondman, and the fellow-bondman of thy brethren the prophets, and of those who keep the words of this book. Do homage to God. 10 And he says to me, Seal not the words of the prophecy of this book. The time is near. 11 Let him that does unrighteously do unrighteously still; and let the filthy make himself filthy still; and let him that is righteous practise righteousness still; and he that is holy, let him be sanctified still. 12 Behold, I come quickly, and my reward with me, to render to every one as his work shall be. 13 I am the Alpha and the Omega, the first and the last, the beginning and the end. 14 Blessed are they that wash their robes, that they may have right to the tree of life, and that they should go in by the gates into the city. 15 Without are the dogs, and the sorcerers, and the fornicators, and the murderers, and the idolaters, and every one that loves and makes a lie. 16 I Jesus have sent mine angel to testify these things to you in the assemblies. I am the root and offspring of David, the bright and morning star. 17 And the Spirit and the bride say, Come. And let him that hears say, Come. And let him that is athirst come; he that will, let him take the water of life freely. 18 I testify to every one who hears the words of the prophecy of this book, If any one shall add to these things, God shall add to him the plagues which are written in this book. 19 And if any one take from the words of the book of this prophecy, God shall take away his part from the tree of life, and out of the holy city, which are written in this book.

20 He that testifies these things says, Yea, I come quickly. Amen; come, Lord Jesus. 21 The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with all the saints.